Now, we'll look at red black BSTs which is
a simple data structure that allows us to
implement 2-3 tree with very little extra
code beyond the basic binary search tree
code. So this is, and actually the version
that we're going to, looking at is called
left-leaning red-black BSTs. On a personal
note, I wrote a research paper on this
topic in 1979 with Leo Givas and we
thought we pretty well understood these
data structures at that time and people
around the world use them in implementing
various different systems. But just a few
years ago for this course I found a much
simpler implementation of red-black trees
and this is just the a case study showing
that there are simple algorithms still out
there waiting to be discovered and this is
one of them that we're going to talk
about. So, the idea is that we are, are
going to represent every two, three tree
as a binary search tree. And in order to
get that done, we just need a simple
representation for three notes. So, what
we are going to do is use internal
left-leaning links to glue the three nodes
together. So, the larger of the two nodes
in the tree node will always be the root
of a little binary search tree of size two
for the three node and the link between
the two nodes, the left link that links
the larger key to the smaller one we'll
color red. And that's to distinguish those
links from the other links in the binary
tree so that we can tell when we're
inserting things which nodes belong to
tree nodes and which ones don't. And you
can see from this transformation that it's
easy to perform this, see this
correspondence the middle link between A
and B, those are the keys that are less
than B and larger than A. So, that takes
two comparisons to get to them the ones
that are less than A, less than, less than
A, that's two comparisons for that and the
ones that are greater than B are the right
link of B. So, just following those three
cases, I see t hat this correspondence is
going to work. So, any 2-3 tree
corresponds to a left leaning red-black
BST in this way. Just take the three nodes
and split them into little binary search
tree of size two held together by a red
link. And correspondingly given a
red-black BST then you can get the 2-3
tree if you wanted it. But just look at
the properties of looking at the
properties over a left leaning red-black
BST. You know, with reference to what we
know about 2-3 trees. First of all no node
has two red links connected to it cuz the
only red links are internal to three
nodes. And those have to have ex, external
links or tree links connecting them to
some other node. Every path from the root
down to a null link has the same number of
black links that just follows directly
from the corresponding property for 2-3
trees. A left-leaning red-black BST has
perfect black balance. And all the red
links lean left. So, given a BST with some
of the links colored red that has those
properties that's going to correspond to a
2-3 tree. And that's a key property is
this one-to-one correspondence between 2-3
trees and left-leaning red-black trees.
Given a 2-3 tree, we saw how to do it.
Given a, a, given a red-black tree, we
just make the red links horizontal, and
merge the nodes together to be three
nodes. So, all of the operations that
we're going to look at for red-black trees
can be understood in terms of the
corresponding operations on 2-3 trees. Now
the first, and really one of the most
critical observations, is that search in a
red-black BST is exactly the same as for
an elementary BST, we just ignore the
color. Now, it's going to be much faster
because of better balance in the tree, but
in terms of the code, we don't have to
change the code at all. Our regular search
code doesn't examine the color of a link
and so we can just use it exactly as is.
And in fact, most of the other operations
that we implemented on BSTs are also
identical. They d on't need the colors,
but they can all benefit from the fact
that the trees are much better balanced.
So this aspect of red-black BSTs is an
extremely nice one because of the
operations that we implemented for regular
BSTs that involves some complicated code
for floor and ceiling and rank and so
forth, and we don't have to change that
code at all. We just during the insertion,
make sure that we, we [cough] maintain the
properties the balance properties and by
doing that, we wind up with balance trees
and we make all the operations quick and
we don't have to re-implement, we don't
have to change it at all. So first before
we get to the code for insertion, we have
to look at the representation. We don't
actually have explicit representation of
links or links in trees or just references
to nodes. You could implement this by
building explicit links but the an easier
thing to do is to know that every node is
referenced by just one link in a tree the
one from it's parent. So, you can put the
color of a link in the node that it
references. So, in this case we have a red
link connecting E and C. What we do is put
a bit, a color bit in each in the node
class. And then, if the link coming into a
node is red we set that to true. So this
simple thing just tests is a node red. We
consider all null nodes to be black null
links to be black, we don't have red links
dangling off, that would be incomplete
pre-nodes. And [cough] otherwise if the
color's red, we return true otherwise
return false to test whether a node is
red. So in this tree, the color of h.left
is red, the color of h.right is black and
so forth. So, that's the way we represent
colors by putting the, a color bit in the
node for the color of the length that
points to it. [cough] Alright, so now,
there's a couple of elementary operations
that we have to perform on red-black
trees, called rotations. And the idea is
that during the construction of a tree, or
during an insertion operation, sometimes
we wind up with red links that are leaning
in the wrong direction. And so we'll need
what's called a left rotation, and the job
of that operation is to take a, a right
leaning red link that is there for
whatever reason and reorient it to lean to
the left. [cough] so, in this case, we
have the right link of E points to S and S
is red so that's a right-leaning red link
and so now that's the before and what we
want to do is reorient things so that it
leans to the left. And again, that has to
be a local operation that only changes a
few links and just from the diagram it's
not difficult to see that this little bit
of code will do the job. If we start with
a right-leaning red link. So, first thing
we do is take the reference of h.right,
and save that in x. So, that's the node
that's going to be the new root of the
three nodes so to speak. And, and then,
x.left after the rotation is going to be
h. And also whatever color h was, well, it
looks like it should be black. But
actually this situation is where it could
be red. Then x is going to have that color
cuz the link coming into h is going to be
the link coming into x. And then h's color
is going to be black afterwards. And then,
we return x to link further up the tree
which happens during our standard
recursive insert. So, that's a rotate left
operation. Now, the property of this
operation that's very important is it
maintains a symmetric order. The keys
between E and S are still there. We just
changed the way we get to them. And the
keys less than E and so forth. And also we
maintain perfect black balance because we
didn't change the black height, height of
anything by doing this transformation. All
those subtrees, those three subtrees are
exactly the same relative to the top and
bottom of the tree, as they were before
the rotation. Now paradoxically and you'll
see why very soon it also turns out that
to get the insertion done properly we
sometimes need to take a left-leaning red
link and temporarily make it lean right.
And later on, we'll get it back to the
left again. But anyway, that's a basic
operation that we sometimes need. And so
that's just the symmetric code to the code
that we just did. Now again, now x is
h.left. And h.left is going to be x.right
after the rotation. X's color is still
going to be h's color. And h's color is
going to be red. And the right rotation
implements this and again that's going to
maintain a, a symmetric order in perfect
black balance we change the way the red
goes but we didn't change anything about
the black. Okay, that's a right rotation.
Now, here's the third elementary operation
that we're going to perform. It's called a
color flip. Sometimes during the
insertion, we might wind up with a node
that's got two red links coming out of it.
That's corresponds precisely to our
temporary four node when we're doing 2-3
trees. And what we wanted to do with the
temporary four node was to split it and
pass the center node up to the root. Well,
you can see from this structure that we're
all set to do that all we need to do
actually is not change any links, just
change all the colors. And so, that is, we
change the link from E to A and from E to
S to be black. That essentially splits the
four node. And then, we want to insert the
E into its parent. And we just do that by
changing its link to be red. So, that's
flipping the colors. And that's the way we
split a temporary four node in a
left-linear red-black tree. And again,
that's just flipping colors. It doesn't
change any links so it still, of course,
maintains symmetric order and perfect
black balance. So, those are the three
basic operations we're going to use.
Rotate left, rotate right and flip colors.
So, the basic s trategy is, with those
operations, maintain one-to-one
correspondence with 2-3 trees when we do
insertions. So, here's an example. If we
want to insert C into this red black tree
which is a representation of this 2-3
tree, then C is going to be less than E
greater than A. So, it will get added to,
as the right link of A and every time we
add a node we just create a red link to
its parents and so, that's changing the
two node into a three node. In this case
it's three nodes that's oriented the wrong
way so we need to do a left rotate. After
we do the left rotate, we have a legal
left-leaning red-black tree, and it
exactly corresponds to that 2-3 tree, so
the insertion of C gives us exactly what
we would want, that correspondence with
the 2-3 tree. We have to work through
other cases that can arise but there's not
too many so we'll work through and we have
the basic operations, left rotate, right
rotate, and flip colors. Alright, so
first, warm up, insert into a tree with
exactly one node. Well, if it goes on the
left, then we just make a red link and add
it on then we're done. If it goes on the
right, then we attach a new node with the
red link on the right but we have to
rotate it to the left to make a legal
three node. So, that's inserting to a tree
with the one node and make it a tree with
two nodes. And that one generalizes to
help us insert into a two node at the
bottom. So, we do the standard BST insert
color the new link red and then if that
[cough] new three node happens to lean
right, rotated to the left. That's the
case that we just did. So now, let's look
at the second warm-up. So, say, we have
just two nodes in the tree, so it's we
have two nodes and that means it's a
single three node. Then there's three
cases. So, one is that the new one is
larger than both of the keys. If that's
true, then we attach the new node with the
red link as always. And that gives us a
temporary four node. And what we want to
do is split that four node and in this
case, since we are at the root that's all
so that just flips the colors. Now, the
color of the root in our code will
temporarily turn red and then we turn it
black again. So, that's inserting into a
tree that's a single three node a node
that's larger than both of them, a key
that is larger than both of them and we
get wind up with a four node. Well, let's
look at the other two cases and these
understanding needs is crucial to
understanding the whole algorithm. Let's
say, the new key is smaller than both of
the keys in our three node. Now, we attach
a new link at the left of the smaller
node. And now, we've gotta find BST. But
it has two red links in a row. And that's
something that's not allowed. So, what
we're going to do is we're going to rotate
the top link to the right. So that puts B
at the root. And now, it's got two red
children. It reduces to this case. And we
flip the colors and we have a single four
node. Sorry a, a red black. A tree that's
got three two-nodes and no red links so
same situation as before. So, we had a
single temporary four note and we split it
up into a two, two note not connected to a
four note. And then, so that's the case
when it's smaller. Now, we have to look at
the third case, which is, when it's, the
new node inserted this in between and
comes out of this link here. Again, we
just had a red link and now we have a BST
with two red links along the path
connected to A and that's not allowed. In
this case it's a bit trickier to affix the
situation, what we do is we rotate the
bottom link left. So, and that gives us
this and reduce it to the other situation
that we had before. And then we rotate the
top link right and then, we flip the
colors. So, this one we used all three of
our operations, rotate left rotate right
and flip the colors. And that gets us an
insertion into a tree that has from a tree
that i s a single three node to a tree
that is three two nodes that is containing
three keys. So that sort of operation is
going to work in a big tree when we insert
into a new three node at the bottom. We do
the standard BST insert, color the new
link red, and we do the rotations that we
need, either one or two rotations to
balance the temporary four node, and then
we flip colors to pass the red link up one
level and then remind me to rotate to that
to make that one lean left. So, for
example if we insert h in to this tree
here, it comes off as the left link of R
so that gives us a temporary four node
that's not balanced so we need to rotate
the link from S to the right and that
gives us now temporary four node that is
balanced and again, these are all local
transformation it's not changing the rest
of the tree. Now, we flip colors and that
gives us a, a good red-black tree, except
that, that one red link that we just is
leaning the wrong way. So, now we need to
rotate left and then once we've done that,
now we have a legal left-leaning red-black
tree. So [cough] that's a insertion into a
three node at the bottom. So, here's
another one that involves, remember, we
passed that red link up. There might, if
that gets passed up to a three node, then
we have to continue moving up the tree and
just treat it in the same way as we just
treated inserting at the bottom. We have a
new red link appearing into some three
node. There's the three cases that could
happen and here's an, an a, an example.
So, say, we're inserting P into this
left-leaning red black tree it goes to the
right event so we get a temporary four
node that's got two red links both
children are red in that thing so we want
to flip the colors. We flipped the colors
and now our temporary 4-node is up higher
in the tree but it's not balanced so we
are going to have to do two rotations to
make that balanced. First one is to make
the bottom link left-leaning and then the
second one is to make the top link
right-leaning so that we can have the
temporary four node balance. And then the
last thing we do is flip the colors and
now that's the result of that insertion.
It's a bunch of transformations but
they're all simple using our flip colors
or left or right rotation. And [cough]
that one happened to be at the root. If
that red link were, were way down in the
tree and there were another three node
about it, we might have to do it again.
Again, exactly as what would happen in a
2-3 tree. So, let's do a demo of
constructing the red-black BST from our
standard set of keys. So, we start with a
single key. Now, if we want to insert E,
if it goes to the left, that's fine.
That's a legal left-leaning red-black
tree. A would go to the left of E two
lefts in a row so we have to rotate that
to right. And then we have to flip the
colors. And that's a legal red-black BST.
So now, if we insert R into this one then
it goes on a red link to the left of X, S
and that's fine, it's a red-black BST. And
now, if we insert C into this one, it goes
less than E, greater than A it's a red
link connecting A and C but it's leaning
the wrong way. So, we have to do a left
rotation, legal-red black BST. And you
want to insert h that goes to the left of
R, two reds in a row, rotate the top.
Rotate the top, our temporary four node is
balanced, flip colors. Now, we have a
three node, but the red link is leaning
right so we have to rotate. And now, we
have a legal red-block BST. Insert x into
that one that goes to the right of S, it's
leaning the wrong way, rotate left. Insert
M into this one, goes to the right of h,
leaning the wrong way, rotate left. Most
of the operations are simple ones like
this happening at the bottom. Insert P,
that goes to the right of M that makes M a
temporary four node that happens to be
balanced, so flip the colors. Flip the
colors, now we h ave a temporary four node
that's out of balance so we need a double
rotation. First rotate E to make that link
point lean to the left, then rotate R to
make the, bring the temporary four node
into balance. And then, flip the colors
and that's a legal red-black BST. Insert L
into that one. It goes to the right of H,
leading the wrong way rotate left. [cough]
And that's an example of building a
red-black BST from our standard set of
keys. Now, we're ready to look at the
implementation for, of the code for
inserting into a left-leaning red-black
tree. And the key to understanding this
code is to realize that the same code,
code handles all of the cases. And the way
that it works is we are always reducing
one case to another. We get this most
complicated case we did a left rotate on
the bottom node and that, that transformed
it to this case where they're both leaning
left. And then we did a right rotate on
the top node, and that transformed to the
case where our temporary four node is
balanced. And then we flipped colors on
that. So, for a particular insertion, we
can take advantage of this reduce one case
to another by, in, in the way that we're
moving in the tree, not to get everything
happen with just a, a few extra lines of
code in our standard binary search tree.
So, in gray is our, standard insertion
code for binary search trees. And remember
we took some pains to think about the
recursive implementation where when we go
down a link we replace that link by
whatever the recursive routine gives us
back and that strategy is going to pay off
in giving us a really simple code. [cough]
and because in this implementation for
left-leaning red-black trees we're going
to return the link whenever we're done,
and then that will get that link installed
up in the node above whether it be left or
right. Typical implementations of
red-black trees that do not use this
recursive strategy wind u p having lots of
cases depending on whether left or right
or double rotate to the left or double
rotate to the right can be critical of
this code because my own was this way for
the first three editions of the book. And
it's only in this edition that we figured
out how to make the code this simple.
Okay. So what are the things left to be
done? Let's just check. When we insert a
new node all we want to do is create a new
node with the, I've given, associating the
given value with a given key, as before
but now we just make that node red. So,
that's adding a new node with a red link
at the bottom inserting that into whatever
the two or three node it's attached to.
And then we do the comparisons as, as
before and that, and that's all fine. Now,
when it's returned then that's the point
at which we're going to check whether the
left, the links are leaning to the left as
they are suppose to and whether or not
there are any double links or not. So the
first thing is if, if is red h.right and
not is red h.left? So, that means H is
h.right is red so that means the right
link of H is leaning the wrong way. So, H
is a three node leaning the wrong way. So
we just rotate left H. So, whenever we
find a right link, we're sitting on a
right red link we just rotate it left and
return that. So, that would be in this
case here, we'd rotate it left and reduce
it to that one. [cough] or in, in you
know, in the case when we're just
inserting a new node and it's turns out to
be the right red link attached to a black
one, if that handles that case. Now, if
h.left is red and h.left is also red
that's this case here where we have two
left-leaning red links. And then in that
case, we just rotate the top one right and
that brings us to this one. So, notice,
we're in this case we do this rotation
first, we're on this node and then , that
returns and we come up to deal with the
situation on this node after the return,
and then we do that rotation. And then
after that rotation, or if there were no
rotations at all, if the insertion
happened over here then we'd test and flip
the colors. It's a little mind bending at
first because of the recursive structure
but it won't take you long to convince
yourself that this little bit of extra
code completes the implementation of
left-leaning red-black trees. It's quite
remarkable, actually. So, let's look at a
visualization. Watching the [unknown],
this is a balanced tree getting
constructed in the worst case where
everything that comes in is in ascending
order. A regular binary search tree will
just be all strung out in a single line
and wouldn't have quadratic time for this
input but a left-leaning red-black tree
actually when, whenever it becomes a power
of two is completely balanced as you can
see from this example. Even though they
came in, in ascending order, the tree
winds up being perfectly balanced. And
what about descending order. Well, it's
left leaning and the process is a little
bit different and sometimes the left path
can get long but not that long. The worse
that can happen is that it alternates red
and black. And then after it gets to that
worse case it also winds up being
completely balanced when we have a power
of two. Interesting to think just, just
about this case and to prove to yourself
that it's always going to be perfectly
balanced when it's descending. And this is
just for random insertions. The tree stays
very balanced. It's guaranteed that the
longest path which is alternating red and
black can be no more than twice as long as
the shortest path which is all blacks. And
so in this case the longest path is ten
and the average path is seven for 255.
Very close to log based two of N. So easy
to prove by correspondence with 2-3 trees
that t he height is guaranteed to be less
than two log base two N. Every search in
left-leaning red black three is guaranteed
to take less than two log base two of N
cuz every path gets the same number of
black links so you never have two red
links in a row. [cough] And actually, in
typical applications with any kind of
randomness or even if there is a lot of
order its difficult to find situations
orders of keys that build the trace of
height is bigger than actually one log N
in, in a real application, its very close
to fully balanced all the time. So, that
completes our summary for a symbol table
implementations with red-black BSTs. We
have full code it's the regular BST code
with the couple of lines adding the calls
and the basic operations. She rotate
right, rotate left. In color flip, we
could guarantee logarithmic performance
not just research, insert, in delete code.
Delete code is a bit more complicated but
it's on the book side and in the book. But
also, since it's the compare-to interface,
and since it's a binary tree
representation all the other comparable
operations extended operations for ordered
symbol tables are going to be implemented
and take time proportional to the log N. A
lot of people ask why use the name
red-black. Well we invented this data
structure this way of looking at balance
trees at, at Xerox PARC which was the home
of the personal computer and many other
innovations that we live with today
entering graphic user interface and
internet and object oriented programmings
and many other things. But one of the
things that was invented there, was the
laser printing and we were very excited to
have nearby color laser printer that could
print things out in color and out of the
colors, the red looked the best. So,
that's why we picked the color red to
distinguish red links the types of links
in three nodes. So, that's an answer to
the question for people t hat have been
asking. Now, here's another war story
about red-black BSTs. As I mentioned
they're widely used. And there was an
example not that long ago, where a
telephone company contracted with a
database provider to build a database that
could store customer information and the
provider implemented the database using
red-black BSTs for search and insert. Now,
our, our original paper on red black trees
was the way the paper was laid out, it
turned out that the delete implementation
happened to be placed after all the
references. So, a lot of people didn't see
the delete implementation. And also we
didn't have the simple left-leaning
representation. So it was more complicated
and involved a lot more cases and so
usually not all the cases were put in the
text books. So, people found deletion more
difficult. In fact, that's what lead to
[unknown] analyze the situation then come
up with a left-leaning variant. So, what
they did in this implementation was they
just put in regular Hibbard deletion in
the binary search in the red-black BST.
Not the deletion algorithm that's
guaranteed to keep the constant black
height all the time. And so but, but they
still thought that it should be balanced
and it shouldn't matter much. And they had
a complex error recovery process that,
that got triggered if the height limit got
too big. And they rebuild the whole tree
and, and then because of the way they did
this deletion, well, the end of the story
was that they had extended the client had
extended outage because the implementer
didn't use the full algorithm. And there
was a lawsuit and some legal testimony and
I am happy to report that, that it was
clear that Hibbard deletion was the
problem once the expert analyzed it and
the expert witness, who's a colleague of
mine, said if implemented properly, the
height of a red-black BST with N keys is
at most two log N. And so that's the st
ory of red-black BST's guaranteed
logarithmic performance for all symbol
table operations.