Welcome back. Today, we're gonna take a
look at a number of interesting
applications of symbol tables and the
binary search tree data structure to
address problems with processing geometric
data. So let's take a look at it. The idea
is that we're gonna be talking about
geometric objects, not simple keys like
strings and numbers. So here's an example.
So say your geometric objects are points
in the plane and you specify a rectangle
that's oriented with the
horizontal/vertical axes. And you might
wanna ask, which points are inside the
rectangle or how many points are inside
the rectangle? Or maybe what you are
processing is rectangles. You have a set
of rectangles, and we want to know which
of these rectangles intersect? Or how many
rectangles intersections are there? These
are interesting problems that have lots
and lots of applications, from
computerated design, to games and movies
and also in abstractions such as data
bases and other situations where you might
have multiple keys or multiple dimensions.
And it's a very interesting extension of
the ideas that we've looked at for symbol
tables for all sorts of familiar
applications. And, surprisingly binary
search trees and these associated
algorithms that we've looked at are going
to provide very efficient solutions to a
number of important problems in this area.
And really have enabled a new developments
and new technology in all of these kinds
of applications. So, to get started, we're
going to look at a simple problem called
one-dimensional range search. And it
really forms the basis for what we're
going to do. It's a little bit of an
extension of the ordered symbol table API
that we gave before and we're going to
have operations range-search and
range-count. So, a one-dimensional just
means we have one key, so we'll insert a
key value pairs before and what we want to
do is to be able to search for a key, and
a value associated with it, want to b e
able to delete. But then we want these
operations range-search and range-count.
So, find all the keys that are between two
given keys, or give how many keys are
there between two given keys. So, for this
example at right we have insert a number
of keys and, and we're just showing them
in sorted order. But then, you might say,
well, how many keys are there that are
between g and k? In this case, there's
just two. And then the client might say,
well, what are those keys and you want to
be able to return them. And this is a very
common operation, say, in databases. You
want to return how many taxpayers have
salaries between one million and ten
million and then which ones are they and
so forth. So, range searching is a very
important fundamental operation. Now, in
geometric interpretation, we just think
that the keys as points on a line. And so,
the key values well, are just specified as
points on a line. We might convert the
letters to numbers, or we might, keys
might be numbers. And then, what we're
looking for is to find or count the points
in a given interval in one dimension. So
how we're going ti implement that? Well
this is the basic problem that is very
similar to our symbol table problem. We
might consider keeping the things in an
unordered array. Just put them in an
array, and then, well, insertion is, is
fast. We just add it to the end of the
array. We might have to use resizing to
make the array grow. But this is
unattractive because for large numbers of
keys, in order to count the keys that fall
within a given range, you have to go
through all the keys and test whether
they're in the range or not and to return
them the same way. So take linear time for
large number of keys. If you keep the
things in order like in a binary search
situation then to insert in order to keep
it in order in an array, you might need to
move the larger ones over one pos ition
and so forth or elementary implementation
of binary search when we did symbol tables
did this. So, the insertion time might be
linear, but then you can use binary
search, to look for the two endpoints,
that's only going to take time
proportional to log in. And then from
that, you can figure out how many keys
there are or return them all between the
index, the lowest one in the range, index
the highest one in the range. So, those
elementary implementations are no
acceptable for a large numbers of keys cuz
they have the linear time operation. So,
what we really want is to have time
proportional to log in. For insert and,
and for counting. For range search, of
course, we, we have to touch every key
that we return, so the running time is
going to be proportional to the number of
keys that match. But anyway, those are
reasonable goals. And they're easy to
achieve. So [cough] so, for example what
about one-dimensional range counting?
Well, what we're going to do is just keep
the keys in a binary search tree and we
looked at the implementation of the rank
function for binary search trees where for
every key, we can compute how many keys
are there that are strictly less than that
key. So in this case, the rank of e is two
and h is three and so forth. So, in a
binary search tree, those rank numbers go
in an increasing order as we do in an
ordered traversal and that's easy to
compute. You need to keep that rank tree
as a field, or keep a field which has the
size of the tree and it's easy to complete
the rank from that. So how many keys
between, say e and s? Well one, two,
three, four, five. It's actually just the
difference between the ranks plus one if
the high [cough] entry in the range query
is in the table and not +one over. So,
there's the same number of keys between e
and s as there are between e and t five.
Between f and t, there's only f our. So,
that's a, a really 1d range count is a
very easy computation to perform in, in
log time with a binary search tree. The
[cough] number of nodes examined when we
do a search is the length of the search
path to low plus the length of the search
path to high to [cough] find their ranks
and that's going to be time proportional
to log N. [cough]. So and a range search.
Well, we just do a recursive search and to
find all the keys between low and high you
look in the left subtree if any of them
could fall in the range. You look at the
current node and you look at the right
subtree, if any of them could fall in the
range. And it's easy to tell whether any
of them could fall in the range by just
checking whether they're range overlaps
the root or not. So, if we are looking for
all the keys between f and t then we have
to look at both the subtrees of the root
s. But we don't to look at the left
subtree of e because all of those are less
than e and therefore are less than f. So,
we don't have to have to look there. But
otherwise, it's a simple modification of
recursive tree search to find all the keys
and it's easy to see the running time to
that is going to be proportional to the
number of keys returned plus log N. So,
that's one dimensional range search using
binary search trees.