To finish up, we're going to look at the
rectangle intersection problem that's got
important practical applications and, uses
the techniques that we've been studying so
far. And it's a simple generalization of
our line intersection problem. So now, we
have a bunch of rectangles. They're all
oriented horizontal or vertical. And what
we need to do is find all the
intersections in that set of rectangles.
And again N could be huge in applications,
as we'll talk about in a second. And the
[cough] Naive Brute-Force Algorithm
involves checking each pair of rectangles
for intersection. And what we want is a
more efficient algorithm than that as
usual. And again, to keep the code simple
we're going to assume that all the
coordinates are distinct. We don't have
any, any equal lines that we have to worry
about whether we consider rectangles that
touch to be intersecting, and so forth. So
that's, that's the problem, rectangle
intersection search. This is historically,
an extremely, important problem. In the
1970s, when we switched to very large
scale integration for computers, we were
switching from a situation where we were
wiring physical devices together, to a
situation where we were essentially
drawing the computer. And there were
machines that would take drawings and, and
return, [cough] and from those drawings,
like this, make, physical things that
implemented computers with different
layers and different, physical materials
interacting, in different ways. Some
things are wires, and some things are
switches that, are used to, implement
memory bits and computer logic. But the
key point about it is that designing a
computer became a geometric problem. And
so, people, to design new computers,
would, make huge drawings that just showed
the lines that corresponded to the
materials that had to be created to make
the computer. Now, it was very expensive.
You didn't want to have any bugs when
you're making a chip. And, there were
various rules about what you can do on
these drawings. And basically, these rules
had to do with doing this ortho,
orthogonal rectangle intersection search.
You, you can't have [cough] lines that
come too close to other lines, certain
types of lines can't intersect. Need
spacing between certain types of wires
and, you wanted to, before you tried to
make the physical circuit to do this
checking, which involved this orthogonal
rectangle intersection sort. And it was
actually the case that the progress of
faster and faster processors with more and
more components was slowed because people
were using the naive quadratic algorithm
to do this design rule checking. And its
example of, of Moore's law. So, as we
built a faster computer say, in 1970X, we
needed to check in rectangles. But now,
maybe a year and a half later, you have a
computer that's two times faster but you
also want to build a bigger computer so
you have twice as many rectangles to
check. So you have two end rectangles to
check now, and your computer's twice as
fast. So, we get to use the faster and
bigger computer to build faster and bigger
circuits but that doesn't help if you're
using a quadratic algorithm. If you're
using a quadratic algorithm and it takes
you n days to check your design rules, and
people were running these things on the
order of days, then for the next computer,
it would take 2n days, it would take twice
as long. And so people that were using
quadratic algorithms were definitely held
back and, it was, Ed, Ed McCreight at
Xerox Park who, discovered interval search
trees and the logarithmic algorithm that
allowed us to sustain Moore's law and keep
building bigger and bigger computers. By
changing this quadratic algorithm to a
linear logarithmic algorithm, and let's
see how it works. Really, it's a
modification of the sweep line algorithm
that we looked at for intersecting lines.
But now we're going to use that for
intersecting rectangles rather than using
range search as our basic operation, we're
going to use interval search. So now,
every time the line sweep hits a
rectangle, that corresponds to an
interval. If it's the left part of a
rectangle, then we put that interval into
our interval search tree. So in this case
we put on zero and then we put on one and
then we put on two. And, and that will
give us now three rectangles on our sweep
line. And so now, the question is when we
hit a, a new rectangle, we want to do an
interval search to, if we're at the left
to check which ones intersect and the
interval search tree algorithm is going to
tell us which intersections there are
right away. When we reach the right then
we remove intervals and so forth. But with
the basic interval search tree algorithm
and the sweep line process that we've
talked about, you can get the orthogonal,
orthogonal rectangle intersection search
problem solved in time proportional to
analog N log N + R log N, where R is the
number of intersections. And typically, in
design rule checking, you wouldn't expect
too many intersections. So again, just as
with, line intersection search, using a
priority queue or a sort is only N log N
for processing the X coordinates. And
because the interval search trees take log
N for every operation, the insert and
delete intervals is N log N totaled and
the searches is N log N + R log N. So, the
bottom line is that the sweep line
algorithm takes this rectangle
intersection problem and reduces it to 1D
interval search and we have an efficient
algorithm for that problem and that
enables us to solve the problem in linear
rhythmic time instead of quadratic time.
And that definitely enabled new progress
in technology and it's a fine example of
the importance of algorithmic technology.
So here's our summary of applications of
binary search trees for geometric
problems. We started with one dimensional
range search and just used regular binary
search tree to compute ranks to get the
answer. But that as the basis, we're able
to solve the two dimensional line segment
intersection search using the sweep line
algorithm. Then we looked at range search
and other operations using KD trees.
Again, modification of binary search
trees. And then the interval search tree
to solve the one dimensional N over search
problem and then how that corresponds to
the basic algorithm that you get to if you
use the sweep line algorithm to solve
rectangle intersection. Many of these
problems are the basis for geometric
processing of huge amounts of data that we
see all over the web. And our basic search
tree mentality and APIs, and binary search
tree data structure give us efficient
solutions to these important practical
problems.