So now let's look at a basic geometric
data processing problem of determining
intersections among a set of line
segments. So, it's called the orthogonal
line segment, segment intersection search
where the lines segments or constrained to
be either horizontal or vertical. And so,
suppose we have a large number of such
line segments and what we want to be able
to do is to find all places where they
intersect. And as we'll see this extends
to a practical problem in a number of
situations. So, in this case there's four
places where these lines intersect. So,
how are we going to be able to determine
these intersections efficiently? Now, the
natural algorithm, or the naive
brute-force algorithm, is quadratic in
time. So that is, for every line segment,
you check whether it intersects with every
other line segment. And again, as we know,
such an algorithm is not going to be
practical, for huge numbers of line
segments. So, just, to simplify our code
in the slides in it's off, off from the
case for geometric data processing. We
don't have to worry about degeneracies
where lots of things have the same x or y
coordinate. And just to simplify the code
and to get it the main principles of the
algorithms, we're going to assume that all
the coordinates that we have are distinct
that we've preprocessed in some way to
remove the ones that touch without
intersecting. So the method that we're
going to look at is a so called Sweep Line
algorithm and the idea is to think of
vertical line that sweeps left to right
through the data. In to. Consider it as a
every time it hits some line segment as an
event where we have to do something. So
sweeping from left to right means we
consider each x coordinate as an event. So
first thing is if we hit a horizontal line
segment. Well we're going to hit the left
endpoint first, and so what we'll do when
we hit the left, endpoint is, insert, the
y coordinate of that line into a binary
search tree. So, we're going to keep track
of y coordinates in a binary search tree.
So that's what's happening over in the
right there. So now again, sweep from left
to right. What's the next smallest x
coordinate? In this case it's the line
number one there, and we'll remember its y
coordinate in a binary search tree. And
then two and three. So those that's one
kind of event that can happen as we sweep
from left to right. Another kind of event
is that we hit the right endpoint of a
horizontal line segment. In this case we
hit the right endpoint of line segment
two. So, at that point the right point of
a horizontal line segment we just remove
it because we've processed that line
completely. In this case we didn't find
any intersections. So, left endpoint
insert the y coordinate into a BST, right
endpoint remove that ycoordinate from the
BST. So, the BST contains the y
coordinates of all the horizontal lines
that currently might involve an
intersection. And then the third kind of
event is what happens when we hit a
vertical line segment? Well, in that case
all we want, need to do is just do a range
search, for the interval of y end points.
So, any point that's inside that interval,
is going to represent a horizontal line
segment that is an intersection. That's
the basic idea behind the sweep line
algorithm, to find intersections in sets
of horizontal and vertical lines. And it's
actually a very simple algorithm, and it's
very easy to see that the running time is
going to be proportional to N log N plus
the number of intersections returned.
Where there's N horizontal vertical line
segments. And it's, and a couple of ways
to implement it, one thing is you could
sort according to the x coordinates, or
you could just put them all on a priority
queue. And then, so, so that's going to
take N log N for every one of the lines to
process them all either N to build the
priorit y queue and then log N to take the
smallest off each time, or N log N for the
sort. And then putting the y coordinates
into, into a binary search tree is, again,
N log N. And same for deleting. Each point
has to be inserted, deleted. It could be
as many as N in the tree for each one. So
it's a total of N log N. And then the,
range search, in the binary tree, for
each, each one of the range searches. It
might take, log N, it might be as many as
N. And then there's, plus the number of
points return. So, That's a, quick sketch
of the proof of this proposition. And with
that 1D range search, implementation, we
get an efficient N log N, 2D orthogonal,
orthogonal line segment, intersection