Now we're going to look at KD trees, which
is an extension of BSTs that allow us to
do efficient processing of sets of points
in space and it's very flexible and very
useful in lots of applications. So now
we're going to extend the API to talk
about two dimensional keys. So that's
just, you can think of two dimensional
keys as, points in the two dimensional
geometric space. So we're going to talk
about insertion, and search. We won't talk
about deletion and then range search and
range count. So, we want to be able to
insert and delete, points. You can think
of a two dimensional key as a point in two
dimensional space. And we want to be able
to find all keys that lie within a two
dimensional range. That's a rectangle. As
I mentioned at the beginning or count the
number of keys that lie in a two
dimensional range. So again, the geometric
interpretation is the keys or points in
the plane. And we have a, a, a range, 2D
range is a, a rectangle, or is oriented,
to align with the horizontal, vertical
axes. And we want to be able to find or
count the points in a given rectangle. In
this one has many, many applications and
we'll talk about some of them later on.
And even if it's not points in the plane,
just databases you might ask for all the
people with incomes between 1,000,000 and
10,000,000 who are between 40 and 50 years
of age. And this kind of algorithm and
data structure would be useful for that
kind of situation too. So how are we going
to solve this problem, implement this API?
We build a data structure containing
points that can efficiently support range
searching and range counting. Well one
easy way to do it is to just think about
dividing space into a grid of squares. So
we'll pick a parameter M and divide space
into an M by M grid of squares and then
process all the points and make a list of
points that are contained in each square.
We can use a two dimensional array to
directly index, relevant squares. And for
insert, you just, take X, Y. Figure out
which square it belongs to. Simply divide
by, both coor dinates by N, and look into
the two dimensional array. And just add
the point to the list for the
corresponding square. And then range
searches, only find the squares that
intersect the query, and process the
points, in that square. And depending on
the value of the parameter M, you have a
space/time tradeoff. The amount of space
required is M^2 for the grid + N. You have
to have a linked list element, or whatever
for each point. And then the time, though,
gets divided by M^2. Your number of points
and were spread out over the N squared,
different squares. And so on average you
examine N over M^2 points per square. So
you don't want to make M too big that
would be too much space, you don't want to
make M too small that would be too much
time. So what we want to choose is the
square size that would best balance these
two needs and then it is easy to see that
what you should choose is M to be about n
square root of N. So then your space is
within a constant factor of N and your
time is constant. So if the points are
randomly distributed, then this is ideal.
It takes us, linear time to initialize the
data structure. And to insert and search,
it take constant time per point in the
range. And this is absolutely a fine
method that, is not that difficult to
implement, in the case that the points are
evenly distributed. Unfortunately, it's
usually the case that, in geometric data,
that the points are not evenly
distributed. There's a well known
phenomenon known as clustering that says
that, the, the points aren't going to be
evenly distributed all over the whole
thing. In the case of the, the grid
implementation, they might all fall on the
same square. And so, the average list
length is short. This is like what we
encountered with hashing. If you take, all
the points in one square, and zero and all
the rest of them. Your average is still, N
over M squared. But. They are all in that
long list and you're going to have a slow
algorithm if it's, if it's based on this.
So we need a data structure that more
gracefully adapts to the distribution of
the data. And again it, it's well known
that most geometric data has this kind of
problem. So for example here's some data
which cities in the US. It's got 13,000
points, but if you try to use the grid
implementation for this, you'd find that
half the squares would be empty. And half
the points are in just ten percent of the
squares. So, the clustering in the data is
going to make the implementation
inefficient. We need to adapt to the data.
And this is very, very typical, in
geometric data. Particularly, in higher
dimensional data, as we'll see in a
minute. So, people have developed all
different kinds of, methods for, adapting
in this way. And what we're going to look
at is one of the most widely used. Which
is basically to use a tree to represent a
recursive subdivision of the plane, of two
dimensional space. It's going to be
recursive. It's going to be based on the
points the way in which we divide into
half planes. And its one of many different
algorithms that, have been, studied for
this, but again its a simple one and
widely used. So, for example if you played
the game Doom or use the flight simulator,
that, these types of graphical simulations
and animations are made possible only
through the use of space partitioning
trees, like 2d trees and quad trees and
also in all different types of scientific
data processing these things are extremely
important whenever you're processing.
Geometric data, doing some kind of
geometric search. Where is the closest
thing? How am I going to find the closest
thing efficiently? What things are nearby,
and so forth? So, rest assured, these
types of algorithms, lie at the heart of,
any program that you use that, is
involving a lot of geometric data. So,
those are just, two examples. So let's
look at how it looks now. So, a 2D tree,
is, again, it's going to be a data
structure based on a bunch of points
that's going to facilitate, efficient data
processing of these points. So, just as we
do for, symbol tables, where we take,
keys. Now we're going to ta ke points, and
we're going to build a data structure
based on these points. And the idea is to,
build a tree that corresponds to
recursively partitioning the plane. So
arbitrarily our first point we're going to
divide the plane into two parts based on a
vertical line through that point. So now,
in the tree on the right there, all the
points that fall to the left of the first
point are going to be on the left, and all
the points that fall to the right. That
first point, you're going to be on the
right. But then we get to the next point,
we'll switch and we'll partition on a
horizontal line. So now, our second point,
in the tree, the left sub-tree corresponds
to everybody below that horizontal line,
and the right sub-tree corresponds to
everybody above it. Similar if our third
point comes on the left again we'll
partition according to the horizontal line
through that point on the left. So if we
go left and then left that means all the
points to the left of one and above three,
so the square in the upper left is
represented. By, that node in the tree.
And, again. Now, when we go one level
below, we switch again to vertical.
Alternate between horizontal and vertical
partitioning, of the plane. So it's a
regular binary search tree. But it's got
this interpretation based on the geometric
data, where we switch which key we use
for, the comparison, the X coordinate or
the Y coordinate, at each level. And that
corresponds to this partitioning of the
plane. So now five comes in, that's to the
left of four because it was partitioned at
a vertical and five's going to partion on
a horizontal. This is simple, and
completely well defined partion of the
plane corresponding to a binary tree. Now
the ninth point well it's to the left of
eight, above to and to the left of eight
and then corresponds to horizontal
partitioning, tenth point is to the right
of one, it's below two and we go to the
left and it's to the right of seven so we
go to the right. So that's a way to build
a Binary tree corresponding to a
partitioning of the pla ne. And it's
really the same as the binary search tree.
It's just that we alternate which
coordinate we use as the key. At the even
levels, we think of a vertical line. And
the left subtree is all the points to the
left, and the right subtree is all the
points to the right. On odd levels, we use
a horizontal line, in the left subtrees
all points below. In the right subtrees,
all points above. And the, and the code
for this is, you know, the same as for
binary search trees. It's simply, which,
coordinate we use for the comparison.
That's the only difference. So that's 2D
tree implementation. So now what about
solving a problem like this rain search
problem for a 2D tree. So now we have a
query like this green rectangle and what
we want to find is all the points in the
data structure that fall within that
rectangle. Well, we're going to use, the
2D tree represents our points and we are
going to use the structure and definition
of that tree, to go ahead and help us find
the points that are in the rectangle. If,
if the root node lies in the rectangle
then we're done. We can return that, that
point but we have to look on both sides to
look for more, but if the rectangle lies
to the left of the root node then we have
to look at the left and so forth. So let's
look at how this works in the demo. All
right, so, we're going to try to find all
the points that are contained in that
green query rectangle. So first thing is,
to check if our rectangle contains the
node of the root. In this case it doesn't.
So since, it's to the left of the
splitting line of the root we only have to
search in the left sub-tree. Now, we
search the left sub-tree and we're going
to check if it contains.3. It does not
contain.3, but now which, sub-trees do we
search? In this case, now the rectangle
intersects a splitting line, so we have to
search both subtrees, both above and
below. So, first we search the left
subtree that's the one below does it
contain .4? No. It's to the left so we're
going to have to search the left sub-tree
of .4. And so we search the left sub-tree
and we check if it contains point five and
it does, that's the one that we return.
It, it also intersects the splitting
lines, we have to search both the
sub-trees, in this case they're both
empty. So we're done with that but now we
have to go back and we have to search the
other sub-tree of point three and that's
the above, so now we check this .6 in the
rectangle. In this case, it's not. And
it's still a left sway if it's to search
the left sub tree a .6 and that one's
empty and now we return and we're done. So
we don't always go down just one branch if
our splitting line hits a rectangle we
have to go down both branches but still
this is a very efficient algorithm,
particularly think about the rectangle
being small, it's going to be not that
different than a regular search in a
binary search tree. Alright. So what about
the analysis of how long is this going to
take? Well again, a typical case. A
rectangle's small that we're only going to
examine, really, a path of the three,
maybe a couple of other nodes along the
path. And the running time will be
proportional to the number of points
returned plus lg N. With geometric data
the worst case can be bad. So, like all
the points could be arranged in a circle.
All, all different types of problems that
might occur in, with some difficulties.
It's possible to prove, that even if the
tree is balanced, you can get a worst case
proportional to square root of that. So
analysis of 2D trees that the under scope.
But, for many practical applications they
are easily implement and worth using.
Let's look at another using 2D trees to
solve another problem, a so called nearest
neighbor search. So now, instead of a
rectangle, we have a query point. And our
goal is to find the closest point to that
point. So in this case our query point is,
over here in green. And our algorithm's
going to want to return to 0.5. That's the
closest one to the query point. So let's
see how that looks in a demo. So again, we
start at the root. And wh at do we want to
do? Well, we're going to check. And I,
whenever we're at a node, it represents a
point so we're going to check that point
and we'll compute the distance from that
point to our query point. And, if that
distance is less than the best found so
far, then we'll keep that as the champion.
So the first point, that's the closest
we've found so far to the query point. So
we'll say, number one is the distance. And
we'll only worry about the possibility of
finding something closer, than that. And
so just using that distance we recursively
search, any part of the tree that could
contain a closer point. And so that's well
it continued to do so in this case the
query point is to the left of the
splitting line and will always go towards
the query point first and so in this case
we have to search both to see if there
might possibly be a closer point than one
over on the right if you come like
straight across, there might be a closer
point. We're going to have a look at both
as far as we know now but we'll go
towards. The query point and see if we can
find something closer. So in that case now
we go to .3. Compute the distance of that
point to the query point. It's closer so
we update three to be our new champion. So
now we are going to look in parts of the
tree that could give us a point that is
closer to our query point then three. So
already that would mean when we search the
point one we wont search the right sub
tree because there could be no point on
the right sub-tree right of the splitting
line. So lets closer to query point than
three and so that idea getting closer and
closer to the query point is going to cut
out different parts of the tree as we
process so, but anyway starting at point
three as far as we know that we may have
to look at both sub trees, so sometimes
when we look at both sub-trees but as we
get closer and closer we only look at one
so lets look at point three now. So,
again, go towards the query point. So
we'll, go to the top first, and that takes
us to six. Six is not any closer than
three was. So that's not going to, update
our champion. And so we'll search 6's left
sub-tree which is empty which is right
sub-tree and the nearest neighbor can't,
we don't have to go down the right
sub-tree of six because you can't have a
point in that rectangle that's closer to
the query point than three. So now we can
return from that, And now we have to look
at the bottom sub tree associated with
three. And so that takes us to four, And
that one is, not closer. So we still have
three as our current champion. So now,
we'll search the left subtree of four
first because that query point is to the
left of that splitting line. And that
takes us to five and five is our new
champion. So that's the closest point that
we know about. Could there be a node
that's closer to five, to our right query
point than five in the right subtree of
four? Oh. We have to go above. Sorry to
look at the top sub-tree associated with
five, and we find that it's empty. And now
we're back at four. Do we have to search
the right sub-tree of four? No, because
there can't be a closer point, than five
in the right sub-tree of four. So we're
done with four, and we return to, come to
three, and now we search the, suppose to
search and return from there we are now at
one, suppose to search the right subtree
one next but we can term that nearest
neighbor couldn't be in there. So, then we
are done and we found that the nearest
neighbor, is five. And this is going to
be, very efficient because as we get
closer and closer, the query point, we are
cutting out all the subtrees that are
away, and again in practice, the running
time of this algorithm, is going to be
close to logarithmic. So in, in typical
cases that the running time of nearest
neighbor search in a 2D tree is going to
be proportion to logarithmic. It is
possible to concoct cases where you are
going to have to examine all the points
for example if they're all arranged in a
circle and your query points to the center
or something of that sort. But for typical
data it's very efficient. Now we're going
to look at an application where we
simulate a phenomenon in nature. And this
is what kind of patterns do things like
starlings and geese or cranes or, or fish
or fireflies? How do they flock together.
And we'll look at a simulation that
corresponds to that. And then, when the
moment is right, they behave in a way,
that should be impossible. [music] And it
happens everyday, right through the
winter. Just a couple of miles from my
doorstep. Help you desire. >> So to,
there's a simple model developed by Craig
Reynolds awhile ago for simulating this
situation called the boid. And the idea is
to use three simple rules to you get
something very close to this complex
flocking behavior. So, you have col,
collision avoidance where you always try
to point away from the K nearest boids.
You have centering where you try to point
near the center of mass of the K nearest
boids, and velocity matching where you
update your. Philosophy to the average of
the k nearest boids. And that algorithm
works like this. So as that example shows,
2D trees are extremely effective in
quickly processing huge amounts of
geometric data, and what's more, it
expands to more dimensions. With a very
simple modification we can take it to D
tree and created data structure known as a
KD tree, which even works for K dimensions
and the idea is even if there is K
dimension, what we will do is recursively
partition one dimension at a time, so
that's called a KD tree and we use the
same ideas for two D trees, but instead of
cycling through just horizontal vertical,
we cycled through, however many dimensions
there are, so its where in three space, we
use a plane and do above and below and
then simply cycle through the dimensions.
At level I, we put on the left points
whose I-th coordinates are less than P and
on the right, we put the points to whose
I-th coordinates are greater than P and at
level in cycle three of the dimensions at
the level I might k we just use that
dimension of the point to do the
comparison. The implementation is simple,
ex cept for the comparison. And we get the
same kind of partitioning for three
dimensional data, so we could do boids in
three dimensions or for databases with
large number of dimensions. You could do
even much higher dimensional data. And
find nearest neighbors and do range
searching extremely efficiently. It's a
very efficient and simple data structure
for processing K dimensional data that's
very widely used and the whole idea is
that data clusters, particularly, in high
dimensions. And also one point to make for
this class is that, this algorithm was
discovered by an undergraduate in an
algorithms class, so that's, John Bentley,
who discovered this while an undergraduate
at Stanford. And, so it's a simple idea
that, but, experts scientists where
struggling with, dealing with huge amounts
of geometric data, and, Bentley found this
way, to process it efficiently that's been
widely used ever since. And in, in
particular just as another example
consider the idea of N body simulation
which is a classic problem in physics.
Where you've got N particles mutually
affected by gravity and basically the
computation is based on computing the
interacting force for each pair of
particles. And so then there'd be mutual
gravitational pull. [inaudible] and this
is what happens with a large number of
particles in a certain simulation and
people understand properties in the
universe by coming up with, doing these
kinds of calculations and comparing
against what's observed in space. Now but
the thing is for each pair of particles,
so if you have M particles and you have to
do it for each pair, that's M^2 so the
progress of scientific investigation is
going to be affected by how quickly, you
can do this calculation for a large number
of particles. There's a lot of particles
out in the universe. And, you can't do a
quadratic calculation for large N. So,
another, undergraduate in an algorithms
class discovered, this idea, for N body
simulation. And that's, Andrew Appel. And
his idea was that if some part. Particle
is way away from som e cluster of
particles, we can treat that cluster as a
single aggregate particle. And not do the
individual force calculation between our
particle and every one of those in the
aggregate. But use the center of mass. And
you get a very accurate approximation to
the N body doing that. And the algorithm
that he used is based on 3D trees. With
the N particles as nodes and storing the
center of a mass of a sub-tree in each
node. And then to compute the total force,
traversing the tree of all the information
that you need, to, complete the N body
calculation. But in time, much closer to N
lg N than to N^2. And that, idea that, you
didn't need to take time proportional to
N^2 but with a, a geometric algorithm,
like a 3D tree, you could get the time to
N lg N. That enabled, all sorts of new
scientific investigation in this example
of the use of algorithms to enable new