As a final example of a symbol table
client, we'll take a look at a
mathematical application where we want to
implement sparse vectors and matrices. So,
this is a standard matrix vector
multiplication that you learn in Math
where we have a square matrix and a column
vector and we want to do a dot product of,
of first row with the column vector to get
the first entry in the result. So, in this
case, they're all zero, except for 0.04
0.9 which is 0.36. And then similarly, dot
product of this with that column is 0.297
and so forth. So standard implementation
of this is quite easy. We have a
two-dimensional matrix one-dimensional
column vector for the multiplicand and the
result. And then they get initialized in
some way, but the main computation is a
pair of nested four loops for each row in
the matrix we have to go through each
entry in the column vector and compute a
running sum of for that row in the matrix,
that corresponding expanding entry with
the entry in the column and them, keep the
running sum and then that's the result
that we put in the result column factor
for every value of i. And the key thing
about this standard implementation that
it's two nested four loops that each run
up to N. So, that's N^2 or quadratic
running time. And that's fine in typical
applications when the matrix is small, or
when there's lots of entries in the
matrix. But the fact is that in many
practical applications, the matrices are
what's called sparse. They, most of the
entries are zero. And so, symbol tables
provide us with a way to provide a more
efficient implementation of, of this
process when we have lots of zero entries.
So in a typical thing, say, maybe the
matrix dimension would be 10,000, and
maybe there would only be ten non-zero
entries per row. Or, even nowadays you
might have matrices that are, are even
bigger. 10,000 by 10,000 if, if there was,
if it was full, that would be a billi on
or 100 million entries. And so that's
definitely going to be costly eh, if
you're doing this operation a, a lot. And
the idea is to cut down on that cost by
taking advantage of idea that there's a
lot of zeros. So let's start by just
looking at vectors. So the standard
representation that we use for vector is
to simply use a one dimensional array. We
have constant time access to every
element, but the space is proportional to
N. So, even if there's a lot of zeros we,
we still have to take the space to store
them all. Instead, we're going to use a
symbol table representation where our key
is the index and the value is the entry.
And we just use that for every non-zero
entry in the vector. So, this has got the
same amount of information. It says that
index one has got 0.36, index five also
has 0.36, index fourteen has 0.18 and so
forth. But the space is proportional
instead of to N, it's just proportional to
the number of non-zero entries which
again, in typical applications, may be
way, way less. And so now, just we, we
know we have a symbol table implementation
that has efficient iterator. And also
access is not bad. It's just that we're
able to do it with way less space. So,
here's what the implementation of a sparse
vector might look like. So first thing is
the representation is going to be a symbol
table. And in this case, we might as well
use a hash table because the order in
which we process things is not important.
Uh-huh, we just want to get at the, all
the non-zero entries. So the constructor
is going to create in this [cough] symbol
table. Just a new symbol table that
associates integer indices with double
values. So, the put which is to store a
value associated with an index i, is just
put into that hash table, associate key i
with value x. Associate an integer with a
double. And get I'll return zero if the
index key is not in the symbol table. We
didn't, that's the whole poin t was, we
don't represent zeroes. Other, otherwise
it returns the value associated with the
index. And the iterable just returns all
the key to iterate. And the most important
thing is that if we want to do a dot
product with a vector, say, then the time
that it takes is only proportional to the
number of non-zero keys. The zero keys are
going to be zero on the dot product so
what we're going to do is take the item
key of the vector and multiply it by
whatever value we get for the non-zero
entries. So, it's a dot product that takes
time proportional to the number of
non-zero entries in the vector. And, and
that's going to be important in the use of
a matrix. So instead of using the standard
matrix representation, where every row of
a matrix is an array, that's what a two
dimensional array is and the space is
proportional to N^2. Now we're going to
use a sparse matrix representation, where
each row of the matrix is a sparse vector.
We can iterate through the elements in, in
constant time, and with a hash table, we
can get at them in near constant time and
then constant time in the average. But the
space is only proportional to the number
of non-zero elements plus N for the extra
symbol table overhead. So, those are
independent symbol table objects. But they
allow us to have a much more efficient
matrix multiplication method. So now if we
have a sparse matrix times a vector our
running time is going to be constant for
each row or proportional to the number of
non-zero entries for each row which means
that the running time is going to be
linear for a sparse matrix just by the use
of a symbol table. And this clearly can
make the difference between being able to
address a huge problem. If we have a
10,000 by 10,000 matrix we can get it done
nearly instantly linear time versus
10,000^2. If we now run out of space, we
might run out of time. But with the symbol
table implementation we can ef ficiently
process huge sparse