Here's another simple client program for
symbol tables related to indexing.
Again, another common function that's
easily handled by symbol tables.
There's all kinds of cases where we just
have a lot of information, maybe on our PC
or all over the web, and we want to create
an index that allows us to specify.
A search key and get all the associated
information.
And you've, you've used programs like this
on, on your computer many instances, most
likely.
So, more generally, here's the goal.
So, we're going to list of files that are
specified.
And then, and maybe it's all files on the
computer, or maybe it's specified in, in
some other way.
And what we want to do is create an index,
so that we can efficiently
find all the files that contain a given
query.
String.
so, in this small example.
So, our client is going to called file
index.
And in this small example say we are going
to have five text files.
And these are just pieces of literature.
And so what we want to do is, build and
index from that set of text files.
And then given a key, a string key, we
want
it to print out the files that might
contain that key.
So, for example, the word freedom appears
in the
Magna Ca, Carta and in Moby Dick and A
Tale
of Two Cities [COUGH] in all three of them
but not in Tom Sawyer and not in Aesop's
Fables.
The word whale is only in, Moby Dick.
The word lamb appears both in Tom Sawyer
and Aesop's Fables, and so forth.
So we're looking for a piece of
information somewhere in a computer,
and it'll give us the names of the files
that contain that information.
so, with the, more [COUGH] complex user
interface, this is, very
much what the spotlight or find function
on your computer is doing.
And a programmer might use the same
program, to find places where certain,
Programming
terms are used in a bunch of programs.
So, normally we have a bunch of dot
java files when we're working on an
application.
Like these are all the ones associated
with
this, lecture, so we might build an index
from
that set of files, and then we might
wonder well where do we use the import
statements.
So we just search for import and it'll
tell us,
look in those three files.
Or, did we use comparators anywhere here?
In, this Index will tell us no.
So again, a very general capability that's
got lots and lots of
applications and easy to implement with
our symbol table api.
And the idea is, that what we're going to
do is associate.
On keys with values well the key is
the string we type what's the value?
Well what we're going to use for value is
a
set of files, the files that contain the
query string.
So just given that high level description
then the implimintation is pretty direct.
Here's the implementation of file index
using our symbol file implimintation.
So now we're going to build a symbol
table.
That associates string keys with sets of
files.
So this creates a new symbol table
associating string keys with sets of
files.
So first thing we do, as before, is build
the index.
So we're going to take, this time we're
going to take
the list of file names from the command
line.
And [COUGH] for each file we're going to
create an input stream.
We're going to read every word in the file
if
the symbol contains does not contain the
word.
Will create a new set for that word and
put that in the symbol table,
and then, we simply get the set
associated with the key and add the new
word to that set, the new file
name to that set.
So, this one, for each word in the file.
It'll add that file name to the
corresponding set for that word.
That's building a symbol table associating
keys with sets of files.
And then processing queries is the same as
before, as
long as standard in is not empty we take a
query.
And then simply print out the set of
strings associated
with that word which is a list of file
names.
So again,
our symbol table API gives a very easy way
to
implement this file indexing function,
which is very widely useful.
And similarly, maybe we want to build a, a
book
index, maybe for a real book, or maybe for
an ebook.
Or more generally, people want to often
process,
preprocess text to, maybe a huge amount of
text,
to support, so called, concordance
queries.
So what you want to do, is given a word,
find all occurrences of that word along
with immediate contexts.
And context just means a few words before
and a few words after.
So for example, in tail of two cities.
The words cities actually only appears in
this one place and this is [COUGH] Context
that it appears.
With the forwards tongues of the two
before and that were blended in after.
The word majesty appears in three places,
and there's, there's the context.
In well, this is, the very special case
that you're very familiar with.
In web searches.
You type in a word, and then you get
places that, where that word appears in
context.
Again, our symbol table API provides for
an easy way to implement this.
This is a, a.
[COUGH] concordance client that that does
the job.
Now what we want to do is read text, and
we want to build an index for each word.
So this is a
[COUGH] a, a java construct for.
Reading all the strings
on an input stream, on standard input,
and, splitting em by
blank space and putting em into array, so
now all the words, are, in the an array.
On standard input.
And then we're going to create a new
symbol table that associates
strings with sets of integers.
And again the string is the key and the
sets of integers
are going to be the places in the array
where the given work appears.
So, we go through.
All the words, pick out our key, s, and
again, if, it's not there yet, we create a
new set associated with that s, and,
then, afterwards, we go ahead and.
Get that set, and put the new index on
that set.
And then that allows us to process
queries, where we take a
query, and then get the set of indices
associated with that query.
And then we left out, left out the code
where you print out the nine words that
you want.
The four to the left and the four to the
right.
Again, quite useful and familiar
functionality and very
easy to implement with our simul table
client.