Now, let's look at a dictionary client,
another very useful and common application
of symbol tables. So, in this case, we are
going to write a client called Lookup CSV
that [cough] is going to take three
arguments. The first will be a file name,
a so-called common separated value file
and the next two arguments are integers
which will tell us what to treat as keys
and values in the file. In this example or
CSV file relates URLs to IP addresses. So,
each line has a URL and IP address and are
separated by commas. And in general, a CSV
file might have many fields separated by
comma, comma. So, we number them zero,
one, and so forth starting from the left.
So, what we are going to do with this
client is specify with integers which
field is the key, and which is the value.
So, if we call this client with second
argument zero and third argument one, that
means we want to use the URL field zero on
the CSV file as the key, no one use the IP
address that's field one in the CSV as the
value, you want to associate keys with
values. So the client will build a symbol
table that makes us associations for every
line in the file and this could be huge
file. And then, if we want to look up the
IP address associated with a given URL we
can just type in URLs and the client will
return the IP address, it'll do the look
up. So, Adobe.com has got this IP address
that's shown if this line here in the
table, and so forth. Princeton.edu has
this IP and ebay.edu is not in the file.
Now, on the other hand, we could, from
this same file, we could build a symbol
table where we treat the IP address as
the, as the key and the URL as the value.
So, in that case, it'll build a symbol
table with IP addresses as keys and we can
type in an IP address and get the
associated URL. So, with one client we can
handle lookups of all kinds in CSV files.
For example, here's another CSV file that
from biology that deals with, amino acids
and codons and names. So, in this case,
the first field is three letters from the
DNA sequence which, represents a codon.
And certain codons have names, that's the
amino acids. So, TCC is called serine, and
so forth. And that's an association that's
well known to biologist and then you can
use this lookup CSV client to quickly get
the name associated with any given codon.
That's just another simple example. This
is a very general tool. Any CSV file, you
can pick any field as the key, any other
field as the value. So here's still
another example where we might use for a
class list, which has the person's year of
graduation, last name, first name precept
name and login name. And so in the first
call over here, we might use the login
name as the key and the first name as the
value. So, we type in somebody's login
name we get their first name. And again,
with the same client login is key and get
the section as a value. So, all kinds of
information processing that we might need
to do for large amounts of data,
represented in comma, comma separated
value files this one client which is based
on a symbol table will provide useful
functionality. And here's the
implementation there's very little to it
given the symbol table API that we've
articulated and the implementations that
we have. So what do we do to get lookup
CSV implemented? Well, first thing is to
set up the input stream from the first
argument, so that's our input file. And
then, get the numbers of the fields, so
the key and the value. And now build a
simple table that associates strings with
strings. Then there there's a while loop
where we just read a new line in that read
line, read line and then split according
to comma into tokens in an array. And
then, the index in the array is going to
build the fields that we're going to use.
So, the key is the string in the key field
entry of the array, and the value is the
string in the value field entry in the
array, and we simpl y put that into symbol
table. So, this value loop just builds the
symbol table from the file. Then from
standard input we take queries, just read
a string, check if the symbol table
contains the string. It, it doesn't, print
not found. And if it does, print the value
associated with the key. So, a very small
amount of code based on a symbol table
implementation that gives us the
dictionary functionality.