So let's just look at a little bit of the
context of hashing in practical
applications. As I mentioned, it's very
widely used. So here's an, here's an
example right from Java. The first.
Implementation of Java 1.1. The designers
found that the cost of computing the hash
function for strings seemed to be
excessive, particularly for long strings.
And that was one of the main uses of
hashing, was just to be able to do
searching with string keys. And so what
they decided in the first implementation
was let's just look at every eighth or
ninth character, and that way, we don't
have to spend a lot of time computing the
hash function. So they had a hash function
pretty much like the one that we use.
Except that it compute a skip that would
mean that, that only look at about every
eight key and they wouldn't have to do
quite so much work performing the hash
function. And that's diffidently one thing
to consider when using hashing is that the
cost of computing the hash function for a
complicated key might exceed the cost of
searching and using a simpler structure
like a binary search tree. And anyway for
Java 1.1 what happened was that there was
a huge potentail for really bad collision
patterns on typical data. So here's the
example of typical data, which is a URL.
All of these keys, which are totally
different, would wind up having the same
collision. And so client programs and
system programs on the Java system were
having terrible performance on their
symbol table because of the shortcut in
hashing. So this well illustrates that you
need to use all of the data in the hash
function and sometime we do a closer
analysis. The cost of computing the hash
function can mean that something like red
black trees will even outperform hashing
even for just searching and insert. So
there is another thing about the uniform
hashing assumption is that it is an
assumption and if you are writing code
where we have to have guaranteed
performance like when your aircraft is
landing or you are controlling a nuclear
reactor or somebody's pa cemaker. That, if
that assumption doesn't hold and you get
bad performance you're going to have
disastrous consequences. So that's another
reason to think about maybe paying a
little extra and using to guarantee that
you get with red black search trees.
Instead of hashing. And there's another
surprising situation that happens in
today's world. For example Java publishes
its hash function. And so if you're trying
to provide a service over the web. An
adversary can learn your hash function and
just send you data that causes huge
performance problem by just making all
that data hash to one particular item. And
that's definitely something to worry
about. And, and in the real world you can
nowadays find on the web particular
sequences of keys that will cause
particular services to crash. And again,
that's a little harder to do with
something like a red black tree where we
have performance guarantees. When you make
an assumption you better be sure and
you're depending on that assumption, you
better be sure that it holds somehow. This
is different than for example for quick
sort when we, our assumption was we're
going to create randomness and we are
going to depend on that randomness. In
this care we're kind of hoping for
randomness and maybe that doesn't really
always hold. So that's certainly something
to be aware of when using hashing in
practice. So here's just simple example on
hashing in java. So what we can do is it's
pretty easy to find a family of strings
that have the same hash code for example
with just a little fooling around now days
you can just look it up on the web, you
can see that these two character keys,
both have the same hash code because when
you just do the math in a base 31 hash
code it'll tell you that answer. Well what
that means is that actually, just like
working in binary you got, you can combine
those things. In all possible ways, and
you can get two to the N strings, for any
N of length to N that all hash to the same
value. And somebody's implemented a
service in Java that it uses a simp le
table that takes string keys, you can
cause that to crash in this way. Little
bit scary for some systems designers. At
least reason for pause in using hashing.
Now, hashing also has a extremely
important application in today's Internet
commerce. And so the, it's the concept of
so called one way hash functions which
mean that we, we, use it for secure to try
to be, have some secure fingerprints for
use on the web. And there's been a lot
research done to develop functions that
take keys as input, and then produce
values that look random. In such a way
that, it's hard for someone else to find
another key that collides with that. This
technology is, is useful for storing
passwords and digital fingerprints and
things. But it's too expensive for use, in
a symbol table. So the bottom line is
separate chaining versus linear probin
collision resolution message methods. Now
there's a number of considerations to take
into account. Separate chaining is really
easy to implement both insert and delete
it performs, it degrades, it does so
gracefully and the clustering is, is maybe
less of a problem if you have a bad hash
function. Linear probing tends to make
better use of space. And also it'll
perform better for huge tables whereas
caching is involved. And if, in the
classic algorithm or computer science
problems for people to think about is what
do we do to delete in these two situations
and exactly how do we resize. Those are
all at the level of exercises in the
context of the kinds of algorithms that
we've seen. And as I mentioned, there's
been many, many improved versions of
hashing that have been studied. I
mentioned the two probe, or double hashing
version. Another way to use two hash
functions is just to hash the two
positions and put the key in the shorter
of the two chains. In, in that case, then
the expected length of the longest chain
will be lg, lg N which is quite an
improvement. You get constant time
expected and lg, lg N worst case. Double
hashing is the variant of layer probing
where you just skip a variable amount, not
one each time. And that pretty much wipes
out clustering but it, it is more
difficult to implement delete for that
one. In a new method called, relatively
new method called Cuckoo Hashing. It's
another variant of linear probing where we
hash a key to two positions and insert the
key in either one. If occupied you, you
reinsert the displaced key into its
alternative. It was in one, each one can
go to two. And that one actually gives
constant worst case time for search.
That's another variation on the team. And
all of these things allow us to make
better use of memory, allows the table to
become nearly full. It would have been
very exciting. Thing to be researchers in
the 1950's who cared so much about memory
and nowadays a little extra memory is not
something that people care about so much
and most people just go with the easy
algorithm except for really performance
critical applications. What about hash
tables versus balance search trees? Well
hash tables are really simple to code
usually if you don't have to do the hash
function. And if you don't have order in
the keys at all then you need the compare
to, to implement balance search trees. So
you have to use hashing if you don't have
the comparison. And it'll probably be
faster for simple keys to use hashing.
It's a few arithmetic operations to do the
hash versus lg N and compares for the
balance tree. And there's some better
system support in Java for strings that
cache hash code means that you don't even
have to compute the hash if your, your
simple table for strings is in an inner
loop. On the other hand, balanced search
trees have a much stronger performance
guarantee. It, you don't have to assume
anything. It's going to be less than lg N
and compares and it's got support for all
those ordered ST operations, and compared
to and is pretty easy and natural function
to implement. So it's more flexible and
more broadly useful. And actually the Java
system and other systems include both so
that programmers can make use of either
one in diff erent situations. That's our
context for hashing algorithms.