Another popular closure resolution method
is known as linear probing. In this you
know many different versions of hashing
that are based on this idea. With linear
probing is called open addressing and is
also around the same time in the 50's the
idea is just use an array. Instead of
using space for the length in a length
list. I use that same space, and just,
allocate an array. In this case, the size
of the array is going to have to be bigger
than the number of keys that we
[inaudible] expect. And we use the empty
slots in the array. To. Essentially
terminate the length of the [inaudible]
list that we have to search through when
we're doing a insertion. So let's look at
a demo of how it looks. So to hash again
we do the same thing, we just map the key
to a index. But, in linear probing, to
insert what we do is when we put it in
position I if that's free, if not we just
look at I plus one, and I plus two, and
wrap around to the beginning if we reach
the end. Now that's also simple to
implement and it works well as long the
size of the array is, significantly bigger
than the number of keys. Let's look at,
Well it's a demo. So we start with an
empty table, insert s, it's hash value is
six, six is empty so we put it there. Now
we look at e, hash of e is ten, we look at
ten, it's empty so we put e there. So at
the beginning we're going to be fine. A is
four, empty, put it there. R is fourteen,
empty, put it there. So we just
essentially, using the hash funtion as an
array index. C is five, that's empty and
we put it there. So H now, the hash value
of H is four. So now we look at four, and
that's occupied, so we can't put the H
there. And then linear probing says, just
look at the next position, look at five.
That's still not empty. So we look at six.
And we keep going till we find an empty
place, and then we put H there. Now when
we search, we're going to have to do the
same thing. We'r e going to have to look
at all those positions to look at H. The.
Group of four key, continuous keys in a
table space there is called a cluster and
clearly we want to keep those clusters
small. And we do that by juts by not
putting too many keys in to the table. So
X hashes to fifteen, that's empty so we
put it there, M hashes to one, that's
empty and we put it there. P hashes to
fourteen, 14's occupied, 15's also
occupied, now we run off the end of the
table, and look at zero, and that's empty
so we put it there. L hashes to six. Six
is occupied. We look at seven, seven is
occupied. We look at eight, and we put it
there. And, so that's an example of
inserting, keys into a hash table. And
now, for a search, we just do the same
thing. We, use the hash function. To
search for E, E's hash value is ten so we
look in ten and there it is. So that's a
search hit. If we're going to search for
say L L's hatch value is six so it's not
there. So in order to look at every place
in the table where L could be, we have to
keep looking til we found an empty table
position, or we find L itself. So now we
look at seven L not there, we look at
eight L is there, that's a search hit. If
we have a value that's not in the table
like K, well hash and is in position five,
no, six no, seven no, eight no and we find
an empty position at that point we can
conclude that K is not in the table.
Because if K were in the table it would be
somewhere between it's hash point five and
that empty position nine. That's a search
miss, and we return all. So that's a short
demo of linear probing hashing. So here's
a summary of linear probing, hashing. To.
To get started we map a key to a integer
between zero and m-1 where m is the sides
of our array where we are storing the
keys. To insert we put the key value pair.
Use parallel arrays [inaudible] and the
value array with the same index. We put
the entry at the table index A for three.
If not try I+1 I+2 until getting to a
empty position. And for search you do the
same thing you hash to the table position
and you look there into the right. To find
the key and you stop when you find an
empty table position. Find the key or find
an empty table position. Now, it's
essential that the array size is greater
than the number of key value pairs N. And
for linear probing hashing, really, the
implementation needs to include array
resizing, whenever the hash table gets too
full. Here's the implementation. And it's,
quite straightforward, given the demo that
we talked about. You use the same hash
function. And we use parallel arrays for
the value in the keys. And we have to use
ugly cast, 'cause we can't have a race of
generics. Then let's do the search. So. We
just have a for loop starting at hash of
key and going until we get to a position
that's null. As long as it's not null, we
stay in the loop and increment I mod m. So
that's when I gets to the end it gets to
the end, it's in the position m minus one
and it goes... In the next increment goes
back to zero at the left end of the table
and we just test for all the non null
keys. If it's equal, if it is, go ahead
and return the associated value and if you
get to an empty position, then return
null. And the implementation of put is
similar. Find a, a position, if it's,
that's equal, And then, reset the key, in
the value. If the key's there, it just
resets the value. If they key's not there,
it puts a new entry in. So again, that's,
fairly little code, to implement, a fast
symbol table and insert, search and
insert. But it's only going to be fast, if
the, table size is set appropriately. In
ancient times, memory was, at quite a
premium and so people were very concerned
in m-m-making sure that the hash table
never, got too empty. Remember in the
first computers, each bit was a physical
thing, a magnetic core that somebody had
to string a wire through, so. The bits
were really expensive, and people wanted
to make sure, that they were making best
use of the memory. And just leaving empty
positions around, in a hash table, or
using links in a link list, did not seem
like an appropriate use of space. And, so
there was quite a bit of effort, devoted
to figuring it out, how full we could get
the hash table, in linear probing. And how
close it could get to full without
sacrificing performance. And one way to
think about what goes on is to just watch
what happens when a hash table fills up.
So here we just as, as it goes up we're
showing each key getting inserted in the
number of probes of the table that are
needed for the insertions are J hash to
the same position that A; you had to look
for a while, and the one thing to notice
is as the table gets full, is that first
of all. You have, these clusters or these
chains building. And so, what's clear
about that is that, it means that, the new
hash is likely to hash into a big cluster.
>> And not only that once you have a big
cluster and you hash into the middle of it
you've got a good chance that, that
clusters going to get longer, or worse.
That's it's even going to merge with
another big cluster. And so, that's the
situation as the table fills up. You get
long clusters and they're likely to get
longer. And the math bares that out. Now
this was studied in detail by Knauf, Don
Knauf, in the 1960's and actually this
problem, Knauf says, was the origin of the
origin of analysis of algorithms.
Mathematicians were trying hard to
understand this problem and were ready to
give up and he realized you could use
classical balls and bins type
probabilistic analysis. Not an easy
analysis, but we actually could make
precise accurate statements about the
performance of this algorithm. And those
statements can be borne out in practice,
because the hash functions approximate
random, the math assumes random and the
formulas predict what actually happened in
practice. No way can you formulate the
problem as so called parking problem. So,
what happens is that you are on a one way
street and you are looking for a parking
place and, it's, the idea's you start
looking for a parking place at particular
times and say "Okay, now I need a parking
place", and what you're doing is linear
probing hashing. If the current space is
taken, you try the next space and the one
after and so forth. And the question is.
If every car. Starts looking for a place
at a random time. That. Then that models
the hash function, then how far do they
have to go to look for a place? That's
canoot's parking problem. And he was able
to show, and we'll talk just a little bit
about this, that if, there's, only half of
the parking spaces are occupied, then, on
average, half the people find, find it
after one place and the other half have to
look one extra. So that's the kind of
performance that we want. But as it gets
full. The displacement gets up to square
root, of pi M over eight. Which is
obviously much higher than we want. We
don't want our searches to take that long.
And that actually, the analysis, is
amazing function that goes back to famous
Roman Nuygen and other classical results
from our commentorial analysis. What
Canute's theorem says is that under the
uniform hashing assumption, the number of
probes in the linear hash table size M,
that is alpha percent full, so the number
of keys is a fraction of M, is for a
search miss half one plus one over alpha,
and a search miss one plus one over one
minus alpha squared. One myse alpha is for
the hit, one myse alpha for the squared
for the insert. Now as alpha gets close to
one, you can see these things are going to
grow, and particularly the search miss is
growing to grow quite, quite a bit. If
it's 9/10's full one over one minus alpha
squared is 100 one over 100, so it means
it's going to be 50 p robes for a search
miss if it's 9/10's full, and that's
independent of N and M, whereas if it's
half full then we get the nice. Numbers of
only 3-house for a hit, and only 5-house
for a miss. And, again these formulas are
nice approximate formulas, but Knuth, once
he figured this out, in 1963, tells
stories, that time, he decided to write
his famous series of books on algorithms.
Now there's four volumes out and more
planned, and this is where, all computer
scientists go. For detailed information on
a performance, eval grievance. So, in, in
summary. You can't have M too large, what
we want to use nowadays is array resizing
to make sure that the array is always
about half time, half full. And if we can
keep the array about half full then we get
constant time performance for search hit
and search miss. And linear probing is
very attractive in this case. There's
other things that we can do
algorithmically to bring down the search
time a little bit. Like using another
hatch function rather than looking at the
next entry. Use another hatch function to
determine the stride that we're going to
use. And that brings it down somewhat and
allows us to keep the tables more full.
But the bottom line is that now we have
two methods that under the uniform hashing
assumption can give us constant time,
search, search it insert and delete. For
symbol table implementations where we
don't need ordering. And we've got a
reasonable hash function. So, that's a
summary of linear probing or second hash,
collision avoidance strategy.