Next we'll look at separate chaining, a
collision red solution strategy that makes
use of elementary link list. So, what are
we supposed to do when two different keys
hash to the same index? The birthday
problem tells us that we're going to have
collisions. You need a quadratic amount of
memory to avoid collisions. In the lower
balancing, a coupon collector analysis
tell us that the collisions are going to
be evenly distribute, distributed among
the table, around the table. So, what we
want to do is have an easy way to deal
with collisions. And so the first way
we'll look at is called Separate Chaining
and it's a very diagonal idea back1953,
and the idea is just build a link list for
each of the table positions. So, we'll
have a table that's smaller than the
number of keys that we have, the hash
function will map each key to some
integer. So in this case, we have a table
of size five. So the hash function will
map any key. In this case, we use single
letter keys. It'll map any key to an
integer between zero and four and then to
[cough] do an insertion we'll just keep a
link list at the table position
corresponding to the hash value. So S hash
is to position two, it'll be on the link
list that is first link is at position
two. And E goes to zero, and A goes to
zero. And for search, we're going to have
to go to, if we're going to look at is C
in this table say, we're going to find the
hash value for C and we'll look down the
list to see if we can find C. So we have
to look through the whole list for search
but you only have to look through one list
out of all the lists. Essentially if you
have M entries in the hash table and M
keys the link of list you're going to look
at is about N over M cuz they're evenly
distributed. So that's a straightforward
and simple scheme for implementing symbol
tables with hashing. Now, we could use a
interval bag or some data structure like
that and hide the link list structure
underneath and that's a perfectly fine way
to proceed in modern programming. This
implementation directly implements the
link list. Now, for a practical situation
we picked some kind of, some value of M.
You could make it so that the hash table
itself grows once it gets really huge and
such hybrid methods are easy to implement.
So we won't talk to much about that. We
need to just in terms of implementation
details, our keys and values have to be
objects. Because we can't have an array of
generics. So, since we're making array of
nodes, a node would have generics if we
use to key in value. So we have to make
them objects then when we get things off,
we're going to have cast. So [cough] this
is the get procedure. So to look for a key
in the hash table we compute the hash
value. In our hash function is pull out
the system hash code, make it positive by
ending off the sign bit and then mark with
M to get a number of, zero and -one. So we
pick that number, I and then we just go to
that list and this is the standard code
for diversing a link list start at the
first node as long as it is not null go x
= x dot x. And if you find a key that's
equal to the key you're looking for,
return the value and we have to cast it to
value because of the generic recreation
problem in Java, otherwise return null. So
that's not much code, and it's trivial
code at that for doing an efficient symbol
table search using hashing. And insertion
is not much more difficult if you do the
same thing and if you find a node where
key equal to key on the link list, reset
the value and return. Otherwise, you make
a new node and put it at the beginning of
the link list with the standard code. Now,
replace STFI with a new node that links to
the old STFI. So again, very little code
to implement search and insert using
hashin g and that's why it's so popular.
And what about the analysis? Well, again
this the [cough] standard probabilistic
analysis of the balls and bins problem
tells us a lot of information of what goes
on. And again, if the uniform hashing
assumption holds the probability that the
number of keys within a list is within a
constant factor of N over M is extremely
close to one. So, it means that we've
divided the search cost which would be N
if we have a sequential search by a factor
of M. And, and in many applications even
setting M = 100 or 1,000 is going to be
very effective. And that's why so many
system programs refuse that. So, number of
pros for search and insert's proportional
to N over M. Now typically, what we'd what
a programmer would do is try to figure on
making M about equal to the number of keys
divided by five say. So, you can't make M
too large, you have too much space and
you'll have empty chains or short chains.
And if you make M too small then they're
too long, you have to search through them
all. So let's say, N over five and then
you get constant time searches and not
much extra space. You have extra space for
the links to implement the link lists but
the rest of the table is not much extra
space. And those are typical parameters.
If you want a full service symbol table
which is going to, going to grow from
small to huge and then back down to small
again then you'd want to use array
re-sizing to make sure that M is always
within a constant factor of N but we will
leave that detail out for now. So that
brings us to this summary where red-black
trees, we were happy with a log based two
of N for search and insert with separate
chaining, you can really get it down to a
constant number of operations for search
and insert. So hashing's going to be
preferred for short keys where the hash
function's easy to compute. And where we
don't need ordered iteration or any of the
ordered symbol table operations because it
has really fast access to the symbol
table. That's our first collision
resolution method, hashing with separate
chaining.