Now we'll look at our first implementation
of an algorithm for solving the dynamic
connectivity problem, called Quick-find.
This is a so called eager algorithm, for
solving kind activity problem. The data
structure that we're going to use to
support the algorithm is simply an integer
array indexed by object. The
interpretation is the two objects, P and Q
are connected if and only if, their
entries in the array are the same. So for
example in this example with our ten
objects the idea array that describes the
situation after seven connections is
illustrated in the middle of the slide. So
that, after the, at this point zero, five,
and six are all in the same connected
component, because they have the same
array entry, zero. One, two, and seven all
have entry one. And three, four, eight,
and nine all have entry eight. So that
representation is, shows that they're
connected. And clearly, that's going to
support a quick implementation of the find
operation. We just check the array entries
to see if they're equal. Check if P and Q
have the same ID. So, six and one have
different IDs. One has ID one, six has ID
zero. They're not in the same connected
component. Union is more difficult in
order to merge the components, containing
two given objects. We have to change all
the entries, whose ID is equal to one of
them to the other one. And arbitrarily we
choose to change the ones that are the
same as P to the ones that are same as Q.
So if we're going to union six and one,
then we have to change entries zero, five,
and six. Everybody in the same connected
component as six. From zero to one. And
this is, as we'll see, this is a bit of a
problem when we have a huge number of
objects, because there's a lot of values
that can change. But still, it's easy to
implement, so that'll be our starting
point. So we'll start with a, a demo of
how this works. So, initially, we set up
the ID array, with each entry, equal to
its index. And so all that says is that
all the objects are independent. They're
in their own connected component. Now,
when we get a union operation. So, say,
four is supposed to be unio n with three.
Then we're going to change, all entries,
whose ID is equal to the first ID to the
second one. So in this case, we'll change
the, connect three and four means that we
need to change the four to a three. And
we'll continue to do a few more so you'll
get an idea of how it works. So three and
eight now so to connect three and eight
now three and four have to be connected to
eight. So both of those entries have to
change to eight. Okay? So now, what about
six and five? So again, we change the
first one to match the second one. So to
connect six and five, we change the six to
a five. What about nine and four? So, now
we have to change the, to connect nine and
four, we have to change, 9's entry to be
the same as 4's. So now we have three,
four, eight, and nine. All have entries
eight. They're all on the same connected
component. Two and one means that we
connect two and one by changing the 2201.
Eight and nine are already connected. They
have the same, entries in the idea array.
So, that connected query, that find says,
true, they're already connected. And five
and zero have different entries. They're
not connected, so we'd return false, in
that case, not connected. And then, if we
want to connect five and zero. Then, as
usual we'll connect, the entry
corresponding to both five and six to
zero. Seven and two, union seven and two.
That's an easy one. And union, six and one
so there is three entries that have to get
changed. All those zeros have to get
changed to ones. So, that's a quick demo
of Quick-find. Now next we'll look at the
code for implementating that. Okay, with
this concrete demo in mind then moving to
coding up this algorithim is pretty
straight forward. Although it's an
interesting programming exercise that a
lot of us would get wrong the first time.
So let's start with the constructor, well
we have a, a private integer array. That's
our ID array. That's the data structure
that's going to support this
implementation. The constructor has to
create the array and then go through and
set the value corresponding to each index
I to I. That's straight forward. The find
operation, or connected operation. That's
the easy one . This is the Quick-find
algorithm. So it simply takes its two
arguments, P and Q, and checks whether
their ID entries are equal, and returns
that value. If they're equal, it returns
true. If they're not equal, it returns
false. The more complicated operation
implement is a union. And there, we find
first the ID corresponding with the first
argument, and then the ID corresponding to
the second argument. And then we go
through the whole array, and looking for
the entries whose IDs are equal to the ID
of the first argument, and set those to
the ID of the second argument. That's a
pretty straightforward implementation. And
I mentioned that a lot of us would get us
wrong. The mistake we might make is to put
ID of P here rather than first picking
out, that value. And you can think about
the implications of that. That's an
insidious bug. So, that's a fine
implementation of QuickFind so the next
thing to decide is how effective or
efficient that algorithm is going to be
and we'll talk in some detail about how to
do that but for this it's sufficient to
just think about the number of times the
code has to access the array. As we saw
when doing the implementation, both the
initialized and union operations involved
the for-loop that go through the entire
array. So they have to touch in a constant
proportional to n times after touching
array entry. Find Operation is quick, it's
just to a constant number of times check
array entries. And this is problematic
because the union operation is too
expensive. In particular if you just have
N union commands on N objects which is
not unreasonable. They're either connected
or not then that will take quadratic time
in squared time. And one of the themes
that we'll go through over and over in
this course is that quadratic time is much
to slow. And we can't accept quadratic
time algorithms for large problems. The
reason is they don't scale. As computers
get faster and bigger, quadratic
algorithms actually get slower. Now, let's
just talk roughly about what I mean by
that. A very rough standard, say for now,
is that people have computers that can run
billions of operations per second, and
they have billions of entries in main
memory. So, that means that you could
touch everything in the main memory in
about a second. That's kind of an amazing
fact that this rough standard is really
held for 50 or 60 years. The computers get
bigger but they get faster so to touch
everything in the memory is going to take
a few seconds. Now it's true when
computers only have a few thousand words
of memory and it's true now that they have
billions or more. So let's accept that as
what computers are like. Now, that means
is that, with that huge memory, we can
address huge problems. So we could have,
billions of objects, and hope to do
billions of union commands on them. And,
but the problem with that quick find
algorithm is that, that would take
ten^18th operations, or, say array axises
or touching memory. And if you do the
math, that works out to 30 some years of
computer time. Obviously, not practical to
address such a problem on today's
computer. And, and the reason is, and the
problem is that quadratic algorithms don't
scale with technology. You might have a
new computer that's ten times as fast but
you could address a problem that's ten
times as big. And with a quadratic
algorithm when you do that. It's going to
be ten times as slow. That's the kind of
situation we're going to try to avoid by
developing more efficient algorithms for
solving problems like this.