Alright. Now that we've seen efficient
implementations of algorithms that can
solve the unifying problem for huge
problem instances let's look to see how
that might be applied. There's a huge
number of applications of Union-find. We
talked about dynamic connectivity in
networks there's many other examples in
our computational infrastructure. Down at
the bottom is one of those important one
is in image processing for understanding
how to label areas in images. We'll see
later Kruskal's minimum spanning tree
algorithm, which is a graph processing
algorithm which uses Union-find as a
subroutine. There's algorithms in physics
for understanding physical phenomenon that
we'll look at an example and many others
on this list. So, the one we're going to
talk about now is called percolation.
That's a model for many physical systems
I'll give an abstract model and then just
talk briefly about how it applies to
physical systems. So let's think of an n
by n grid of squares that we call sites.
And we'll say that each site is open.
That's white in the diagram with probably
P or blocked, that's black of the diagram
with probability one - P and we define a
system to, we say that a system is
percolated if the top and the bottom are
connected by open sites. So the system at
the left, you can find a way to get from
the top to the bottom through white
squares, but the system to the right does
not percolate, there's no way to get from
the top to the bottom through white
squares. So, that's a model for many
systems. You can think of for electricity.
You could think of a vacant site as being
a conductor and, and a block site as being
insulated. And so if there's a conductor
from top to bottom then the thing conducts
electricity. Or, you could think of it as,
as water flowing through a porous
substance of some kind. Where a vacant
side is just empty and a block side has
got some material, and either the water
flows through from top to bottom, or not.
Or you could think of a social network
where it's people connected and either
there's a c onnection between two people
or not and these are a way not to get from
one group of people to another
communicating through that social network.
That's just a few examples of the
percolation model. So if we, we are
talking abouta randomized model where the
sites are vacant with the given
probability. And so it's pretty clear that
if it's. Probability that a site is vacant
is low as on the left, two examples on the
left in this diagram, it's not going to
percolate. There's not enough open site
for there to be a connection from the top
to the bottom. If the probability is high
and there is a lot of open sides, it
definitely is going to percolate. There
would be lots of ways to get from the top
to the bottom. But in the middle, when
it's medium, it's questionable whether it
percolates or not. So the scientific
question, or the, mathematical question
from this model is, how do we know,
whether it's going to percolate or not? In
this problem and in many similar problems,
there's what's called a phase transition.
Which says that, you know, when it's low,
it's not going to percolate. When it's
high, it is going to percolate. And
actually, the threshold between when it
percolates and when it doesn't percolate
is very sharp. And actually there is a
value as N gets large that if you're less
than that value it almost certainly will
not percolate, if you're greater it almost
certainly will. The question is what is
that value. This is an example of a
mathematical model where the problem is,
is very well articulated. What's that
threshold value but, nobody knows the
solution to that mathematical problem. The
only solution we have comes from a
computational model, where we run
simulations to try and determine the value
of that probability. And those simulations
are only enable by fast union find
algorithms, that's our motivating example
for why we might need fast union find
algorithms, so let's look at that. So what
we're going to run is called a so called
Monte Carlo simulation. Where we
initialize the whole grid to be block ed
all black and then we randomly fill in
open sites. And we keep going. And every
time we add an open site, we check to see
if it makes the system percolate. And we
keep going until we get to a point where
the system percolates. And we can show
that the vacancy percentage at the time
that it percolates is an estimate of this
threshold value. So what we want to do is
run this experiment millions of times,
which we can do in a computer, as long as
we can, efficiently do the calculation of
does it percolate or not. That's a Monte
Carlo simulation, a computational problem
that gives us a solution to this,
scientifc problem where, mathematical
problems nobody knows how to solve yet.
So, let's, look in a little bit more
detail of how we're going to use our
dynam-, dynamic connectivity model to do
this. So, it's clear that, we'll create an
object corresponding to each site. And
we'll give'em a name, from zero to N^2-1
as indicated here. And then we'll connect
them together. If they're connected by
open sites. So the percolation model on
the left corresponds to the, connection
model on the right, according to what
we've been doing. Now, you might say,
well, what we want to do is, connect,
check whether any site in the bottom row
is connected to any site in the top row,
and use union find for that. Problem with
that is, that would be a brute force
algorithm. Would be quadratic, right on
the face of it. Because it would have N^2,
calls to find, to check whether they're
connected. For each site on the top, I'd
check each site on the bottom. Much too
slow. Instead, what we do is create a
virtual site on the top and on the bottom.
And then, when we want to know whether
this system percolates, we just check
whether the virtual top site is connected
to the virtual bottom site. So how do we
model opening a new site? Well to open a
site we just connect it to all it's
adjacent open sites. So that's a few calls
to Union but that's easy to implement. And
then with that, simple, relationship we
can use the exactly the code that we
developed to go ahead and run a simulation
for this connectivity problem. And that's
where we get the result that, by running
enough simulations for a big-enough n,
that this, percolation threshold is about
.592746. With this fast algorithm we can
get an accurate answer to the scientific
question. If we use a slow Union-find
algorithm we won't be able to run it for
very big problems and we won't get a very
accurate answer. So in summary, we took an
important problem. The, the dynamic
connectivity problem. We modeled the
problem to try to understand precisely
what kinds of data structures and
algorithms we'd need to solve it. We saw a
few easy algorithms for solving the
problem, and quickly saw that they were
inadequate for addressing huge problems.
But then we saw how to improve them to get
efficient algorithms. And then left us
with, applications that, could not be
solved without these efficient algorithms.
All of this involves the scientific
method. For algorithm design where we try
to develop mathematical models that help
us understand the properties of the
algorithms that we're developing. And then
we test those models through
experimentation enabling us to improve
algorithms iterating, developing better
algorithms and more refined models until
we get what we need to solve the practical
problems that we have of interest. That's
going to be the overall architecture for
studying algorithms that we're going to
use throughout the course.