Okay. So, we've looked at the quick union
and quick find algorithms. Both of which
are easy to implement. But simply can't
support a huge dynamic connectivity
problems. So, how are we going to do
better? That's what we'll look at next. A
very effective improvement, it's called
weighting. And it might have occurred to
you while we are looking at these
algorithms. The idea is to when
implementing the quick union algorithm
take steps to avoid having tall trees. If
you've got a large tree and a small tree
to combine together what you want to try
to do is avoid putting the large tree
lower, that's going to lead to long tall
trees. And there's a relatively easy way
to do that. What we'll do is we'll keep
track of the number of objects in each
tree and then, we'll maintain balance by
always making sure that we link the root
of the smaller tree to the root of the
larger tree. So, we, we avoid this first
situation here where we put the larger
tree lower. In the weighted algorithm, we
always put the smaller tree lower. How we,
let's see how we implement that. Let's see
a demo first. Okay, so again start out in
our normal starting position, where
everybody's in their own tree. And for
when there's only two items to link it, it
works, works the same way as before. But
now, when we have eight to merge with four
and three, we put the eight as the child,
no matter which order their arguments
came, because it's the smaller tree. So,
six and five doesn't matter, whichever one
goes down doesn't matter. Nine and four,
so now, nine is the small one four is the
big one. So, nine is going to be the one
that goes down below. Two and one, five
and zero. So now, five and zero five is in
the bigger tree so zero goes below. Seven
and two, two is in the bigger tree so
seven goes below. Six and one they're in
equal size trees. And seven and three,
three is in the smaller tree so it goes
below. So, the weighted algorithm always
makes sure that the smaller tree goes
below. And again, we wind up with a single
tree representing all the objects. But
this time, we h ave some guarantee that no
item is too far from the root and we'll
talk about that explicitly in a second.
So, here's an example that shows the
effect of doing the weighted quick union
where we always put the smaller tree down
below for the same set of union commands.
This is with a hundred sites and 88 union
operations. You can see in the top the big
tree has some trees, some nodes, a fair
distance from the root. In the bottom, for
the weighted algorithm all the nodes are
within distance four from the root. The
average distance to the root is much, much
lower. Let's look at the Java
implementation and then we'll look in more
detail at, at that quantitative
information. So, we used the same data
structure except, now we need an extra
array, that for each item, gives the
number of objects in the tree routed at
that item. That will maintain in the union
operation. Find implementation is
identical to for quick union, you're just
checking whether the roots are equal. For
the union implementation, we're going to
modify the code to check the sizes. And
link the root of the smaller tree to the
root of the larger tree in each case. And
then after changing the id link, we also
change the size array. If we make id, i a
child of j, then we have to increment the
size of j's tree by the size of i's tree.
Or if we do the other way around, then we
have to increment the size of i's tree by
the size of j's tree. So, that's the full
code in white for implementing quick
union. So, not very much code but much,
much better performance. In fact we can
analyze the running time mathematically
and show that defined operation, it takes
time proportional to how far down the
trees are in the node in the tree, the
nodes are in the tree, but we can show
that it's guaranteed that the depth of any
node in the tree is at most the logarithm
to the base two of N. We use the notation
Lg always for logarithm to the base two.
And, and, so for, if N is a thousand,
that's going to be ten, if N is a million
that's twenty, if N is a billion that's
30. It's a very small number compared to
N. So, let's look at the proof of that. We
do some mathematical proofs in, in this
course when they're critical such as this
one. And why is it true that the depth of
any node x is, at most, log base two of N?
Well, the key to understanding that is to,
take a look at exactly when does the depth
of any node increase? When does it go down
further in the tree? Well. The x's depth
will increase by one, when its tree, T1 in
this diagram, is merged into some other
tree, T2 in this diagram. Well, at that
point we said we only do that if the size
of T2 was bigger than the or equal to size
of T1. So, when the depth of x increases,
the size of its tree at least doubles. So,
that's the key because that means that the
size of the tree containing x can double
at most log N times because if you start
with one and double log N times, you get N
and there's only N nodes in the tree. So,
that's a sketch of a proof that the depth
of any node x is at most log base two of
N. And that has profound impact on the
performance of this algorithm. Now instead
of the initialization always takes time
proportional to N. But now, both the union
and the connected or find operation takes
time proportional to log base two of N.
And that is an algorithm that scales. If N
grows from a million to a billion, that
cost goes from twenty to 30, which is
quite not acceptable. Now, this was very
easy to implement and, and we could stop
but usually, what happens in the design of
algorithms is now that we understand what
it is that gains performance, we take a
look and see, well, could we improve it
even further. And in this case, it's very
easy to improve it much, much more. And
that's the idea of path compression. And
this idea is that, well, when we're trying
to find the root of the tree containing a,
a given node. We're touching all the nodes
on the path from that node to the root.
While we're doi ng that we might as well
make each one of those just point to the
root. There's no reason not to. So when
we're looking, we're trying to find the
root of, of P. After we find it, we might
as well just go back and make every node
on that path just point to the root.
That's going to be a constant extra cost.
We went up the path once to find the root.
Now, we'll go up again to just flatten the
tree out. And the reason would be, no
reason not to do that. We had one line of
code to flatten the tree, amazingly.
Actually to make a one liner code, we use
a, a simple variant where we make every
other node in the path point to its
grandparent on the way up the tree. Now,
that's not quite as good as totally
flattening actually in practice that it
actually is just about as good. So, with
one line of code, we can keep the trees
almost completely flat. Now, this
algorithm people discovered rather early
on after figuring out the weighting and it
turns out to be fascinating to analyze
quite beyond our scope. But we mentioned
this example to illustrate how even a
simple algorithmah, can have interesting
and complex analysis. And what was proved
by Hopcroft Ulman and Tarjan was that if
you have N objects, any sequence of M
union and find operations will touch the
array at most a c (N + M lg star N) times.
And now, lg N is kind of a funny function.
It's the number of times you have to take
the log of N to get one. And the way to
think, it's called the iterated log
function. And in the real world, it's best
to think of that as a number less than
five because lg two^ 65536 is five. So,
that means that the running time of
weighted quick union with path compression
is going be linear in the real world and
actually could be improved to even a more
interesting function called the Ackermann
function, which is even more slowly
growing than lg. And another point
about this is it seems that this is
so close to being linear that is t ime
proportional to N instead of time
proportional to N times the slowly growing
function in N. Is there a simple algorithm
that is linear? And people, looked for a
long time for that, and actually it works
out to be the case that we can prove that
there is no such algorithm. So, there's a
lot of theory that goes behind the
algorithms that we use. And it's important
for us to know that theory and that will
help us decide how to choose which
algorithms we're going to use in practice,
and where to concentrate our effort in
trying to find better algorithms. It's
amazing fact that was eventually proved by
Friedman and Sachs, that there is no
linear time algorithm for the union find
problem. But weighted quick union with
path compression in practice is, is close
enough that it's going to enable the
solution of huge problems. So, that's our
summary for algorithms for solving the
dynamic connectivity problem. With using
weighted quick union and with path
compression, we can solve problems that
could not otherwise be addressed. For
example, if you have a billion operations
and a billion objects I said before it
might take thirty years. We can do it in
six seconds. Now, and what's most
important to recognize about this is that
its the algorithm design that enables the
solution to the problem. A faster computer
wouldn't help much. You could spend
millions on a super computer, and maybe
you could get it done in six years instead
of 30, or in two months but with a fast
logarithm, you can do it in seconds, in
seconds on your own PC.