Welcome back to algorithms. Today, we're
going to talk about the union find
problem. A set of algorithms for solving
the so-called dynamic connectivity
problem. We'll look at two classic
algorithms. Quick Find and Quick Union,
and some applications and improvements of
those algorithms. The subtext of today's
lecture really is to go through the steps
that we'll follow over and over again to
develop a useful algorithm. The first step
is to model the problem. Try to
understand, basically, what are the main
elements of the problem that need to be
solved. Then we'll find some algorithm to
solve the problem. In many cases, the
first algorithm we come up with would be
fast enough and maybe it fits in memory
and, we'll go ahead and use it, and be off
and running. But in many other cases maybe
it's not fast enough, or there's not
enough memory. So, what we do is try to
figure out why, find a way to address
whatever's causing that problem, find a
new algorithm and iterate until we're
satisfied. This is the scientific approach
to designing and analyzing algorithms,
where we build mathematical models to try
and understand what's going on, and then
we do experiments to validate those models
and help us improve things. So, first
we'll talk about the dynamic connectivity
problem, the model of the problem for
union find. So, here's the idea. They're
going to have a set of N objects. Doesn't
really matter what they are. We're going
to use the numbers, zero through N to
model our objects. And then, we have the
idea of a connection between two objects.
And, we'll, postulate that there's going
to be a command that says, connect two
objects. Given two objects, provide a
connection between them. And then key part
of the problem is find query or the
connected query, which just asks, is there
a path connecting the two objects. So for
example, in this set of ten objects, we
performed already, a bunch of union
commands, connecting four and three, three
and eight, six and five, nine and four,
two and one. And now we might have a
connected query that says, is zero connect
ed to seven? Well, in this case, there is
no connection, so we say no. But if we ask
is eight connected to nine? We are going
to say yes, even no we don't have a direct
connection between eight and nine. There
is a path from eight to three to four to
nine. So, that's our problem, to be able
to officially support these two commands
for given set of objects. Now, let's say
we add a union five, zero. So, that
creates a connection between five and
zero. Seven and two creates a connection
between seven and two. And six and one,
between six and one. So, now if we ask our
zero connected to seven, well one and zero
we can do that too. And that's a redundant
connection. And now, if we ask is zero
connected to seven we're going to answer
yes. So that's our problem, intermix
union, commands and connected queries and
we need to be able to officially support
those commands for a large number of
objects. So, here's a much bigger example.
And you can see that we're going to need
efficient algorithms for this. First of
all, you can see we're going to need a
computer for this. It would take quite,
quite some time for a human to figure out
whether there's a connection. In this case
there is a connection. Now, the algorithms
that we're looking at today are not going
to actually give the path connecting the
two objects. It's just going to be able to
answer the question, is there a path? In
part two of the course, we'll consider
algorithms that explicitly find paths.
They're not as efficient as union find
because they have more work to do. Now,
applications of these, these algorithms
involve objects of all types. These are
used for digital photos, where the objects
are pixels they're used for networks,
where the objects are computers, social
networks, where it's people, or computer
chips, where it's circuit elements or
abstract things like variable names in a
program, or elements in a mathematical
set, or physical things like metallic
sites in a composite system. So, all
different types of objects for, but for
programming we're going to associate each
object with a name and we'll just name the
objects with a number, integers from zero
to N-1. That's a very convenient initial
starting point for our programs because we
can use integers as an index into an array
then, and then quickly access information
relevant to each object. And it also just
supresses a lot of details that are not
relevant to union find. In fact, to make
this mapping from an object name to the
integer zero through N - one is to find
application of a symbol table or a
searching algorithm, which is one of the
things that we'll be studying later in
this course algorithms and data structures
for solving that problem. Now, the
connections, well, we need, a few abstract
properties that these connections have to
satisfy. And they're all quite natural and
intuitive. So we assume that is connected
to is an equivalence relation. That is,
every object's connected to itself, it's
symmetric. If P's connected to Q, then Q's
connected to P, and it's transitive. If
P's connected to Q, and Q's connected to
R, then P's connected to R. Now these
properties are very intuitive. But it's
worthwhile to state them explicitly and
make sure that our algorithms maintain
them. When we have an equivalence relation
a set of objects and connections divide
into subsets called connected components.
A connected component is a maximal set of
objects that's mutually connected. For
example in this small example here,
there's three connected components. One
consisting of just object zero, second one
objects one, four and five. And third one
the other four objects. And these
components have the property that if any
two objects in them are connected and
there is no object outside that is
connected to those objects, that's
connected components. Our algorithms will
gain efficiency by maintaining connected
components and using that knowledge to
efficiently answer the query that's, that
they're presented with. Okay, so to
implement the operations, we have to find
query and the union command. And so we're
going to mai ntain the connected
components. The find is going to have to
check if two objects are in the same
component and the union command is going
to have to replace components containing
two objects with their union. So, for
example, if we have these components, and
we get the command to union connect, two
and five. Essentially, we need to merge
the connected components containing the
one containing two or the one containing
five to get a big connected components and
now we have only two connected components.
All of that leads up to, in a programming
world to specifying, a data type which is
simply specification of the methods that
we are want to going to implement in order
to solve this problem. So you know,
typical Java model, what we will do is
create a class called UF that contains two
methods, one to implement union, the other
one to implement connected, which returns
a boolean. The constructor, takes SR unit,
the number of objects, so that it can
build data structure based on the number
of objects. So, and we have to, bear in
mind, as we're building our logarithms,
that both the number of objects can be
huge, but also, the number of operations.
We can have a, a very large number, of
union and connected, operations and our
algorithms are going to have to be
efficient, under those conditions. One of
the practices that will follow often in
this course is to check our API design
before getting too far into dealing with
the problem, by building a client that is
going to use the data type that we
develop. So, for this example, we've got a
client that, Will read information from
standard input. First, an integer which is
the number of objects that are going to be
processed. And then a series of pairs of
object names. And what the client does is
it, it'll, first it'll read the integer
from standard input, and create a, a UF
object. And then as long as standard input
is not empty, it's going to read two
integers from the input. And if they're
not connected, then it'll connect them and
print them out. If they are connected
it'll ignore. So, that's our test client
and that's a fine test client to make sure
that any implementation does what we
expect that it will. So, that's the setup.
We've described the operations we want to
implement all the way down to code and we
have client code that we're going to have
to be able to service with our