Observing what's happening as we did in
the last section it gives us a, a way to
predict performance but it really doesn't
help us understand what the algorithm's
doing. So next, we're going to look at
mathematical model. A way to get a better
concept of what's really happening. Again,
this concept was really developed and
popularized by Don Knuth starting in the
late 60s. At that time, computer systems
were really becoming complicated for the
first time. And computer scientists were
concerned about whether we really were
going to be able to understand what's
going on. And Knuth was very direct in
saying that this is something that we
certainly can do. We can calculate the
total running time of a program by
identifying all the basic operations,
figuring out the cost, figuring out the
frequency of execution and summing up the
cost times frequency for all the
operations. You have to analyze the
program to determine what set of
operations and the cost depends on the
machine and the computer in the system is
what we talked about before. The frequency
leads us to mathematics because it depends
on the algorithm and input data. Knuth has
written a series of books that give very
detailed and all exact analyses within a
particular computer model for a wide range
of algorithms. So, from Knuth, we know
that in principle, we can get accurate
mathematical models for the performance of
algorithms or programs and operation. All
right. So what, what does this process
look like? Well you can, if you want run
experiments. In, in ancient times, we
would actually look at the computer manual
and every computer came with a manual that
said precisely how long each instruction
would take. But nowadays, it's a little
more complicated. So, we run experiments
and, and you can go ahead and do a billion
ads and figure out that maybe on your
computer, an ad takes 2.1 nano seconds. Or
you can do more complicated function s
like computer sign or an arc tangent
although that's already getting close to
the analysis of algorithms. So, there's
some way to determine the costs of the
basic operations. And so, we'll just in
most, most of the cases we'll just
postulate that it's some constant and you
can figure out what the constant is.
Although when we're working with a
collection of objects, of anobjects there
are some things that takes time
proportional to N like if you're going to
allocate a array of size N it takes time
proportional to N because in Java the
default is that all the elements in the
array initialize to zero. In other
operations it depends on the system
implementation and an important one is
string concatenation. If you concatenate
two strings the running time is
proportional to the length of the string.
In many novices programming in Java, make
a mistake of assuming that's a constant
time operation when its not. Alright, so
that's the cost of each operation. More
interesting is the frequency of operation,
of execution of the operations. So this is
a, a, it's a very simple variant of the
three sum problem. That's the one sum
problem. That's how many numbers are
actually equal to zero? How many single
numbers add up to zero? So, that one, it's
just one four loop, and we go through, and
we tested the number zero and increment or
count. And by analyzing that code you can
see that I and count have to be declared
and then they have to be assigned to zero.
There's compares of i against N and
there's N + one of them. There's compares
of A(i) against zero, there's N of those,
N array axises and the number incremented
is number of times there's an increment is
variable. I has incremented N times, but
count could be incremented any number from
zero to N times. And so that frequency is
dependent on the input data. Or we might
need a model for describing that or maybe
there's other operations that are more e
xpensive and we won't need to worry about
that. So, let's look at the next more
complicated problem is what about the
frequency of execution of instructions in
this program which is the two sum problem,
how many pairs of integers sum to zero?
Well, in this case, you have to do a
little bit of math to see that when we
when i goes from zero to N, and j goes
from i + a to N the number of compares
that we do work, plus array axises that we
do is two for each time the if statement
is executed for Ai and Aj and that time
is, thing is executed N - one times the
first time through the loop and N -two^2
and so forth. It's the sum of the integers
from zero up to N - one which is a simple
discrete sum one-half N, (N - one) and
since, and since we're doing it twice the
number of array axises is N, N - one. So,
we can go ahead and get these actual exact
counts. But already, it's getting a little
bit tedious to do that. And as far back as
Turing who also knew that and as well as
Babbage did, that we want to have a
measure of the amount of work involved in
the process. He recognized that you didn't
want to necessarily go through and do it
in full detail. It's still helpful to have
a crude estimate. So, you could count up
the number of times that every operation
is applied, give it weights and, and count
the [inaudible] and so forth. But maybe we
should just count the ones that are most
expensive that's what Turing said in 1947,
and realistically that's what we do
nowadays. So rather than going in and
counting every little detail, we take some
basic operation that's maybe the most
expensive and or and or the one that's
executed the most often. The one that cost
and frequency is the highest and use that
as a proxy for running time. Essentially,
making the hypothesis that the running
time is, is going to grow like a constant
times [inaudible], So, in this case, were
going to pick array axises. So, that's the
first simplification. And the second
simplification is that we're going to
ignore low order terms in the formulas
that we derive. And there's an easy way to
do that. It's called the tilde notation
and, and the idea is when N is large in a
formula like this the N^3 term is much,
much higher than the N term or sixteen. In
fact, so much so that we wouldn't even
hardly notice these low order terms. So,
all of these formulas are tilde one-sixth
N^3 and that's a fine representative or
approximate, approximation to these
quantities. And it greatly simplifies
their calculations to for a, through a way
to lower, lower to terms like this. So, by
focusing on one operation and , throwing
away the tildes, the lower the terms and
this is the technical definition of tilde.
It's just, F(N) tilde G (N) means the
limit as FN or GN equals one, and you can
check that that's going to hold in these
kinds of situations. So, that greatly
simplifies the frequency counts. And if
we're only picking one thing we're just
talking about tilde N^2 and maybe another
tilde N^2 for the increment for the two
sum problems, okay. So again, when N is
large, the terms are negligible and when N
is really small, they're not negligible
but we don't really care because we're
trying to estimate running times for large
N and running times for small N are going
to be small no matter what. All right, so
now, we're using both the cost model and
the tilde notation and then we can simply
say, that this program uses tilde N^2
squared array axises and have implicit the
hypothesis that we think the running time
is going to be tilde, a constant, times N
squared. Okay, we now what about three
sums, let's do a, a real problem. So now,
we have the triple loop. And then, we have
to do a more complicated combinatorial
problem in is not that big a deal really
we are looking at the distinct number of
ways you can chose three things out of N
and that 's binomial coefficient. And
again, doing the math and using the tilde,
it's just tilde one-sixth N^3 three ray
axises for each triple so we can say
one-half N^3. So we're not computing and
summing the costs of all operations that's
too much work. We're picking the most
expensive in terms of cost times frequency
and approximating that and trying to get a
good model for the running time. So now
most, we're not going to do of a full
discrete mathematics in this course but
there's some basic things that we'll want
to use and are, are not that difficult to
understand. So, a lot of times we find out
that we need to come up with an estimate
of a discrete sum. Like we did for one +
two up to N. Or some of the squares or
other things like the three sum triple
loop. And so actually if you've had basic
calculus, one way to think of it as to
just replace the sum with an interval,
integral. That usually works or we can do
the math and use the so-called
Euler–Maclaurin summation formula to get
a true approximation. But if you think of
it this way you'll believe us when we say
that, that thing is tilde one-half N^2 or
sum of one+ one-half + one-third up to one
/ N. That's like integral from x = one to
N1 / x and that's natural log of N. Now
even the three sum triple loop kind of if
you're used to multiple integrals, I will
quickly give you the one-sixth N^3.
There's many more and other techniques
that we could use for this. And we're not
going to teach all that, but we'll
sometimes refer to results of this type.
Alright, so in principle, Knuth tells us
that accurate mathematical models are
available in practice, we can get really
complicated formulas. We also might need
some advance mathematics that the
theoretician will revel in. But that maybe
people learning algorithms for the first
time might not be expected to know. So in
the end careful exact models are best,
best left for exit, experts. There's
really a lot of things that can go on. On
the other hand approximate models are
definitely worthwhile. And for all the
algorithms that we consider we'll try to
communicate a reasonable approximate model
that can be used to describe the running
time. Sometimes we'll give the
mathematical proofs and other times we'll
have to just cite the work of some expert.