Welcome back. Today we're going to do some
math and some science. Not a lot, but we
need to have a scientific basis for
understanding the performance of our
algorithms to properly deploy them in
practise. So today we're going to talk,
about how to, observe performance
characteristics of algorithms. We're going
to look at how to make mathematical models
and how to classify algorithms according
to the order of growth of their running
time. We'll talk a bit about the theory of
algorithms and also how to analyze memory
usage. So to put this all in perspective,
we're going to think about these issues
from the point of view of different types
of characters. So the first one is the
programmer who needs to solve a problem
and get it working and get it deployed.
Second one is the client who wants to use
the whatever program did to get the job
done. Third one is the theoretician,
that's somebody who really wants to
understand what's going on. And, and the
last one is kind of a team, this basic
blocking and tackling sometimes necessary
to get, you know, all these things done.
So, there's a little bit of each one of
these in today's lecture. And actually
when you're a student you have to think
that you might be playing any or all of
these roles some day. So, it's pretty
important to understand the different
points of view. So, the key that we'll
focus on is running time. And actually the
idea of understanding the running time of
a computation goes way back even to
Babbage and probably before. And here's a
quote from Babbage, "As soon as an
analytical engine exists, it will
necessarily guide the future course of the
science. Whenever any result is sought by
its aid, the question will arise by what
course of calculation can these results be
arrived at by the machine in the shortest
time". If you look at Babbage's machine
called the analytic engine, it's got a
crank on it. And literally the concern
that Babbage had in knowing how long a
computation would take is, how m any times
do we have to turn the crank. It's, it's
not that different, in today's world. The
crank may be something electronic that's
happening a billion times a second. But
still, we're looking for, how many times
does some discreet operation have to be
performed in order to get a computation
done. So, there are lot of reasons to
analyse algorithms. In the context of this
course we are mainly interested in
performance prediction. And we also want
to compare the performance of different
algorithms for the same task, and to be
able to provide some guarantees on how
well they perform. Along with this, is
understanding some theoretical basis for
how algorithms perform. But primarily, the
practical reason that we want to be
analyzing algorithms and understanding
them is to avoid performance bugs. We want
to have some confidence that our
algorithms going to complete the job in
the amount of time, that, that we think it
will. And it's very, very frequent to see,
in today's computational infrastructure, a
situation where the client gets bad
performance, because the programmer did
not understand the performance
characteristics of the algorithm. And
today's lecture is about trying to avoid
that. Now, we're going to focus on
performance and comparing algorithms in
this course. There's later courses in
typical computer science curricula that
have more information about the
theoretical basis of algorithms and I'll
mention a little bit about that later on.
But our focus is on being able to predict
performance and comparing algorithms. Now
there's a long list of success stories in
designing algorithm with better
performance in, in enabling the solution
of problems that would otherwise not be
solved. And I'll just give a couple of
examples. One of the first and most famous
is the so called FFT algorithm. That's an
algorithm for breaking down the wave form
of n samples of a signal into periodic
components. And that's at the basis for
dvds and jpegs and, and many other appl
ications. There's an easy way to do it
that takes time proportional to N^2. But
the FFT algorithm, takes only N log N
steps. And the difference between N log N
and N^2 is, is the difference between
being able to solve a large problem and
not being able to solve it. A lot of the
digital technology, digital media
technology that we have today is enabled
by that fast algorithm. Another example
was actually developed by Andrew Appel,
who's now the chair of computer science
here at Princeton. And it was developed
when he was an undergraduate for his
senior thesis. It's a fast algorithm for
the N body simulation problem. The easy
algorithm takes time proportional to N^2,
but Appel's algorithm was an N log N
algorithm that again, meant that
scientists can do N body simulation for
huge values of N. And that enables new
research. S0, o the challenge is that we
usually face is, will my program be able
to solve a large practical input? And, and
actually, the working programmer is
actually faced with that all the time.
Why, why is my program running so slowly?
Why does it run out of memory? And that's
faced programmers for a really long time
and the insight to address this. Deuter
Kanoof, in the 1970s, was that, we really
can use the scientific method to
understand the performance of algorithms
in operation. Maybe we're not unlocking
new secrets of the universe but, we can
use the, scientific method, and treat the
computer, as something to be studied in
that way and come to an understanding of
how our program are going to perform. And
let's take a look at that in more detail.
So this just a quick summary of what we
mean by the scientific method, which has,
been successful for a couple of centuries
now. So, what we're going to do is,
observe from some feature of the natural
world. In this case, it's going to be the
running time of our program on a computer.
Then we're going to develop hypothesis
some model that's consistent with the
observations, and we're going to hope
that, that hypothesis is good enough that
it'll allow us to predict something.
Usually predict a running time for larger
problem size, or on a different computer.
And then we'll verify the predictions by
making more observations, and validate
until we're comfortable that our model
hypothesis and observations all agree.
That's a way to get comfort that we
understand the performance of our
programs. Now, the within the scientific
method, there's some basic principles and
the, the first is that if you're going to
run experiments, you should expect that
somebody else should be able to run
experiments and get the same result. And
also the hypotheses have to have a
specific property that the experiment can
show the hypothesis to be wrong. So, it
has to be carefully crafted, and we'll be
sure to try to do that. So, and again the
future of the natural world that we're
studying is some particular computer that
exists in the natural world. It changes
the algorithm from an abstraction to a,
some, some kind of actual physical thing
happening like electrons racing around
inside the computer.