So far, we've been talking about running
time. Now we have to talk about the memory
requirements over our programs as well.
Well, the basics are we want to know how
many bits the program use or bytes, eight
bits at a time. And actually, we'll be
talking in terms of millions of bits or
billions of bits and actually surprisingly
there is a controversy about even these
basic definitions. Computer scientists
think of a million bits is two^20 and a
billion is two^30 because that's a number
of possible things that you can fit into
30 bits and everything is consistent with
our calculations. Other scientists stick
to one million or one billion for a lots
of reasons we'll usually use two^20, I
mean, a megabyte. Now an old computers we
used to for many years, we use a 32-bit
machine so that pointers were four bytes.
Just in recent years we've mostly switched
to a model where machines are 64-bits and
pointers are eight bytes. That allows us
to address much more memory but pointers
use much more space and actually this
transition caused a lot of problems
initially because programs were using way
more space than people thought they
should. You're not going to have to go
through this kind of transition the way
that we did because 64 bits is definitely
enough to address anything that you might
need to address, two^64 is really a huge
number. So in terms of bytes we have to
start out with typical memory usage. Now,
again, this is very dependent on machine
and implementation but these numbers are
reasonable and are found on typical
implementations. So a boolean, it will be
nice of a boolean just took a bit cuz
that's just true or false but actually,
usually we have to count for a byte for a
boolean. All byte is a byte. Character
nowadays is two byte, 16-bit characters.
Not that a long ago we used eight bit for
chars. Integer regular int is four bytes
or 32 bits and a float is also four bytes
long int is eight and a double is eight.
Usually, we use double for floating point
and ints for integers in most
applications. So, that's for primitive
types. And then for arrays there's a
certain amount of overhead for making an
array and then if there's n items, it's
whatever the cost of the primitive type
times n so an array of doubles is say 8n +
24. And two-dimensional array then well,
we can go ahead and compute the exact
thing but now, now, it's time to use, the
tilde notation. And then for arrays we
could say a double is tilde 8n for
one-dimensional. For two-dimensional,
two-dimensional array of doubles is tilde
8mn. And there's extra terms for the over
head but for large m and n that's going to
be pretty accurate. So, that's our basic
usage for primitive types and arrays in a
typical Java implementation. Now, a lot of
our programs and objects like link list
and so forth. So, we have to also factor
in object overhead to crossover reference
and also there's padding built in, in
typical implementations to make it so that
each object has used a multiple of eight
bytes. So, for example if you have a date
object that had three int instance
variables then that object would take a
total of 32 bytes. Each int takes four
bytes, object overhead is sixteen bytes.
It needs four bytes for padding so it's a
total of 32 bytes. So and the other one
that often comes up is a string and the
string is a little bit more complicated
than a than an array but the typical
implementation of a string in Java has a,
a reference out to an array of characters
and then, its got int values for offset
count in a hash value and then some
padding and adding it all together the
[cough] cost of the string is about 2n +
64 bytes. So, these are the basics that we
need to analyze the memory usage for a
typical Java program. A h, so for
primitive, for data type value, if it's a
primitive type it's four for an eight, and
eight for a double, and so forth. If it's
a reference, it's going to be eight bytes
and that's for the pointer takes array 24
bytes plus the memory for each entry in an
object sixteen bytes plus the memory for
the instance variable plus if there's an
inner class , it's another eight bytes as
we talked about with nodes for link list.
And then there's the padding. So then we
have to, to think about who is responsible
for referenced objects, you know, in, in
some cases. And we'll take care of that
when we get to these situations. So, as an
example, a simple example of memory use
analysis, let's take a look at how much
memory are rated quick union UF function
from a, a few lectures ago, uses as a
function of n. And there's only a couple
of memory elements and each one of them
are easily analyzed using the basics that
we just gave it's an object so the sixteen
bytes of object overhead there's two int
arrays. Each one of them have array
overhead of 24 plus and then 4n for the n
entries. Each and vn entries takes four
bytes and there's four bytes for the count
and there's four bytes for the padding and
if you add it altogether it gets 8n + 88
which is tilde 8n and again, all that's
saying is when n is large, all we are
going to care about in terms of analyzing
the memory is that we've got [cough] 2n
integers two arrays of size n each one of
which takes four bytes for a grand total
of 8n bytes. Okay. So, in summary we
really can figure out how many times we
have to turn the crank on modern
computers. We can do it with empirical
analysis where we actually execute the
program, can do experiments and use
[inaudible] power law, formulate
hypothesis and make predictions. But we
can do more, we can do mathematical
analysis where we can identify the most
costly operations, analyze the frequency
of execution of those operations and using
the tilde notation to simplify analysis.
We can actually explain the behavior, not
just predict it. And this is a fine
example of the use of the scientific
method to understand the artifacts that
we're studying, the algorithms. Our
mathematical models are usually
independent of a particular computer
system and even implied to machines that
are not yet built. But we always validate
our mathematical models by running
experiments on real machines so that we
can be confident where we're making
predictions and analyzing algorithms.