Okay, so the first step is to be able to
make some observations about the running
time of the programs. And for analysis of
algorithms that's easier than in a lot of
scientific disciplines, as we'll see. For
a running example we're going to use the
so-called 3-sum problem. And it's an easy
to state problem. If you've got N distinct
integers, how many triple sum to exactly
zero? For example in this file 8ints.text.
Text which has eight integers in it.
There's four triples that sum to zero. 30
- 40, ten. 30 - twenty - ten and so forth
and so our goal is to write a program that
can compute this quantity for any input
file, any set of N integers. This is
actually a, an extremely important
computation that's deeply related to many
problems in computational geometry which
is a branch of computer science that
covers the algorithms and underlying
science related to graphics and movies and
geometric models of all sort. So this is a
actually an important practical problem.
But it's a simple one to write code for in
a view you could write down this program
without much effort. It's a, got a static
method count that is going to go ahead and
take a integer array as an argument. And,
is that, that's a number of integers,
that's the length of the array. We will
start with a variable count equals zero,
and then a triple for loop, that checks
each triple I j k, we go I from one and j
from I+1 to n, and k from j+1 to n, so
that we get each triple just once. And
then if I+j, ai + aj + ak = zero, we
increment the count. Alright. And after
that triple four loop, we return the
count. And then the main method, in this
simple class just reads in, all the
integers, and prints out the count. So
that's a brute force algorithm that is a
fine method for solving the three sum
problem, now what we're interested in is
how much time does this take as a function
of' n? Well, one to time our program is to
is just look at the watch. If you have a
stopwatch, or look at the clock or your
phone, or whatever you might need you can
just go ahead and time it if you want or
we have, Java has this part of it's
standard library, a stopwatch class that
will go ahead and compute a lapse time.
So, in order, anytime you run a program,
if it is setup to easily take input of
different sizes, a natural thing to do, is
just run it for bigger sizes. So for eight
ints this program takes not too much time,
for 1000 ints it takes half a second. For
2,000. Takes more time. That's 3.7 seconds
run it again, still takes 3.7 seconds for
4,000, so each time we're doubling the
size of the input and it's definitely
taking more time each time. And actually
as we'll see if programmers who get in the
habit of testing or any time on their
program in this way can get so that you
can actually pretty easily and quickly
evaluate when it's going to finish. In
fact. While you're waiting for it to
finish you can often figure it out. So
that one took 30 seconds for 4K and
definitely we could figure it out how long
it's going to take for 8K before it
finishes, and you'll see how in just a
second. I'm not going to wait right now.
You can think about what you think. Okay
so [cough] that's empirical analysis,
analysis. Run it for various input sizes
and measure their running time. Now if
this were some scientific problem where we
were counting something that happen in the
natural world. The number of ants in an
ant hill or whatever then we'd have only a
few data points and we would try to
understand whats was going on by doing a
plot of or running time with quite
interested in on the Y axis and problem
size with the X axis. Hit a curve like
this and actually whats science usually do
because of some many problems fall into
out of this class is do the plot as a lg,
lg plot. If you do it as a lg, lg plot
very often you'll get a straight line. And
the slope of the straight line is the key
to what's going on. In this case, the
slope of the straight line is three and so
you can run what's called a regression to
fit a late, the straight line through the
data points. And then, it's not difficult
to show to do the math to show that if you
get a straight line and the slope is B,
then your function is proportional to A,
N^B. That's called the power law. And
that's true of many, many scientific
problems including most algorithms. So
here's a little bit of the math for that.
So the straight line means that since we
did a lg, lg plot with powers of two, that
lg(T(N) = B lg N + C. And we have our
empirical values of B and C and then if
you raise both sides of that equation to
two to that power then you get T(N) = a
constant times N^B. So right away just
from observation we have a pretty good
model for the running time for our
program, we can figure and do the math and
figure out that it seems as though the
running time is about ten^-10 N^3 seconds.
We can use that hypothesis to go ahead and
make predictions. Just plug in for
different values of N and it says it will
take us 400 seconds for 16,000. 400
seconds is plenty of time but now we can
go ahead and invest and run that
experiment and sure enough we're pretty
close to that 408 seconds when we run it.
And now we can make a prediction for
32,000 or for or for whatever else we
might be interested in. The model helps us
do predictions without investing the
expense to run the experiments. In fact,
in this situation if there is a power law,
and again in a very great majority of
computer algorithm running times is going
to be a power law. What we can do is just
double the size of the input each time the
way we were and take the ratio of the
running times for N and 2N. And if you do
that, that ratio going to converge to a
constant. And in fact the log of the ratio
is going to converge to that constant,
which is the exponent of N and the running
time. And you just need a little math to
check that one, but that's a very easy and
natural way to go ahead and predict
running times. So that's what I said
before is, so we have this quick way to
estimate B in the power law relationsh ip.
How do we estimate A? Well we can just run
it and solve for A. So once we've decided
that, that exponent is three let's run it
for some big N and we get pretty close
model to the one we had from plotting
things. So it's almost identical
hypothesis and we just got it by running
the program double N each time. Okay so
there is a lot of effects in trying to
understand the running time of a program
on, on your machine. [cough] So. Key
effects are independent of what computer
it is. And that's the algorithm you're
using and what's the data. And that's
going to really determine the exponent in
the power law. And then there's a lot of,
system dependent effects. What kind of
hardware do you have? Do you have a fast
computer or a slow one? What kind of
software? What's going on in your
computer? All of those things really
determine the constant A in the power law.
So. In modern systems it is so much going
on in the hardware and software, it's
sometimes difficult to get really precise
measurements. But on the other hand we
don't have to sacrifice animals, or fly to
another planet the way they do in other
sciences, we can just run a huge number of
experiments and usually take care of
understanding these kind of effects.