Now, fortunately when we analyze
algorithms, actually not too many
different functions arise and actually
that property allows us to really classify
algorithms according to their performance
as the problem size grows. So that's what
we'll talk about next. So the good news is
there's only these few functions turn up
about the algorithms that we are
interested in. We can craft things that
have other functions and there are counter
examples to this. But really a great
number of the algorithms that we consider
are described by these few functions and
that are plotted here. And [cough] the
when we are talking about the order of
growth, we are not talking about the
leading constant. Normally we'll say the
running time of the algorithm is
proportional to N log N. That means we
that we think that our hypothesis is that
the running time is tilde C lg N, N lg N,
where C is some constant. And in these
plots, these are lg, lg plots that not
really give a good idea of what's going
on. If a order of growth is logarithmic or
constant, doesn't matter how big the thing
is. It's going to be fast of the running
time for is T for say a thousand, and for
half a million it will be pretty close to
T. If it's linear, if it's auto growth is
proportional to N then as the running
time, as the size increases the running
time increases correspondingly. And the
same is true, almost, if it's N log N. So
those are the algorithms that we strive
for. They scale with the input size. As
the input grows, so grows the running
time. And that's, a reasonable situation
to be in. As we talked about when we
talked about Union-find. If it's
quadratic, the running time grows much
faster than the input size. And it's not
feasible to use such an algorithm for
large inputs. And qubic is even worse. So
what we find is for many algorithms our
first task is really, simply, make sure
it's not quadratic or qubit. And these
order of growth classifications actually
come from kind of simple patterns in terms
of the code that we write. So if our code
has no loops in it, then the order of
growth is going to be constant. If our
code has some kind of loop where the
input's divided in half, and so binary
search algorithm is an example of that.
Then our order growth will be logarithmic
and we'll take a look at that analysis and
but if you do the doubling test, it grows
almost linearly, if you have a huge input
and you double the size it's, it's still
going to be I'm sorry, not linearly,
constant just like if it's constant.
You'll hardly notice that lg N. If you
have a loop where you touch everything in
your input. Than the running time is
linear, proportional to end so a typical
example of that would be find the maximum,
or to count the number of zeros. Our one
some problem. A very interesting category
is a so-called N lg N algorithms or linear
rhythmic algorithms. And those are the
ones that arise from a particular
algorithms design technique called the
divide and conquer. And the Mergesort
algorithm, which we'll talk about in a
couple of weeks, is a prime example of
that. And then if you have double four
loops like our two sum algorithm, that's
going to be time proportional to N^2. As
we saw, that's quadratic, or triple four
loop like our 3-sum algorithm, that's
going to be cubic or time proportional to
N^3. For a quadratic algorithm or a cubic
algorithm, the doubling factor is four or
eight as the input size double for cubic
algorithm, the running time goes up by a
factor of eight, and that's the kind of
calculation that you can do in your head
while waiting for a program to finish.
There's also a category of algorithms
who's running time is exponential and in
those algorithms n doesn't get very large
at and we'll talk about those at the end
part two of the course. So these are some
practical implications of, of the order
growth. And we really dwell on this too
much, except to come back to the point
that the algorithms we are really
interested in, that can solve huge
problems, are the linear and N lg N
algorithms. Because even now a quadr atic
algorithm on a typical fast computer could
only solve problems and saying that tens
of thousands in a cubic algorithm only in
the size of thousands. And nowadays those
are just not useful because the amount of
data that we have is more like the
millions or billions or trillions. That
fact is becoming more and more evident as
time wears on the ancient times would have
some discussion about whether quadratic
algorithm might be useful but the
situation gets worse as the time goes on,
so we need better algorithms. To
illustrate the process of developing a
mathematical model for describing a
performance through an algorithm, we'll
look at a familiar algorithm called binary
search. It's, the goal is that you have a
sorted array of integers, say and you're
given a key. And you want to know, is that
key in the array? And if it is, what,
what's its index? And a fast algorithm for
doing this is known as binary search,
where we compare the key against the
middle entry. In this case, if we're
looking for 33, we compare it against 53.
If its smaller we know its in the left
half of the array, if it's larger we know
it's in the right half of the array, if
it's equal, we found it. And then we apply
the same algorithm recursively. So let's
quickly look at a demo. So we're looking
for 33 in this array, compare it against
the middle entry in the array. 53 and it's
less so we go left, so now we can
concentrate just on the left half of the
array, now we look in the middle of this
half, that's 25, 33 is bigger so we go
right. And now we concentrate on the right
half or the left half and we have a
smaller sub array. Look at the middle, 33
is less so we go left and now we have only
the one element to look at and we found
our key 33 in the array and we return that
index four. If we're looking for something
that's not in the array, we do the same
process. So, say, we're looking for 34.
It's going to be the same. Look in the
left half, look in the right half. Look to
the left of the 43. Now, there's only one
key to look at. A nd it's not 34, so we
say, it's not there. So that's binary
search. So here's the code for binary
search. Actually, Binary Search although
it's a simple algorithm, its notoriously
tricky to get every detail right. In fact
one paper claimed, that the first bug free
binary search wasn't published until 1962,
and even in 2006, a bug was found in
Java's implementation of binary search,
just an indication of the care that we
have to take in developing algorithms
especially for libraries that are going to
be used by millions of people. So here's
an implementation. It's not recursive
although often we can implement this
recursively. And it's just reflexing code,
what I described in words, we have to
find. A key, whether a key's in an array.
And we use two pointers, low and high, to,
indicate the part of the array we are
interested in, as long as low is less and
equal to high, we compute the middle. And
then we compare our key against the
middle, actually its a three way compare,
see its less or greater or if its equal,
we, we return that mid index. If its less
we reset the high pointer, if its greater,
we reset the low pointer, and we keep on
going until the pointers are equal. If
they are equal and we haven't found it
then we return -one. And it's easy to
persuade ourselves that this program works
as advertised by thinking about this
invariant, if the keys in the array, then
it's between low and high in the array.
Alright, so that's a program that, you are
probably familiar with. Lets look at the
mathematical analysis of that program. And
this a, a theorem that we are going to
prove easily. We want to a lot of proofs
but this is one worth doing. So its say
that binary search uses at most one + lg
base two event compares, to complete a
search, in a sorted array of size f. So we
do that, to setup the problem by defining,
a variable T(N), which is the number of
compares that binary search needed for its
array size and. And then we write down a
recurrence relation that is reflex the
code. And what the code does is, it
divides the problem size in half so that.
If the event is less or equal to the event
over two plus depending on how you count
what the compare is think of it as a two
way compare so divided in half by doing
one compare and that's true as long as N
is bigger than one. If it's equal to one
the solution is one. So it's a recurrent
relation describing the computation. And
so we, we can go ahead and, solve this
recurrence by applying the recurrence
itself, to the first term on the right.
Now that's called telescoping. So if this
is true and we can apply the same thing to
T(N/2). And throw out another one and if
that's, this is true, apply the same thing
to N over four, and throw out another one
and so forth until we get down to just
one. In which case we have lg N ones left.
Now this is a true sketch you might have
noticed that, that this proof actually
only holds if N is a power of two. Because
we nearly specify in this recurrence what
we mean if N is odd. But it's possible to
go ahead and sorry, possible to go ahead
and take care of that detail as well and
show that binary search running time is
logarithmic always. All right, so given
that fact we can develop a faster
algorithm for a threesome. It's a sorting
based algorithm. And so what we're going
to do is we're going to take the numbers
that we have as input and sort them. We'll
talk about sorting algorithms next week.
And we get that time in time proportional
to N lg N but that's not the main part of
the computation. The main part of the
computation is to after the numbers are
sorted, we'll go through and for each pair
of numbers ai and aj. We'll do a binary
search for -ai + ij. If we find it then
we'll have three numbers that sum to zero.
So if we [cough] sort our numbers and then
go through for each pair do a binary
search to see if it's there, so -40, zero.
Minus that is 40, we do a binary search
that's in there so we have one solution to
the 3-sum problem. And do that for all
pairs of numbers. Then a quick analysis
says the order of growth of running time
is going to be N^2 lg N. Then you need a
good sort, well, you could use the
elementary insertion sort the first one we
talk about but the running time of the
binary search for each of the pairs, each
of the N^2 pairs or N^2/2 pairs we're
going to do the binary search, so we get a
N^2 lg N running time. So, a quick example
of how we could improve the performance,
we could find an imroved algorithm to
solve a problem. N^2 lg N is much less
than N^3 for large N. And so, we're
implicitly making the hypothesis that if
we do this, do the sort base thing and use
binary search, we're going to have a
faster program. And, sure enough we can go
ahead and run some experiments and find
that whereas it took us 50 seconds to
solve the problem for 8,000 numbers
before. It's taking less than a second
now. In 50 seconds we can solve up to
64,000. So typically we expect that better
order of growth means. Faster in practice
and but when it comes to examining the
algorithms in detail we can, we can go
ahead and do the tests and figure out
which algorithm is faster. And certainly
going from N^3 to N^2 lg N we're going to
expect that we're going to have a much
better algorithm.