Welcome back. Today we're going to talk
about algorithms and data structures for
implementing some fundamental data types
called bags, queues and stacks. You maybe
somewhat familiar with these, but today
we're going to take a careful and close
look at them. The idea is that in many
applications, we have collections of
objects that we want to maintain. And the
operations are very simple. We want to add
something to the collection, maybe remove
something from the collection and iterate
through the objects in the collection
performing some operation on them, and of
course, test if it's empty. Now for most
of these, the intent is very clear. The
key is when it comes to removing an item,
which item do we remove? The two
fundamental classic data structures for
this, the stack and the queue differ in
the way in which the item to be removed is
chosen. For the stack, we take out the
item that was most recently added for, the
terminology that we used is push to insert
an item and pop to remove the item most
recently added. That's also called the
LIFO discipline last-in-first-out. For
queue, we examine the item least recently
added and those operations to distinguish
them we call inqueue to insert an item and
dequeue to remove an item and that's also
called the FIFO discipline, first in,
first out. So now we're going to take a
look today on how to implement these
things. Our subtext today is all about
modular programming. And that's going to
be a discipline that we're going to follow
up carefully throughout this course. The
idea is to completely separate the
interface and the implementation. So, when
we have these types of data structures and
data types that are precisely defined like
stacks and queues and so forth, what we
want to do is completely separate the
details of the implementation from the
client. The client has, can have many
different implementations from which to
choose but the client code should only
perform the basic operations. The
implementation on the other hand, can't
know the details of the client needs, all
it's supposed to do is implement those
operations. In that way, many clients can
reuse the same implementation. So this
allows us to create modular reusable
libraries of algorithms and data
structures that we can use to build more
complicated algorithms and data
structures. It also allows us to focus on
performance when appropriate. Again, this
is a modular programming style that's
enabled by object oriented programming
languages such as Java and we'll be very
disciplined in our use of this style.
Alright. So to begin, we'll talk about the
stacks. [cough] Stacks are familiar, many
of you probably implemented stacks in an
introductory programming course but we'll
do a thorough introduction to
implementations right now. As a warm up,
let's suppose that we have string, a
collection of strings. They might be
short, they might be long and what we want
to have is the ability to save away a
collection of strings and remove and
return the most recently added string
periodically, and also test if it's empty.
So that's our API. We have a constructor
to create an empty stack, we have for
insert and we have a method called push
that takes a string as argument. And for
remove, we have a method pop that returns
to the string most recently added. And we
have these empty test which returns a
Boolean. Also in some applications, we
would include the size as well. So again,
as always, we'll first read a client and
then look at implementations and our
client, simple client is to take some
strings on standard input and some pop
commands which are indicated with hyphens.
And so, it'll this client reads strings
from standard input. If the string is
equal to the hyphened character, it'll pop
the string at the top of the stack and
print it. Otherwise, if it's a string
that's not equal to the hyphen character,
it'll just push it on to the stack. So in
the example down below here if we have
this file called tobe.txt then what we'll,
what the client will do is push to be or
not to all in the stack then when it comes
to this hyphen it'll pop the most recently
inserted item which is two in this case
then it'll put b in the top of the stack
and then pop the top item on the stack
which is now b and then pop the item most
recently added, b is gone, two is gone so
the next is not and so forth. So, this is
a simple test client that we can use to
test our implementations. So now, let's
look at the code for implementing a stack.
Now, the first implementation that we'll
look at, uses link list. If you're not
familiar with the link list you'll need to
review that in section 1.3, 1.3 at the
book or in our Introduction To Programming
Java book. Even if you are familiar with
link list, it's worth taking a look at
this code because it's the style of coding
that we'll use throughout the coarse for
much more complicated data structures. So
the idea is to keep a link list where
which is consists of nodes that have
strings in them and references to the next
item in the link list and to, to implement
a stack when we do a, a push operation, we
insert a new node at the beginning of the
link list and we do a pop operation where
we move the first node from the beginning
of the link list, that's the most recently
added items. So, let's look at what that
code looks like. We use to implement link
list in all linked data structures through
out the course. We use what's called an
inner class in Java and that's just a way
to describe that we're going to be
manipulating node objects that consist,
each consist of a string and a reference
to another node. So, the pop operation for
link list is very easy to implement.
[cough] first, we, we're going to need to
return the first item on the list so we
save that away. Take first that item and
save that in the variable item. A h, then,
to get rid on the first node, we just
advance our pointer to the first item on
the list to point two of the next item and
then that first node is ready to be
reclaimed by the garbage collector. And
then, the last thing we need to do is just
return the item that we saved away. Okay,
so that's the pop operation. What about
the push operation? [cough] push
operation, we want to add a new node at
the beginning of the link list. So, first
thing we do is save a way the pointer to
the beginning of the list. That's a little
first thing first. Then we'll create a new
node, that's going to be the new node that
we put at the beginning of the list,
that's first equals new node. And then we
said it's instance variables. It's items
is the string that we want to put at the
beginning of the list, in this case, not.
And it's next is the old first item of the
list which is now the second item of the
list. So, after this operation, we are
first pointing to the beginning of the
list and we have the items on the list in
decreasing order of when they were put on
to the stack. So that also is a four liner
to implement the stack push operation. So
this is a complete link list
implementation of all the code to
implement a link list for a stack of
strings in Java. It's, it's a class the
constructor doesn't have to do anything,
there's no constructor. We have this inner
class that we use to build the items in
the link list and we make them an inner
class so we can directly refer to those
instance variables. And then the only
instance variable of a stack is a
reference to the first node on, on the
list and that starts out being null. Then
it's empty is just testing whether the
first node on the list is null and then
push is the four lines of code that I gave
on the previous slide and pop is the three
lines of code that I gave on the slide
before that. Tha t's a complete
implementation for the link list that'll
work with as a fine push down stack
implementation for any client. So now we
can analyze the performance of that so
that we can provide clients with
information and how well the algorithm
data structure will perform. In this case,
it's easy to see that every operation
takes constant time in the worst case.
There is only a few instructions for each
one of the operations, there's no loops.
So that's obviously a very desirable
characteristic. Then how about space
units, usage? Well, that depends very much
on the implementation in machines so this
a typical Java implementation that we'll
do the analysis for and contest this out
for different types of environments easily
in this representative. So, in Java, an
inter class there's for every object there
is sixteen bytes of over head. There are
some extra over head, eight bytes because
that's an inter class and then there is
two references that we built in our, in,
in our class node. One to string and
another one to a node and those are each
eight bytes. So, we have 40 bytes per
stack node, if we have a stack of size n,
we have about 40 n bytes. That's a little
extra first but that's about an overhead
for the whole stack but when n is large,
40n is a very close estimate to the amount
of space needed. This does not include the
space for the strings themselves which are
owned by the client. But with that, we can
properly asses the research usage of this
implementation for different client
programs. Now it's constant time but
there's faster implementations of stack
and since stack is used inner loop of some
algorithms it's important to think about
even faster implementations. And another,
natural way to implement a stack is to use
an array to store the items on a stack so
let's take a look at that. This
alternative of choosing between length
structures and arrays is fundamental and
it's go ing to come up again and again
when we consider more complicated data
structures in algorithms. So, we want to
be sure to analyze it in the simple case
for stacks to set the stage for more
complicated applications later on.
Alright, so the use in array we just keep
the n items on the stack in the array and
the array location within the n is the
place the top of the stack where the next
item is going to go. So, to push we just
add a new item at s(n) into pop we remove
the item that's at s(n) - one and
decrement n. Now there is a fundamental
defect in using an array and that is that
you have to declare the size of array
ahead of time and so the stack has a
certain capacity. And if there is more
items on the stack than the capacity we
have to deal with that problem and that's
a fundamental problem that we have to deal
with in array implementations in all sorts
of algorithms and data structures. So
again, considering it for the simple case
we'll pay off later on. Alright, so here's
the full implementation of stack for using
an array to represent the stack. So now we
have an instance variable which is an
array of strings and or variable n which
is both the size of the stack and the
index of the next position, next open
position on the stack. This one has a
constructor and the constructor creates
the array. Now, we are cheating in this
implementation to keep it simple and we'll
take care of this cheat in a little while
by requiring the client to provide the
capacity of a stack. In a few applications
this might be fine but in many, many
applications that's two owners are
requirement and client really can't know
how big the stack is. Client might have a
lot of stacks that need to be maintained
simultaneously and then maybe they reached
their maximum capacities at different
times and various other things. So, we
need to remove this cheat and will. But
the code is nearly trivial. If we have the
capacity to check if it's empty we check
if n is zero. To push an item we use n to
index into the array put the item there
and then increment n, that's the short cut
in many programming languages nowadays for
use the index and then increment it. And
to pop we decrement the index and then use
it to return the item in the array. So
each of the operations is a one liner and
this is a fine implementation for some
clients. That's array implementation of
stack but it breaks the API by requiring
the client to provide the capacity. So
what are we going to do about that? Well,
there are a couple of things that we
didn't consider. We didn't put in a code
to throw an exception if the client pops
from an empty stack. Probably should do
that and for overflow, what happens when
the client does too much well, we're going
to talk about an approach called resizing
that will allow us to avoid overflow for
clients. There's another issue about
whether clients can insert null items into
the data structure. In this case, we do
allow the client to insert null items but
we do have to worry about in Java about a
problem called loitering and that is the
idea that we have references to an object
in our array implementation and the stack
array and we are not really using it. So,
when we decrement that value in, there's
still a pointer to the thing that we took
off the stack in that array even though we
know we're not using it. The Java system
doesn't know that. So to avoid that and
really allow most efficient use of memory
it's best to set that. [cough] removed
item entry to null so there's no reference
to the old item left there and then the
garbage collector can reclaim the memory
since there's no outstanding references.
So that's a, a detailed but an important
one that we have to take care of and or
implementations to make sure that we're
getting most efficien t use of memory.