Next we're going to consider addressing
another fundamental defect in the
implementations we've considered so far
that those implementations are only good
for strings. What if we want to have
queues and stacks of other types of data?
And that brings us to the topic of
generics. Alright. So, we implemented
stack of strings but in applications we
have all different types of data that we
might want to implement like stack of int
say or URLs or cars or vans or whatever
data that we might be processing. So how
are we going to implement stacks and
queues for that types of data. Well, first
thing that we might that we might consider
and actually we're forced to consider this
one in lots of programming environment, is
to implement a separate stack class for
each type of data that we're using. That
really seems unsatisfactory. We have our
carefully crafted code that does array
resizing and so forth and we're going to
copy that code and change the data type
string to the data type van or int to
everywhere. And what if we have hundreds
of different types of data that we're
processing. We have hundreds of different
implementations. Unfortunately that
situation at the beginning of Java where
we stuck with that and there are plenty of
programming languages where basically
we're stuck with that so what we want to
look at is a modern approach to avoiding
having multiple implementations for each
type of data. So the a quick hack that is
widely used is to use casting to implement
to reuse the code for different data types.
So, we make our implementation with type
Object so everything in Java is a sub type
of Object and then the client, when the
client comes to use it, will simply cast
the result to the corresponding type. I
don't want to spend a lot of time with
this cuz I think this is a unsatisfactory
solution. So, in this example we have two
types with two stacks one of apples and
one of oranges. And then, it's up to the
client when it pops something off the
apple stacks to cast at the apple to keep
the type checking system happy. The
problem with this is that the client code
has to do this, this casting and it's kind
of an insidious bug if it doesn't quite
get it. So, the third attempt that we're
going to talk about uses generics. And
that way the client code doesn't do
casting. We can discover mistakes in typed
mismatches at compile-time instead of at
run-time. So, in this case, we put, with
generics, we can have a type parameter on
our class and that include, that's inside
angle brackets in this code and then, we
can [cough] if we have a stack of apples
and we tried to push an orange unto a
stack of apples then we're going to get a
compile-time error because that's stack
was declared to only consist of, of
apples. And just the guiding principal in
good modular programming is that we should
welcome compile-time errors and avoid
run-time errors because if we can detect
an error at compile-time, then we can ship
our product or deploy our implementation
our implementation of an API and have some
confident that it's going to work for any
client whereas, the error is not going to
get discovered until run-time it might
occur with some client development. Now,
years after, we have to deploy our
software and be extremely difficult on
everyone. Okay. So actually with a good
generic implementation it's not difficult
to simply [cough], take every place that
we used string and replace it with a
generic type name as in this code here. On
the left is our implementation of a stack
of strings using link list. On the right
is a generic implementation. So, every
place that we used string type on the
left we used the word item on the right.
And at the top, the class declaration we
declared an angle brackets that item is
the generic type that we're going to use.
The implementation could hardly be more
straightforward and it's an excellent way
to solve the problem of handling multiple
types of data with one implementation.
With arrays, it doesn't quite work and
again all programming languages and, you
know, many programming languages nowadays
have difficulties with this and Java's got
a particular difficulty. So, what we would
like to do is just declare a new array
using our generic name Item as in the
highlighted line here. Otherwise it's the
same. Unfortunately, Java does not allow
generic array creation. So there's various
technical reasons for that and you can
read, read extensive debates about this on
the web that's going to go beyond our
scope. For now, what we need to do is put
a cast in to make this work. So, we create
an array of objects and then we cast it
down to an array of items. Now in my view,
a good code has zero cast. So, we want to
avoid cast as much as possible because it,
it, it really is declaring some kind of
weakness in what we're doing. But in this
case we have to put in this one cast and
so what we've heard about that is the ugly
cast it doesn't, it doesn't make you feel
good about the code. It's not something
that you will come up with on your own and
that's, and that's an undesirable feature,
I think for codes so simple as this. But
fortunately, we can get through pretty
much everything that we're going to do in
this course just knowing about this one of
lay cast. So now, when we compile this
program we get a, a warning message from
Java. It says that we're using unchecked
or unsafe operations and we should
recompile with a minus -Xlint equals
unchecked for details. So, we can go ahead
and do that and it says that you have put
in, in your code an unchecked cast and
we're warning you about that cuz you
shouldn't be putting in unchecked cast.
And okay, that's fine and you're going to
see that when you do compiles using code
like these. I, I think maybe they might
have added to this warning statement "We apologize for making you do this". It's
not our fault that we had to do that, we
had to do that cuz of your requirement
about not allowing us to declare generic
arrays. So with that note please don't
think there's something wrong with your
code if you follow our prescriptive and,
and get this warning message. Okay then,
it's one of the detail that Java takes
care of and that's what about primitive
types [cough] so the generic type that
we're using is for objects and you know,
we're casting down from array of objects.
So in order to handle generic types we
have to use Java's wrapper object types.
So Integer with the capitalized rapid type
for int and so forth and many of you were
probably familiar with that. And there's a
process called auto-boxing which
automatically cast between primitive types
and wrappers so all of that handles of
the, the problem of dealing with primitive
types, kind of behind the scenes. And the
bottom line is that we can articulate an
API for generic stacks that works for any
type of data and we've got two
implementations, link list and arrays
that, that performed very well for [cough]
any type of data using the, the resizing
or link list as we've described.