Okay, our basic array implementation of
stacks had the defect where we required
clients to provide us the maximum capacity
of the stack ahead of time. Now, we're
going to look at technique for resolving
that problem. How do we, we do not
implementing the API. The API says we
should just be able to create a stack and
it should be able to grow and shrink to
any size. So, how do we going to go and
shrink the array? Well, first thing you
might think of is when the client pushes a
new item onto the stack increase the size
of the array by one and when pops,
decrease the array by one. That's easy to
code up but not worth it because it's much
too expensive to do that. The reason is
that you have to create a new array, size
one bigger and copy all the items to that
new array. So inserting the first N items
would take time proportional if the text,
stacks is size N - one, it's going to take
time N. And when it's two time N - one so
the first N items will take the sum of the
first N integers which we know is about
N^2 / two. Quadratic time to insert N
items into a stack that kind of
performance is unacceptable for large
problems as we've seen, as we will see
many times. So, the challenge is to do the
resizing. But somehow ensured that it
happens and frequently. So, the well end
technique for doing that called repeated
doubling is to when the array fills up,
create a new array of twice the size and
copy all the items over. Then we don't
create new arrays all that often so here's
the implementation of that. We start with
an array of size one. If we have a full
stack, which we know by testing N which is
the number of items in the stack versus
the rail length, then we just re-size the
array into one of twice the length before
inserting the item. And how do we re-size
to a new capacity? We create a new array
of that capacity and just go ahead and
copy our current stack into that, into the
first half of that and then retu rn it.
And that will reset our instance variable
which is our stack to this new bigger
array. So, the idea and the consequence of
this is if you insert N items into an
array, into a stack with this array
representation, the time will be
proportional to N not N^2. And the reason
is that you only create a new array every
time it doubles but by the time that it
doubles, you've inserted that many items
into the stack so on average, it's just
like adding one operation to cost of one
to each operation. So, if we just, if we
just calculate the cost and inserting the
first N items you're going to have,
instead of the sum of the integers from
one end, you're going to have the sum of
the powers of two from one to end and that
will give a total cost of about 3N. So,
that's an array axises. For the copy,
there's two array axis. So, to insert an
item, its about three array axises. This
plot is another way of looking at it which
is the number of array axis its taken as
you implement push operations. Every time
you hit a power of two, you take that many
array axises but in the sense you've
already paid for them by putting those
items on the stack. So that's called
amortize analysis, where we consider the
total cost averaged overall operations and
this is a, a fine example and useful
example of amortize analysis to get
efficiency in a stack implementation. Now
we, we have, what about the pop? We have
to think about how to shrink the array.
So, we might think, well, we doubled it
when it was full, when do we cut it in
half when it gets to be half full. We
don't want to get the array to get two
empty. Well, that one, one doesn't exactly
work because of a, a phenomenon called
trashing. If you, if the client happens to
do push, pop, push, pop alternating when
the array is full then, it's going to be
doubling, halving, doubling, halving and
creating new arrays on every operation to
take time proportional to N for every
operation and therefore, quadratic time
for everything so I don't want to do that.
The efficient solution is to wait until
the array gets one quarter full before you
have it. And that's very easy to
implement. We'll just test if the arrays
one quarter full, if it is, we re-size it
to half full. And so, then at that point,
it's half full and you can either grow by
adding stuff or shrink by subtracting
stuff but there won't be another resizing
array operation until, I guess totally
full or half again full. So the invariant
of that is the arrays always between 25
percent and a 100 percent full, number one
and number two that every time you
re-size, you've already paid for it in the
amortize sense by inserting pushing or
popping. So, here's just a what happens to
the array for our small client example and
you can see at the beginning, it doubles
from one to two to four but once it gets
to four, it stays once it gets to eight,
it stays to that size for a while even
though there's some of the operations it
doesn't shrink back to four until after
there's only two items in there and then
it shrinks and so forth. So, array
resizing doesn't happen that often but
it's a very effective a way of
implementing the stack API with an array
where the client does not have to provide
this maximum capacity of the stack but
still were guaranteed that the amount of
memory that we use is always only a
constant multiple of the number of items
actually on the stack. So the analysis now
says that the average running time per
operation for whatever the sequence of
operations is the average running time is
going to be proportional to a constant.
Now, there is a worst case that is at the
point when the stack doubles, it takes
time proportional to N so it's not quite
as good performance as we might like but
it's what we the advantage that we get is
ve ry fast pushes and pops just access
array and increment it and very efficient
for most operations. And for many, many
clients that's an effective trade off to
make. So what about memory usage? Well,
this is the analysis of memory usage for
stacks and it's actually less memory than
for strings the amount used is between 8n
and 32n depending on how full the array is
and just a quick analysis of the amount of
space that arrays take in Java. So, again
this analysis is just for the stack itself
not for the strings which the client
wants. So, what are the trade offs between
using a re-sizing array versus a link
list. There's a two different
implementations and the same API and the
client can use them interchangeably, which
one is better? In many situations, we're
going to have multiple implementation of
APIs and depending on properties of the
client program you're going to have to
choose which one is the better one to use.
So, for link list every operation takes
constant time in the worst case that's a
guarantee but we have to use a little
extra time and space to deal with the
links. So, it's going to be slower.
Resizing array implementation we have a
good amortized time so total average over
the whole process is good. We have less
wasted space and probably faster
implementation of each operation. And so,
for some clients, maybe that makes a
difference perhaps, you wouldn't want to
use a re-sizing array implementation at
the moment that your plane is coming in
for a landing and you wouldn't wanted to
all of the sudden, not implement some
operations quickly. If you need that kind
or maybe in an Internet switch where
packets are coming through at a great
rate, you wouldn't want to be in the
situation where you're missing some data
because something got slow all of the
sudden. So, that's a trade off that the
client can make if I want that guaranteed,
if I want to be sure that eve ry operation
is going to be fast use a link list and if
I don't need that guarantee, if I just
care about the total amount of time I'll
probably use the resizing array because
the total will be much less because
individual operations are fast. So, even
with these simple data structures, we have
really important trade offs that actually
make a difference in lots of practical
situations.