Okay. Those are some basic data structures
and implementations and it seem quite
elementary and simple but actually right
away we can get to some very sophisticated
applications of these basic concepts and
that's what we're going to consider next.
Now, first thing to mention is that often
the kinds of data types and data
structures that we implement or found in a
Java library. So, that's true in many
programming environments. So, for example
stacks and queues you can find those words
mentioned in the Java library so there's a
Java collection library and the so-called
List interface which is displayed here. So
Java has general API for sequences of
items and its got things like a, append at
the end, remove from the beginning, and
so forth. Any uses of the resizing array,
so many of the principles that we consider
does also a, a link list interface. So,
why not just use those? Why use our own
implementations? Well, the problem is
often in such library code is kind of
designed by committee phenomenon that more
and more operations get added and the API
becomes too broad or bloated. It's not a
good idea to have lots and lots of, you
know, operations in the same API. And
we'll see example in a second. The
problem, the real problem is that when you
do that you can't know much about the
performance or you can't assume much about
the performance. And so you can kind of
immediately arrive at that performance
even for simple clients. So our best
practice that we recommend is so few that
these basic data structures that we use
and there's so simple is to go ahead and
use the implementations that we've just
discussed for these fundamental data
structures. Maybe later, later on, after
an experienced programmer who knows what
he or she is doing could use some of these
library collections effectively. But
inexperienced programmers often have
trouble with it. Here's a war story from
students Programming assignments not that
long ago. So, we have an assignment where
you need to generate a random open sites
in a percolation system. We have one
student who was paying attention to what
we're saying and uses an array and can
pick the indices into that array at random
check whether they're open and, and
repeat. And so the array is N by N, it's
N^2 things and it takes about N^2 time,
which is actually a linear time for this
application. But then we have another
student who had some Java before coming to
us and considered himself an expert and
said, well, I'm going to use linked list
because I could use Java's library and I
don't have to worry about downloading your
stupid code. And so, I'll just use that
one and pick an index at random and delete
and that program took quadratic time and
poor Kenny, when trying to run his program
for the huge instance that we asked found
out that it wasn't finishing. And the
reason is that the Java linked list
implementation takes a linear time to find
an item with a given index. Not constant
time like an array. And that's difficult
for Kenny to think about and difficult to
drive that information from the
implementation so program is just too
slow. And with the Swiss knife
implementation with so many operations
it's hard to know whether or not the
particular set of operations that your
client needs is efficiently implemented. So
our insistence in this course is that
students should not use the library until
we've implemented it in class. At least
that some indication that you understand
the performance characteristics. So now,
let's look at some applications then of,
of stacks. There's the stacks are really
actually fundamental underlying
computation because they implement ,
recursion and so, you use stacks often
everyday when you wrote, use the Back
button in the Web browser, the places that
you've been are saved on a stack. Right
now we will look at two examples. One,
having to deal with compiling from a
programming language or interpreting into
an actual computation and then the other
one is the PostScript language which is
widely used for, for printing and
publishing. So, so the way the compilers
implement functions is using stacks. When
there's a function call the whole local
environment is pushed and then along with
the return address and then the function
returned is pop the return address in the
local environment. So there is the stack
there that contains all that information
and whether the function calls itself or
not is not relevant. The stack contains
the recursion. In fact, you can always use
an explicit stack to make a recursive
program non-recursive. So, this is so when
we have the GCD function, computing the
greatest common denominator, greatest
common denominator p and q is greatest
common denominator of q and p mod q and it
just calls itself until q gets to be zero.
And as this graphic integrates, it just
does it by saving the information on a
stack. Now a specific example that really
shows this off and also will illustrate
the utility of being able to process
multiple types of data with the same code
is this example is Dijkstra's two-stack
algorithm for arithmetic expression
evaluation. So the goal is, you got an
arithmetic expression this is just
actually like a simple stand in for a
program and we'll talk about that in a
second but let's say, arithmetic
expressions. We have operands and
operators and you want to evaluate it. And
Dijkstra's algorithm is very simple to
express. You processes through the
expression from left to right. If you see
a value, you put it, you maintain two
stacks and if you see a value, you put it
on the value stack and if you see an
operator, you put on the operator stack.
Left parenthesis you ignore. Right
parenthesis, you pop the operator and two
values and push the result. Now that's a
lot of words let's look at a demo. So we
start out with the empty value stack and
operator stack and we're going to move
from left to right. So, and those are the
a top is summarize the four type of things
that we could wind up with and what to do
so the left parenthesis we've ignored, a
value we put on to the value stack. So,
that one goes right in to the value stack.
Operator, we put on to the operator stack.
And plus it goes on the operator stack.
Left parenthesis you ignore. It seems strange
to be ignoring parenthesis and we'll get
back to that in a second. Value, put in
the value stack. Operator, put on the
operating stack. Doesn't seem like we're
doing much except putting stuff on stacks
and now, when we come to our right
parenthesis and that's when it gets
interesting. What it says is to you have
the top operator and the top two values
and that's what you want to do. Supply
that operator to those values and put the
resulting value that you get back on to the
operation stack. So, we take off the top
two things, we do the operation and then we
put the thing that we get onto the value
stack. And that's right parenthesis. So
now continuing along we put a star on.
Left parenthesis, we ignore. Four on, star.
The right goes to the value stack and now
we got a lot of stuff on the stacks and we
got through right parenthesis and that's
going to finish up the computation, take
the top two items off the stack and the
top operator off the operator stack,
perform the operation, put the result
back on the value stack. Another right
parenthesis, take the top two values off.
Perform the operation. Put the value on to
the value stack and finally, the last
right parenthesis, take the two operators
of the value stack, operators of the value
stack, and operator of the operator stack,
perform the operation, put the result back
on the value stack. And we're at the end
of the computation and that's the result.
The value that arithmetic expression is
101. Okay? Yup. Here's the code that
implements Dijkstra's two-stack algorithm.
We have two different stacks. The operand
stack the operator stack is string, it
could be characters which is just our
operator. Then our value stack is doubled
so that's the same stack code but with
generics, we're using, using two different
types of data. And then simply perform
Dijkstra's algorithm. If we have a left
parenthesis... Read a new string. If we have
a left parenthesis, do nothing. If we have
plus or times, push it. If we have a right
parenthesis, then go ahead and pop the
operator. And if it's plus, add the result
of the two values at the top of the value
stack and if it's a star, multiply the two
values on the top of the stack and, and
then push the result. So and then when
you're done then simply print out the
value on the stack and that's a fine and
elegant implementation using stacks for
any arithmetic expression. And it's easy
to extend that to handle other types of
things and so, why does this work? Well,
when the algorithm encounters an operator,
say, in the inside, we got the parenthesis,
operand, operator, operand, parenthesis
its easy to see that what its going to do
inside there is put the at the top of the
stack whatever it is, is to put the two
and three on the top of the value stack
and plus on the top of the operating stack
and when it hits that right parenthesis,
it's going to perform the operation and
it's going to proceed then exactly as if
the original input where that, where the
value replaced. So, just go in from the
inside out for every operation enclosed
within parenthesis like that it's just
repeat the argument that's exactly as if
the original expression were (one + five)
twenty and then again, replacing that one,
one + 100, 101. That's, that's why
Dijkstra's algorithm works. Actually
fairly easy to understand why it works.
And you can go ahead and extend this
algorithm to add functions like logs and
sines or other operators and have
precedence among operators, have them
associate and multiple operations, and so
forth. And actually that's on the road to
developing a compiler or a way to
translate a, a program from a programming
language to a computation, so
Dijkstra's algorithm that uses stack is
one way for entering and understanding of
the basis of computation.