Okay. There's another facility that Java
provides that leads to very elegant
compact client code that's definitely
worthwhile to add to our basic data types
and that's iteration, that's what we're
going to talk about now. So, what we want
to do is to allow the client to iterate
through the items in the collection. But
we don't have the client to know whether
we're using an array or link list or
whatever internal representation we might
have in mind. It's not relevant to the
client. And a lot of clients only want to
do is just iterate through the stuff in
the collection. But Java does provide a nice
a solution to this called iteration. So
what we're going to do is look at how to
make our stack, and queue, and other data
structures that we consider later on
implement the so-called Iterable interface
and it will work for client code no matter
which implementation we used so let's take
a look at the details of that. So what's
an Iterable? Well, in Java lingo what an
Iterable is, it's, it's a class that has a
method that returns an iterator. And so
what's an Iterator? Well an Iterator is
something, a class that has methods hasNext()
and next(). The Java also allows remove().
We think that one is bad news, we don't
use it can lead to insidious debug, bug
debugging problems. So, it's hasNext() and
next() and so to make the data structure
iterable, we're going to implement those
things. It seems like a lot of baggage to
carry around and the reason that we do it,
why do we go to the trouble doing it is
that we can, if we have a data structure
that's iterable we can use a very compact
and elegant client code in Java, the so
called for-each statement. So if we have a
stack we can say - (for String s : stack).
It means for each string in the
stack - print it out. And if we didn't have
that we would now, if we're using
iterators, we could go ahead and write
this longhand code but nobody would ever
do that cuz it's equivalent to the
shorthand or we might have to write client
code that does a lot of unnecessary pushes
and pops just to do this iteration. So
that's the key is to be able to have
client code that is so compact for
iterating through items in the data
structure so we're going to provide
iteration for all our basic data
structures and it's not too hard to do
definitely worthwhile the effort. So
here's what it looks like for link list.
So it's got to implement Iterable so what
does that mean implement Iterable? It's
got to have a, a method iterator() that
returns an iterator. So what's an
iterator? So, we're going to use an
inner class. In this case, we'll call it
ListIterator that implements Iterator and
it's generic. And basically what this
thing has to do is implement these methods
hasNext() and next(). And the semantics just
clear from the names. hasNext() is supposed to
if, if we're done is supposed to return
false. If we're not done we're supposed to
return true and the next() is supposed to
give the next item in the iteration. So if
the thing is a linked list we're going to
start out at first. We have that's the,
our first item in the list and we're going
to maintain an instance variable current
inside this iterator which is the current
thing that we're iterating. So, get the
next one just like if we want to remove
the first. We pull out the current item
and then advance the current reference and
return item. Moving current to the next
place. The client is always going to be
testing hasNext() as I showed as I showed
and that stub code before and so when it
gets to null it will return false in the
iterational stop. But for our iteration,
we just have to worry about implementing
next() and hasNext() and perhaps using a local
instance variable to get it done. We have
to probably to make bullet proof code -
throw exceptions if a client tries to
call next() with no items there and tries
to call remove() at all, we're not going
to support remove(). For, and for array,
it's even simpler. So now with the iterator we
have control over which order we go
through the items and so that's going to
go along with the semantics and the data
structure so probably in a stack you want
to get the things in stack order like the
order that come out of the stack so that's
reverse order in the array so in this case
then next() is just decrement and return the
next one and our instance variable is an
index in the array. And then hasNext() is
okay as long as that thing is positive. So
a little Java [cough] code to provide this
iteration facility but actually within
this framework not too much to do and you
can see how to implement this for your own
data type and we'll use this paradigm for
every basic data type that we, that
involves collections of objects that we'll
encounter. Alright, and in fact, it leads us
to actually for a lot of clients it
doesn't really matter what order we get
the items. Really often what we're doing
is just inserting items into a collection
and then, later on, iterating through the
items that we have. That data structure is
called a bag and so let's look at what
that API looks like. Order doesn't
matter so all we want to do is add an item
maybe you want to know the size and we
want to iterate through all the items in
the bag. So this is a simpler, narrower
API but still it expresses an important
little collection of operations and, and
we'll use this one and we've already seen
the implementations. You just take stack
and remove the pop, or queue and remove the
dequeue [cough] and you have fine
implementation of a useful data structure.