Okay, next, we'll briefly consider queue
implementations using the same basic
underlying data structures. So, here is
the corresponding API for queue of strings.
Actually you know it's the same API for
stacks just the names are different.
Instead of push we have enqueue instead of
pop, we have dequeue. And the semantics is
different. For enqueue we add an item say
at the end of the queue and for dequeue we
remove an item from the beginning. It's as
if you're waiting in line to buy a ticket.
When you're enqueue you're at the end and
when that's been in there the longest is
the one that comes off. So let's look at
how we implement those first using linked list
and then arrays. So, now our
representation of a queue with the linked
list, we need to maintain two pointers
references. One to the first item in the
list and the other to the last item in the
list. When we insert we're going to add
the item at the end of the list instead of
the beginning and when we remove we'll do
the same and we'll take it off the front.
So here's the implementation of dequeue.
It's identical to the code for pop for a
stack. We save away the item. We delete
the first note by advancing the reference
and then we return the item, so identical.
To add a node or enqueue, add a new node
to a linked list, we want to put it at the
end so that would be the last one return.
So we, to add it at the end so first thing
we need to is save a link to the last
node. We're going to need that because we
need to change its reference from null to
point to the new node. Then we'll create a
new note for the end of the list will
populate its fields and then that old link
will change that from null to a pointer to
the new node. So again just a few lines of
code. That's basic linked list processing.
Actually years ago when we taught courses
in algorithms and data structures much of
the course would be about this kind of
pointer manipulation but nowadays that's
restricted to just a few implementations
like stack and queue and a few other
fundamental data structures. So we don't
need so much anymore general programs for
manipulating linked list. We encapsulate
them in basic data types like these.
Alright, so let's go back to our full
implementation and this is just taking
care of collecting a curve from the
previous slides but also taking care of
special cases when the queue is empty to
make sure that if the queue is empty after
we remove an item, we're going to last at
null and make sure that both first and
last always are what we want them to be.
So those are details that are easy to
check. Okay, what about arrays? Well, we
want to do the details but it's not
difficult to implement queues with
resizing arrays as well and not difficult
but definitely a tricky programming
exercise that people are welcome to try.
So we'll maintain two pointers. The first
item in the queue and the tail which is
the position for the next item to appear
so for enqueue you add a new item at tail
and for dequeue you remove an item for
head. And the trick is that once you get
past the capacity, you have to reset back
to zero and so that's a little extra code
and then you have to add the resizing
capability as well to implement data
structure the same as for stack. And we'll
leave that as an exercise.