Next we're going to look at an easy
application of sorting to related problem
called Shuffling. So, suppose you have a
deck of cards. One of the things that you
might want to try to do is to simply
rearrange those cards into random order,
that's called shuffling. Here's a way to
get shuffling done using a sort and seems
like the opposite. The idea is, just
generate a random real number for every
array entry and then sort using those
random numbers as the keys. That's an
effective way to get things shuffled. And
it's possible to prove that, that produces
a uniformly random permutation of the
input if there's no duplicate values,
assuming that you have a real numbers that
are generated uniformly at random. And
that's just means that it's well shuffled
that every possible way of shuffling the
deck appears with the equal probability.
That's fine but it requires a sort and a
sort seems like a lot of work for this
problem and the question is, can we do
better? Can we have a faster way to
shuffle? Do we really need to pay the cost
of a full sort? The answer to that
question is, no. There's actually a very
easy way to rearrange an array so that
the result is a uniformly random
permutation. It only require a linear time
to get the job done. Let's look at the
demo. The idea this to pass through the
array from left to right with an index i
as we've been doing but now we start with
the array in order. And actually, it
doesn't matter how we start the array and
every time we pick an integer between
0 and i uniformly at random and, and
swap a[i] with that integer. So, let's
look at the beginning, we don't do
anything just swap it with itself. Now,
with i = 2 or i pointing to the second
card we generate a random integer in
between 0 and i, in this case it's the
one to the left and we swap those.
Increment i, generate a random integer,
this time it's going to be the first one
again, swap them. Increment i, generate a
random integer, swap them. Increment i,
generate a random integer, swap them. And
continue in that way. Swap. So for every
i, we do exactly one swap. Now, card could
be involved in more than one swap but
that's not an issue. The point is that the
cards to the left of i are shuffled there
uniform, randomly shuffled. On this case,
i and r are the same. There's no swap.
Increment i, generate a random r, swap them.
And at the end we have the deck shuffled.
That's a linear time shuffling algorithm
making use of randomness. It was proved
through actually a long time ago even
before computer implementations that if
you do that, you get a uniformly random
permutation and it only takes linear time.
So, that's definitely a way to get a deck
shuffled quite easily. Easy to implement.
Now it's key that the uniform random
number will be between 0 and i-1. You'll
often see programmers thinking that
they're implementing a shuffle and they
just choose for every entry, they just
choose random place in the array to
exchange it with and that doesn't really
work. You could do the items between i and
n-1, the ones that you haven't seen
yet and that would also work but doing a
whole array doesn't give you a uniformly
random result. So, with that one caveat,
this code is almost trivial. And it's a
method in our standard random class. Now
if you're going to be using random methods
that depend on randomness in real
applications, you do have to be careful.
So this is just an example about software
security. There's a lot of difficult and
deep issues to worry about and so for our
security and we're not going to worry
about all of them. But one thing that we
can do is make sure that our algorithms
work as advertised. So, here's an example
of an implementation for online poker.
Here's the code that you can find on the
web for how to shuffle a deck of cards and
that's pretty similar to our code but it's
actually got a few bugs, more than a few
bugs. So first one is the way that random
works it's actually never gets to 52 which
means that the last card just stays it can
end up in the last place. So, it's
definitely not shuffled because of that.
Maybe that one's minor but it also is
picking a random card from the whole deck
as we just pointed out that's not uniform.
Should be between 1 and i or between
i+1 and 52. Another problem is in
this implementation that the random uses
just a 32 bit seed that if you do that,
there's not enough possible shuffles. The
number of possible shuffles is, is, is
much more, if n, if n is 52, it's 52
factorial which is a lot bigger than two
to the 32nd. So, it's not close to a
random or uniform. And the other thing is
that, the seed is just a number of
milliseconds since midnight and that cuts
down the number of shuffles even more. And
in fact, it didn't take that much hacking
for someone to realize that after seeing
five cards and figuring out what the
server clock was doing, you could get all
the future cards in a real time in a program.
And that's a pretty tough thing to have
happen if you're implementing online
poker. You might want to make sure that if
you're advertising that you're doing a
random shuffle, that you go ahead and do
so. And the famous quote in this many
similar quotes, the generation of random
numbers is too important to be left to
chance. So, if your business does depend
on shuffling people have looked at all
sorts of options including using hardware
random number generators and these
various tests available to make sure that
it's random and you'd better use good
shuffling code that's our topic but the
bottom line is don't think that it's easy
to shuffle a deck of cards. So that's
shuffling - our first non-trivial sorting
application.