我们要看的第一个基本的排序方法很简单，
The first elementary sorting method that
we're going to take a look at is an easy
叫做选择排序。选择排序的思想是从
method known as selection sort. The idea
of selection sort, is start out with a
一个未排序的数组开始，我们将以这些扑克牌为例。在第i次循环中，
unsorted array and we'll use these playing
cards as an example. And in the ith iteration,
遍历数组在剩余元素中找到最小项，本例中，
we go through the array to try to find the
smallest remaining entry, in this case,
2是最小的元素。然后我们将其与第一个元素交换，
the 2 is the smallest from any entry. And
then we'll swap that with the first entry
这样就完成了一个步骤。选择排序基于
in the array and then we know we've got
one step done. Selection sort is based on
迭代思想。好，因此，基本的选择排序方法是，在第i次
iterating that idea. Okay. So, the basic
selection sort method is to, in the ith
迭代时从剩余元素中找到最小项，从第i个元素右侧或者
iteration, find the smallest remaining
entry and to the right of i or bigger
索引大于i的元素中，然后将最小项跟第i个元素交换。因此，从i在最左侧开始，
index than i and then swap that with i.
So, we start out i is at the left end and
接着是剩余的，所有右侧剩余的。扫描一遍，
then the remaining, all the remaining
entries to the right. We scan through and
最小项是2，从右数的第三项，进行交换。
the smallest one is the two, three entries
from the right so we swap that. So that's
这就是第一步。现在，第i个元素左侧已经排好序，
the first step. Now, that part of the
array to the left of i is in it's final
我们只需要继续。所以现在，最小的是三。和第i项交换，
order and we simply continue. So now, the
smallest is the three. Swap that with i,
i自增。现在2和3都排好序了，继续这样的步骤。找到
increment i. So now, we have the two and
three in order, continuing that way. Find
（右侧）最小项，4。将4与第i项交换，i自增。找到最小项，
the smallest, the four. Swap that one with
i, increment i. Find the smallest, it's
5，与第i项交换，i自增。找到最小项，与第i项交换，i自增。
five, swap that with i, increment i. Find
the smallest, swap that with i, increment
每次（迭代）都必须依次扫描剩余的元素
i.  Each time we have to scan
through all the remaining entries in order
来找到最小的一项。但是，一旦找到，只需要交换这两张牌，
to find the smallest. But then, once we
found it, we only have to swap two cards
这是选择排序的关键属性。现在8是最小的，
those are both key properties of selection
sort. Now the eight is the smallest and we
交换。现在我们知道它们是有序的，但程序不是这样，我们必须
swap. And now, we know they're in order
but the program doesn't so we have to look
确定i和n是相同的，然后与自己交换，
and decide that i and n are the same and
then it swaps it with itself and does the
直到最后一次迭代。经过这样的过程，我们才能确定整个
same thing for the last. And so, after
that process, then we know that the entire
数组已经排好序。好。理解某个算法如何工作的一种方法
array is in its final order, all sorted.
Alright. So let's, one way to understand
是考虑不变量。所以，对选择排序来说，
the way that an algorithm works is to
think about invariants . So, for the
我们有一个指针，也就是变量i，它从左侧扫描到
selection sort, we have a pointer that was
our variable i, that scans from left to
右侧。现在，用一个小红箭头表示i。
right. Now, it's indicated by a little red
arrow in this representation. The
不变量就是箭头左侧的元素，箭头左侧的元素保持不变
invariants are that the entries on onto
the left of the arrow are never changed
并且升序排列。箭头右侧的元素没有一个小于
and they're in ascending order. No entry
to the right of the arrow is smaller than
左侧的元素。i就是这样设定的。
any entry to the left of it. That's the
way that we set it up. And the algorithm
maintains those invariants by finding the
smallest entry to the right and exchange
it with the next one. So the code
implements the invariants. So, to move the
pointer to the right, we increment i. So,
now the invariant might be violated so we
have to fix it. It might be violated
because you might have an element to the
right of the pointer that is
smaller than some, the element on the
pointer. So, what we have to do is
identify the index or that minimum entry
and exchange it. Then once we've exchanged
it, again, we preserved our invariant.
After that point, no element to the left
of the pointer is going to change and all
the element, there's no smaller element to
the right. [cough] and that gives us
immediately our code for the selection
sort implementation. We identify the, the
length of the array that's n. Then we
have a for loop that goes through every
element in the array, we keep a variable
min in that is the index of the going to
be the index of the smallest element to
the right of pointer i. We have an
inter-for loop that for j, if it finds a
smaller one, resets min and then once
we've looked at all the elements to the
right of i we exchange the smallest one
with i. That's a complete implementation
of selection sort. Now it's easy to
develop on mathematical model for the cost
of selection sort and here's the
proposition that describes that.
Selections or uses about N^2 / 2
compares and exactly n exchanges. And
just looking at this trace of selection
sort and operation really is a proof,
visual proof of this proposition. In this
diagram, the entries in black, are the
ones that are examined in order to find
the minimum each time with the minimum in
red. Entries in gray are not touched,
they're in their final position. Well, you
can see that this isn't going to be in
general an N by N square and about half of the
elements in the square are black or about
N^2 / 2 and you can see also the exact
formula (N - 1) + (N - 2) and so forth
is the total number of compares used. And
then on each of the Ns values of the
variable i there's an exchange so that's
the cost in terms of the number of
exchanges. Now, what's interesting about
this proposition about selection sort is
that, it doesn't matter what order the
input is. Selection sort is going to use
quadratic time because it always has to go
through the whole thing to look for the
minimum. And another property is that you
can't sort moving less data because
selection sort does just a linear number
of exchanges. Every item is put in to
it's final position with just one
exchange. Let's look at an animation of
selection sort in operation. [cough] You
can see our pointer moving from right to
left every time it finds the smallest
element to the right, it exchanges it into
position. Now, if the array is partially
sorted, it doesn't matter to selection
sort. Still has to go through, even if
it's totally sorted, still has to go
through to the side where that minimum
element is. That selection sort, our first
elementary sorting method.