Now, we look at insertion sort which is
another elementary method and
interestingly has quite different
performance, characteristics than
selection sort. Let's look at a demo of
insertion sort. For insertion sort, what
we're going to do is we'll move an index i
from left to right as before. But now, in
the ith iteration we're going to move a(i)
into position among the elements to its
left. Let's look at how that works on our
example with cards. So now we start by
initializing i to first card and we take
the idea that everything from i to its
left is going to be sorted and everything
from the right, we're not going to look
at, at all. So, everything to the left of
i is in ascending order everything to the
right we haven't seen at all yet. So now,
when we increment i, well, in this case
it's already an order, we don't have
anything else to do. In the third case
now, when i at the third entry in the
array. Now, we start a index j and we move
that starting at i to the left and what we
need to do is just exchange the five with
every element to its left that's greater.
So, first we exchange it with the ten.
It's still not in place so we exchange it
with the seven. Now, we get to the
beginning array, of the array and once
we've done that or we've hit a smaller
element then we have everybody to the left
of i in order. [cough] So now we increment
i again and we come to the three. Again,
we exchange as long as the card
immediately to the left is greater. And
once we've done that, then we have
everything to the left of i in ascending
order. Now, in this case, we have the
eight and we only have to exchange one and
now, it's got the seven to its left and
everything is in order. So, we've achieved
putting it in order with less work in this
case. We don't always have to go all the
way back to the beginning. For exchange it
with everybody to its left that's greater,
until we find a smaller element done in
its ascending order. Two has to go all the
way back to the begin ning [cough]. But
then the very next one, the nine, has to
only go back one position. And the sixth
has to go about halfway back. [cough] And
then, we have the entire array sorted.
Again, we can look at insertion sort in
terms of invariants. Our pointers still
scans from left to right but now, the
elements of the left of the pointer,
including it, are in order. But the
elements to the right have not yet been
seen at all. So, we have to look at the
code that's going to maintain that
invariant as the pointer increments. Move
the pointer to the right, it's incremented
again. Now, the invariant is broken
because the elements the element on the
pointer is not in sorted order to put it
in sorted order, we have to move from
right to left exchanging it with every
larger elements to its left. And that's
with the code at the bottom does starts j
at i and decrements j exchanging j with
the elements to its left. A(j) with the
element to its left, a(j) - one as long as
a(j) is less than a(j) - one or j is
bigger than zero. And that immediately
gives the, this code for insertion sort
which is similar to our code for selection
sort and just as simple it gets two nested
for loops. Selection sort head to nested
four loops a test to comparison and an
exchange inside the four loop. And that's
a fine implementation of an elementary
sorting method. What about the analysis of
insertion sort? It's more complicated. Our
proposition says that insertions sort to
sort randomly ordered array with distinct
keys, it'll use about one-fourth N^2
compares and about the same number when
one-fourth N^2 exchanges on the average.
This is more complicated to prove. It
depends on the array being randomly
ordered. And again, you can get a feeling
for where the propositioning comes from by
looking at this N by N trace. Again, the
black elements are the ones that we
compare and actually, there are also the
exchanges. And the red one is the one
that's finally put in to place. And you
can see t hat for a large array that's
randomly ordered, the element that we put
into place is going to go about half way
back on the average. So, that means about
half the elements below the diagonal are
going to black on the average cuz N^2 /
two below the diagonal, half of that is
N^2 / four. The analysis, exact analysis
is not much more detailed than that. This
is a bigger trace that shows again, about
half the elements below the diagonal or
involved in the sort. [cough] Let's look
at in the animation. Since N^2 / four
versus N^2 / two, insertion sort is going
to be about twice as fast as selection
sort. So, we can do about twice as many
items in the trace in the same amount of
time. It grabs an element, brings it back
into position, every time. So, it's an
animation for randomly ordered items. Now
insertion sort does depend on the initial
order of the data. Let's look at the best
case and the worst case which are
certainly outliers. If the array happens
to be already sorted all insertion sort
does is really to validate that each
element that's got a smaller element to
its left so it does no exchanges and it
gets the sorting job done with just N -
one compares. On the other hand, if the
array is in descending order N is no
duplicates, then every element goes all
the way back. It makes N^2 / two compares
and N^2 / two exchanges. So in the first
case is much, much faster than selection
sort linear instead of quadratic. In the
second case, it's slower than an selection
sort cuz it uses about the same number of
compares but it uses many more exchanges.
So, let's see that in the animation. So,
this is when the items come in, in reverse
order. Now, every time [cough] it, it gets
a new item, that's to exchange it all the
way back to the beginning. Same kind of
dynamic characteristic is selection sort
except for every step, iIt's not just
comparing, it's also exchanging which
makes it even slower in practice. So, this
is the bad case that we wouldn't like to
see in th e practical application but
there's also a good case that actually we
take advantage of in plenty of practical
applications. And that has to do with when
the array is partially sorted. To talk
about this in a quantitative way, we
define what's called an inversion. An
inversion is just a pair of keys that are
out of order in the array. So this array
has six inversions, T and R are out of
order cuz R should go before T. T and P
are out of order and so forth. This array
has six inversions. And we define array to
be partially sorted if its number of
inversions is linear, if it's less than
some constant times N. And partially,
sorted arrays appear often in practice.
For example, if you have a large array
with just a few that's sorted except for
just a few unsorted elements appended at
the end it's going to be [cough] partially
sorted. Or another case is if you only
have a few entries out of place, the array
is going to be partially sorted. These
types of things rise often in practical
applications and what's interesting about
insertion sort is that it runs in linear
time for partially sorted arrays. And the
proof is the number of comparisons and the
number of exchanges is equal to the number
of, number of exchanges is equal to the
number of inversions and then there's an
extra compare for every element except the
first. So, let's look at how that looks in
the animation. Here's a partially sorted
array and you can see that insertion sorts
quickly gets the job done. We're going to
take advantage of this in a little bit
later in this lecture. That's insertion
sort, our second elementary sorting