>> Now we'll look at an application of
sorting from the field of computational
geometry for an interesting computation.
If you have a set of N points in a
plane. There's a geometric object called
the Convex Hull which is the smallest
polygon that encloses all the points.
There's the Convex Hull for that set of
points. [cough] There's a lot of
equivalent definitions of this. Some of
them very mathematical, that extend the
higher dimensions. It's the smallest
convex set that contain all the points,
the smallest area of convex polygon
enclosing the points. It's a convex
polygon that encloses the points whose
vertices points in the set and those are
all equivalent definitions. And what we
want to do is given the set of points,
we're going to have a program that can
give us the convex hull. Now, which should
the output of such a program, such a
method be? Well, in order to be able to
work with the result, it should be a
sequence of vertices that gives us that
polygon if we follow it. If we've got some
points that are on the boundary but aren't
really vertices they shouldn't be
included. This points out examples of how
difficult computational geometry can
sometimes be because degenerate cases
like these are difficult to deal with in
code. We're not going to spend a lot of
time on this, in this lecture. But it's
something always to be aware of when
trying to [cough] apply simple algorithms
in situations like these that turn out to
be maybe more sophisticated than we might
think.
>> [inaudible] the large screen.
>> Oh yeah, got you. Mm-hm. Well, there's
actually a way to compute the convex hull
just mechanically if you put the nails
around the points and put a rubber band
around it, that gives you the convex hull.
Now, we're not going to be able to really
implement that in a computer program but
it's surprising how well we can do. Here's
an application where people want to
compute the convex hull. Suppose you have
a robot that wants to get from s to t and
there's an obstacle that's defined by some
polygon. You wanted be able to go around
the obstacle and it turns out that the
shortest path, either it's a straight line
from s to t or it's part of the convex
hull and is not hard to see why that might
be true. And there's plenty of other
applications where people want to be able
to compute the convex hull. Here's another
application. If you want to find the pair
of points that are the farthest apart in
the set of points in the plane, this is
sometimes important in statistical
calculation or other applications. They're
on the convex hull. If you have the convex
hull, this computation is easy. [cough]
They're, they're going to be extreme
points on the convex hull. So, there's a
lot of geometric properties of the convex
hull that we can take advantage of to
develop an algorithm. In here two
properties. Now, these are the things that
have to be proven and we're not going to
get into the details of geometric proof
but they're intuitive and certainly have
no trouble accepting that these things are
true. One thing is, that you can traverse
the convex hull by making only counter
clockwise turns or left turns if you're
looking at the screen here. And the other
thing is that, so if we travel from p to
point 1 then we make a left turn to go
to point 5 or counterclockwise turn and
then from there, we go to point 9 and
12 and then we eventually get back to
the start point. The other thing is, if
you take the point with the lowest y
coordinate. And then if you look at the
polar angle with respect for every other
point with the respect to that one, so the
angle you get from of the x-axis through p up to
the point, then the vertices appear in
increasing order of that angle. And again,
that's not, not difficult to see that
that's a fact. And the algorithm that
we're going to look at, called the Graham
scan is based on those two facts. It's,
the idea is to start with point p, the
one with the smallest y coordinate. Sort
the points by polar angle with p where
that is we're just going to consider in
that order. And then we'll just throw away
the ones that do not create a
counterclockwise turn and you'll see how
that works when we look at the demo. So we
start at point p. Sort the points by polar
angle with p so that is if we take a, a
vertical line and sweep it in a
counterclockwise direction, what order
that we hit the points? The first thing we
hit is 0, 1, and then we sweep
counterclockwise, we get the 2 and then
3 and 4 and so forth. So, that's
the ordering of those points. And so now
we'll just consider those points in order
and then take them for the convex hull. At
the beginning, 0->1 is a line that's
on the convex hull. So, the point with the
lowest y coordinates on the convex hull
and shows the one that is the smallest
polar angle that creates with the x-axis.
So now what about this one - 2? Is that on
the convex hull? Well, as far as we know
at this point, it could be, it could be
that the thing is a triangle and 0 is
the last point in which case it would be.
But in same with 3. As far as we know,
that one could be on the convex hull. But
as soon as we go out to 4 that's not a
counterclockwise turn. It's going the
wrong way and essentially what this means
is a point 4 is evidence that point,
there is no way the point 3 can be on
the convex hull. You can [cough] convince
yourself with that quite easily. So we
just throw a point 3 out. It's not on
the convex hull so, and what about the
angle from 1 to 2 to 4? That's not
counterclockwise either. It's turning the
wrong way and it's turning to the right. So
point 2 can't be on the convex hull
either. And indeed if you just draw the
line from 1 to 4, you can see the 2
inside so there is no way it could be in
the convex hull. Now that's essentially
the proof that you have to have a
counterclockwise turn. So now, we go on to
5 - turning the wrong way. So, point 4
can't be on the convex hull. So now we go
to 6. As far as we know, it could be, but
as soon as we hit 7, we know that it
can't be cuz that's a right turn. So 6 is
not there. Go to 8, nope. 7 can't
be on the convex hull. Go to 9. 8 can't
be on the convex hull. Now we go to
10 and 11. As far as we know they
could be. If 12 weren't there, they
would be. As soon as we hit 12 we see
that 11 can't be on the convex hull
and 10 can't be on the convex hull and
that completes the computation of the
convex hull with the Graham Scan. Okay.
So, there are number of implementation
challenges for the Graham Scan and we're
not going to go into detail on this
because this is a lecture on sorting
algorithms not computational geometry but
it is indicative of how, even if we have a
good sort, we might have to do some extra
work to actually solve our problem in an
application. So, how do we find the point
with the smallest y coordinate? Well you
could, you could sort, you could define an
order and compare the points by y
coordinate so essentially sorting is the
[cough] answer to that question. And we'll
look at the next lecture of what it means
the divine ordering among objects, little
more general than what we do for sorting.
How to sort the points by polar angle?
Well again we need to define what we mean
when we're comparing points. And then the
next lecture again we'll look at ways to
define different orderings among points
and Graham scan is a perfect example. We
don't want to just be able to sort things,
we don't want to just be able to sort them
by defining and compared to. We're going
to be able to sort the same things in
different way sometimes and this example
is a fine motivation of that. Figuring out
whether what we have is a counter
clockwise turn that's a little exercise in
geometry and we'll just talk about that
briefly in the next couple of slides. And
then wow, what are we getting the sort
efficient, done efficiently? Well, we
could use Shellsort but actually in the
next couple of lectures and we'll look at
classical sorts - Mergesort and Quicksort -
that we could use. The idea though is that
this example illustrates that good sorting
algorithm gives us a good convex hull
algorithm. That's an extremely important
principle in designing good algorithms.
Once we have a good algorithm, if we have
another problem we can say to ourselves,
well, we've got a good solution to this
algorithm, can we use that solution to
solve our new problem? Convex hull, when
we have a good sorting algorithm, it gives
us a good convex hull algorithm. Because
the main, the most work in convex hull is
the sort. And then again there's all, all
kinds of difficulties in implementing
convex hull in real world situations
because of various degeneracies. And these
things are covered on the book site. So
the main part of computation that we
haven't really talked about and we'll
cover briefly is if we have three points,
a, b and c, and you go from a to b to c,
are you making a counterclockwise turn or
not? So, in the example at the left, a to
b to c is counterclockwise. Example at the
right, a to b to c is not counter
clockwise. Going from a to b you turn left
to get to c in the first case and you go
right to get to c in the second case and
we want to do a computation that
distinguishes this. Now, this computation
will be pretty easy except for the
degeneracies. What do you want to count if
they're all on the same line. Or if the
slope is infinity. So, you have to just be
aware that these situations have to be
dealt with. So, the code isn't quite as
simple as you might come up within the
first instance that you try. So, there's
degeneracies to deal with and floating
point precision but people, researchers in
computational geometry have worked this
out and actually there's not that much
code at all in the end involved. The and
this is the slide that, that gives the
math and I won't talk through this math.
If you're interested in implementing this,
you can come back to the slide. And it's
essentially based on the idea of computing
the slopes of the lines between a and b,
between a and c and comparing them to
decide whether you're turning counter
clockwise or clockwise. And this is the
specific math that gets that implemented.
So [cough] this is if we implement a point
data type for computational geometry, you
can have a method ccw() that just with this
little math calculation (b.x - a.x)(c.y - a.y)
minus (b.y - a.y)(c.x - a.x) and we
see that calculation here gives you
immediately whether it's counter
clockwise, clockwise or co-linear. Not
much code at all. And that method is the
basis for the Graham Scan. The Graham Scan
uses a sort where we give two different
ways to sort the points. And that uses a
push down stack for the hull, it puts the
points on the hull in it goes ahead and
for every point considering I'm in the
order of the polar sort it'll compare
whether the top two points on the hull and
the new point implement a CCW turn or not.
And if it's not a CCW turn, it pops and
then continues going. Very little code to
implement the convex hull given that you
have a sort and that's our main point for
this lecture - there is many natural
applications of sorting but also will be
able to develop new algorithms that use
sort that gain efficiency because of the
efficiency of sorting.