Now, we'll look at Shellsort which is a
bit elementary on the face of it but it's
not at all elementary as you'll see. The
idea of Shellsort is that Insertion Sort
is inefficient because elements really
move only one position at the time even
when we're kind of know that they have a
long way to go. The idea behind Shellsort
is that we'll move entries several
positions at a time and the way we're
going to do it, it's called h-sorting the
array. So, an h-sorted array is h
different inter leaves sorted
sub-sequences so in this case with h=4
if we start at L and look at every
fourth element - M, P, T - then it's sorted. If
we start in the second place at E and look
at every fourth element, it's sorted. So
this is 4 interleave sequences, that's
a 4-sorted array. And what we're going
to do is implement a sorting method that
h-sort for decreasing sequences of values
of h. This is one of the oldest sorting
methods invented by Shell in 1959. So, in
this case, it starts out with the input
example shown and then the 13-sort -
a few items are moved, 4-sort - a few
more are moved, and then finally, a 1-sort.
And the idea is that each of the
sorts can be implemented with only a few
exchanges given that the previous ones
happened. So first thing is how do we get an
array h-sorted? That's actually pretty
easy. We just use Insertion Sort but
instead of going one back every time we
come with a new item, we go h back. So for
example when we come to this A in the
Insertion Sort, then it's, we look at the
array before that and then there was M and
E in the positions three back so we
exchange the A with the larger one to its
left, that's M and then the other larger
one to its left, that's E and then put it
into position. So the code is the same as
insertion, as for Insertion Sort, except
that when we go backwards through the
array we skip by h instead of just by one.
That's how we h-sort an array. And the
idea is we're going to use Insertion Sort
because of two reasons based on our
understanding of how Insertion Sort works.
While the first thing is if the increments
are big then the size of the sub arrays
that we're sorting are pretty small so any
sorting method including Insertion Sort is
going to work well. But the other thing is
if the increments are small because we've
done previous h-sorts for bigger
values of h, the array is partially sorted
and so Insertions Sort is going to be
fast. You wouldn't work to use Shellsort
as the basis for h-sorting because that
always takes quadratic time no matter what
order there is in the array. So let's look
at example of Shellsort with increment
7, 3, and 1. So, we start with
this sort example and then 7-sorting
it - just involves doing insertion
sort but just reaching back
7 each time. In this case, the 4
subfiles stretched out at seven each only
have two elements in them. And then we
3-sort. Now, because it's 7-sorted
and a 3-sort elements are either
already in placed or on a go back a few
strides. On this case, it's only the A
that goes back two. And then we 1-sort
and again because of the fact that it's
been 7-sorted and 3-sorted, the
arrays are almost in order when it comes
time to do the 1-sort and most of the
items only go back one or two positions.
So we have to do a few extra passes to do
the higher sorts but the each element
moves only a little bit on each path and
that's how Shellsort gains its efficiency.
So actually once you 1-sort, that's
Insertion Sort so you're going to always
get a sorted result. The only difference
is how efficient is that. Now the
intuition behind Shellsort and actually
the mathematical fact is that if you've
got an array that's h-sorted and then you
k-sort it for another value k different
from h, it's still h-sorted. This is one
of those mathematical facts that seems
obvious but then if you try to prove that
maybe it's a little more subtle than you
think. So, if you think of all this is,
is, is trivial and easy, go ahead and try
to write down a proof that a g-sorted
array remains g-sorted even after it's
h-sorted. But most people will accept that
and it's a fact and that's how Shellsort
gains efficiency. Now there's another
problem is what increment sequence should
we use for Shellsort. One of the first
things you might think of is let's try
powers of two. Actually that one doesn't
work at all, very well at all because it
winds up not comparing elements in even
positions with elements in the odd
positions until the 1-sort which means
performance can be bad. Shell's original
idea is to try powers to two minus one and
that works okay. Knuth when he wrote his
books in the 60s proposed the increment
sequence 3x + 1. We'll start with the
1, 4, 13, 40, 121, 364 like that
and that's good because it's
easy to compute. When we're using in
Shellsort of course, we find the largest
increment less than our file size and then
do the sorts for decreasing values of that
increment. But finding the best increment
sequence is a research problem that has
confounded people for quite a long time.
Here's an increment sequence that I found
after maybe a year's work and it works
well but nobody knows if that's the best
one. So here's the implementation in Java
of Shellsort for Knuth's 3x + 1
increment sequence. We'll just go
ahead and compute the increments that are
less than n, n / 3 and then starting
at that increment whatever it is and say,
we started 364 then next time we need an
increment, we'll just divide it by 3,
364 integer divide by 3, 364 integer /
3 it gets 121, 40 and so forth. So,
this h = h / 3 gets us to the next
increment. And then, the implementation is
just Insertion Sort. We just go through
starting at h for i and when we do the
insertion, the j loop, we decrement j by h
each time, otherwise the code is exactly
like Insertion Sort. So, just adding this
extra loop for h-sorting and this extra
loop to compute the increments to
Insertion Sort, we get a slightly more
complicated piece of code but its much,
much more efficient. Here's what it looks
like for a bigger array. We start with the
randomly ordered input and you can see
that it gets more and more in order on
each time that we h-sort for the
decreasing values of h. Here's an
animation. This animation does the whole
h-sort for each subarray. It's a
little better feeling for what's going on.
And now to do the high ones pretty quickly
and now it's doing the 1-sort and again
it steps through the array pretty quickly.
If it's partially sorted it doesn't make
much difference - does the higher sorts a
little bit faster. But that's simple to
implement and very efficient sorting
algorithm. Now, the analysis of Shellsort
is still open. Now, there's a few things
that we can say. For example we can say
that the number of comparison and the
worst case is O(N3/2) for the 3x + 1
increments. But actually in practice it's
much less than that. The problem is nobody
knows an accurate model for describing
the number of compares taken by Shellsort
for any interesting increment sequence.
This seems to be with a small value,
multiple of n times the number of increments
used which is some multiple maybe of n log n
but nobody is been able to find an
accurate model that proves that for any
interesting increment sequence for
Shellsort. So, why we are interested in
this algorithm? Well, it's a simple idea
that leads to substantial performance
gains. It's very useful in practice
because it's pretty fast except for very
huge arrays. It's going to beat even the
classical sophisticated methods for medium
sized arrays. And it doesn't take much
code. It's often used in embedded systems
or in hardware sort type systems because
there's so little code involved to
implement it. And it just leads to a lot
of interesting questions. This gets to the
intellectual challenge of developing
algorithms. If you think what we've been
studying so far is trivial, go ahead and
find a better increment sequence. Try some
technique to discover one and try to say
something about the average-case
performance of Shellsort. People have been
trying to do that for 50 years without a
whole lot of success. So, the lesson is
that we can develop good algorithms or
good implementations without much code but
there are some out there that are still
waiting discovery. It could be that there are
some increment sequence out there that
make Shellsort more efficient than any
other method, any of the sorting method
that we know for pratical file size, no
one can deny that. That's Shellsort or
first non-trivial sorting method.