Finally, we talk about stability. This is
really one of the rules of the game but
it's much easier to talk about in the
context of the real algorithms that we've
seen so far. And really it doesn't make
sense if you don't know about comparators
which we just introduced. So, the typical
application that I just used as an example
is say the set of student records. So we
have them sorted by name and this is say,
something that we do just before assigning
final grades. Maybe the third line there
is the final grade. So it's all fine
sorted by name and but then in order to
distribute it out to the people leading it
to the sections, what we want to do is
sort by the second fields, sort by
section. The problem is that when we do
that, it messes up the sort by name and
that's annoying. You might assume that
once you have it sorted by name, then when
you sorted by the second field then it
should maintain the sort of by name for
all that have equal keys in that second
field. Actually not all sorts preserve
that property that is called stability.
And clearly, it's worthwhile to think
about for your application whether you
want or need a stable sort. And so, it's
an annoying surprise for many people and
many applications. So a stable sort is a
sort that preserves the relative order of
items with equal keys. Whichever sort are
stable? That's an interesting question
that we'll take a look at now. The quick
bottom line is that insertion sort and
mergesort are stable but not selection
sort or Shellsort. And even within that
bottom line, there's implementations that
maybe are not stable. You have to
carefully check the code to be sure.
Always, in this class, we have an exercise
or exam question is this version of this
sort stable or not? So, students learn to
recognize whether the code is stable. So
this is just another typical example where
we've got things sorted by time, and then
what we want to do is maybe these are
important events. People buying tickets to
a rock concert and I'm going to sort by
location what we'd hope is that it would
keep the sort by time but this is a
non-stable sort that doesn't do bad so
then out in the location they're going to
have to resort it if they use one of
these. But if they use a stable sort, then
it stay sorted by time and lots of
applications you want stability. Alright,
so let's just look at each of the
algorithms that we've considered so far.
Insertion Sort. Insertion Sort is stable.
Why is it stable? Well, we never move
equal items pass one another. In this
example here, when we get A1, well that's
so in this case, the index is just one
that appears in the array, it's just A's
and B's. When we get our second A, we stop
the sort as long as we're not less. We're
equal, we're not less, we stop it so we
never move an equal item pass another one.
If this less or less than or equal, then
it wouldn't work. Or if we did the other
way around and proceeded accordingly. So,
equal items never move past each other in
this code so therefore insertion sort is
stable. But selection sort is not stable.
Usually way, the way to show that a sort
is not stable and it's just to see if it
has a long distance exchange that might
move an item pass some equal item. So,
[cough] in this case, for example, for
selection sort, when we do that first
exchange oops, [cough] where we found the
minimum A and B is in position zero. We
did a long distance exchange and that
catapulted that first item past any item
that it might be equal putting them out of
order. And that's may not get fixed so
that sort is not stable. It might move
items past some equal item and leave a
result where items that are equal or in
different order than they were originally
in the file. Selection Sort is not stable.
Shellsort also has long distance exchange
and so it's not stable. It moves keys past
other keys that could be equal and so its
easy to construct examples showing that
Selection Sort is not stable. And what
about Mergesort? Mergesort is stable well,
it's stable as long as the merge operation
is stable and that operation is going to
be stable depending on how we code it.
And, and in our code, if the two keys are
equal, it takes from the left subarray so
that means that, it will always take the,
if there's a two sets of equal keys, it
will preserve the relative order and
that's enough to show that the merge
operation is stable and then therefore
Mergesort is stable. Stability is an
important property in sorting algorithms.
Mergesort is not only efficient, it's also