Welcome back.
Today we're going to look at Mergesort,
which is one of two
classic sorting algorithms that are
critical
components in the world's computational
infrastructure.
We have a full scientific understanding of
the
properties of these algorithms, and
they've been developed
as practical system sorts and application
sorts that
have been heavily used over the past 50
years.
In fact Quicksort, which we'll consider
next time, was honored as one of the top
10 algorithms of the 20th century in
science and engineering.
On this lecture we're going to look in
Mergesort, which is
the basic sort in plenty of different
programming systems including Java.
Next time we'll look at Quicksort which
is also used in Java for different
applications.
Alright, so basic Mergesort algorithm.
What's it going to look like?
The idea is very simple.
What we're going to do is divide an array
into two halves.
Recursively, recursively sort each of the
halves.
And then merge the result.
That's the over-view of Mergesort.
It was actually one of the first
non trivial algorithms I implemented on a
computer.
John Von Norman realized that the
development of
the EDVAC, his EDVAC computer, one of the
first
general purpose computers that is going to
need
a sorting method and he came up with
Mergesort.
He's widely accredited as being the
inventor of Mergesort.
So the idea of Mergesort is, is based on
the idea of merging.
And so to understand how merging works
we'll
think about the idea of an abstract in
place merge.
So, we've got an array A and its first
half is sorted and its second half is
sorted and the computation we need to
perform is to replace that with the sorted
array where those two sub-halves are
merged together.
Let's look at a demo.
[COUGH]
The method that we're going to use is
based
on taking an auxiliary array to hold the
data.
This is a, one of the easiest ways to
implement the merge.
So the first thing we do is copy
everything over to the auxiliary array.
Now, once that's done, what we'll want to
do is copy
back to the original array to get it in
sorted order.
In order to do that, we're going to
maintain three indices.
I, the current entry in the left half, j,
the current entry on the right half and
k, the current entry in the sorted result.
[COUGH] so the first thing we
do is, take the smaller of the two entries
pointed to by i and j, and compare
those, and take the smallest one, and move
that one to be the next item output.
And whichever one is taken, we increment
its pointer.
Now we compare the minimum again, again,
the one pointed group
by j is smaller, so we move that one to k.
Increment that pointer j and also
increment k.
Now there's two E's, equal we always take
the first.
So the one on the left array goes to k's
position.
And now we increment i and k.
And again, it's an E and they're equal.
We'll take the first one so we move that
one up increment i and k.
And now
j's E is smaller than g.
It's the next thing that has to go in the
output.
So we move that one up and increment j and
k.
Now the one pointed to my i, the G
is smallest so move that and increment i
and k.
Move the M up and increment i and k.
Now the last element in the left sub array
is the one that's going to get moved next.
And now
that first subarray is exhausted so really
all we need to do is take
the rest of the elements from the right
part and move them back in.
Actually since we copied, we could
optimize by avoiding these moves.
That's an abstract in-place merge for
taking the two sorted sub-halves
of an array using an auxiliary array, move
them out, and
then put them back in in sorted order.
Alright, so here's the
code for merging, which is quite
straightforward from the demo.
We first in order to sort an array of
comparables in this implementation we pass
a link to
the auxiliary array, in as well.
And we have three arguments
lo, mid, and hi.
So lo is the first part of the array to be
sorted.
Mid's the midpoint that divides the first
part from the second, so our conditions
are
that from lo to mid is sorted, and from
mid plus 1 to hi is sorted.
[COUGH] so the merge implementation then,
the first thing
it does is copy everything over to the
auxiliary array.
And then that sets up for
this four loop that accomplishes the
merge.
We start our I pointer at the left heart
on the left half.
The J pointer on the left part of the
right half.
That's mid plus one.
And we start the k Pointer at the
beginning lo.
And for every value of k what we're most
often doing is comparing whether aux of j
is less than aux
of i.
And if it is, we move the element of j
over in increment j.
If it's greater we move the element i over
in increment i.
And then in both cases, we increment a,
not imple, increment k, and that
implements the merge.
If the i pointer is exhausted, then we
just move over the j, next jth element.
If the j pointer is exhausted
we move over the next ith element.
So every time we're moving
a new element into k and that's the code
that impelements the
abstract in place merge.
Now with this code,
we're also introducing the idea of making
assertions just to make it
easier to debug our code and to have
confidence that it's correct.
In this case, this insertion just says we
want to
be sure that a of lo to mid assorted and
that mid plus
one to high is sorted before our code and
then we
want to check that, the whole thing is
sorted after our code.
And generally programmers, Java
programmers know that it's a good idea to
try to do these assertions.
Not only does it help detect bugs, but it
also documents what the code is supposed
to do.
And that merge code is a good example of
this.
If you put at the beginning of the code
what you expect
in the, in the form of an assertion, which
is code itself.
And you put at the end of the code what
you
think it's going to do, again in the form
of an assertion.
You're both testing that these conditions
hold, and also telling someone reading the
code, what you're trying to do with it.
So Java is just an assert statement.
It takes it, boolean condition.
In this case, we're using that method is
sorted that we were before.
That returns true if the ported is sorted
and false if it's not.
And what assert will do is it will throw
an exception
unless that condition is true.
Now the thing about assertions in Java is
that you can enable or disable them at
runtime.
And that's really important, because it
means you can
put them into your code to check while
developing.
But it doesn't incur any extra cost at all
in production code.
So by default, insertions are disabled.
Something goes wrong
somebody analyzing the situation can
enable insertions and they
often will help find out where, what the
problem is.
So, the best practice is to use insertions
just as we did in that
example with merge and to assume that
they're not going to be there in
production codes.
You shouldn't use them for the things like
checking
if the input is the way you like it.
Alright, so with that merge
implementation, then
the sort implementation is a quite simple,
recursive procedure shown here.
So we use the merge procedure we just
showed, and then our sort procedure.
It's recursive so, checks that we have
something to do first.
Then it computes the value of the midpoint
same way as we did
for a binary search.
Sort the first half.
Sort the second half, and then merge them
together.
And then the actual sort is takes just the
one argument
of the array creates the auxiliary array
and then uses that.
Now, it's important to not create the
auxiliary array in the re in
the recursive routine because that could
lead
to extensive cost of extra array creation.
And you'll sometimes see Mergesort
performing poorly because of that bug.
Otherwise this is a very straight forward
implementation.
And it's actually a prototype for
algorithm design
that we'll see come up again and again.
It's called divide and conquer.
Solve a problem
by dividing it into two halves, solving
the two halves,
and then putting the solutions together to
get the appropriate answer.
[COUGH] here's a trace of what Mergesort
does and if you haven't studied a
recursive program before it's worthwhile
studying this thing in, in some detail.
This gives exactly what happens during
each of the calls to merge.
We start out with a big problem to solve
but we divide it in half,
then we divide that one in half, and then
we divide that one in half.
And the very first thing
that we actually do is just compare
and exchange if necessary the first two
elements.
And then we do the same thing for the next
two elements.
Then merge those two together to get the
first four done.
And then we do the same thing for the next
four in the array.
So now we have two sorted sub-arrays at
size four.
And we merge those together to get one of
size eight.
And then we do the same thing on the
right,
and eventually we have two eights that we
merge together
to get the final result.
Very instructive to study this trace to
really understand what this recursive
algorithm is doing.
So now we can animate and again
Mergesort's more
efficient, so we can do more and more
items.
You can see it's got the first half
sorted, now it's working on the second
half.
And then once it gets the second half
sorted,
then it's going to go ahead and merge them
right together to get the sorted result.
It's got a little extra [COUGH] dynamics
in the animation because of the auxiliary
array.
Let's look at it when it's in reverse
order
again it gets the first half done now it's
working on the second half once
it gets the second half done then it goes
ahead and merges together the whole thing
it's just as fast in reverse order as as
in auditory order.
So you can run a Mergesort on huge
problems.
It's a very efficient algorithm.
And so, for example,
what this table shows, if you were to try
to use a insertion sort for a huge
file, say a file with a billion elements,
on
your PC it'd take a few centuries to
finish.
Even on a super computer, if you're using
insertion
sort nowadays it'd maybe take a week or
more.
But if you have a good algorithm like
Mergesort, and you're trying to do a
billion items,
you can do it in just less than half an
hour on your PC.
And a supercomputer can do it in an
instant.
And smaller problems only take an instant
even on your PC.
So you can spend a lot of money or a lot
of time, or you can use a good algorithm.
And that's one of our main themes in this
course.
A good algorithm is much more effective
than spending
money or time wasting money or time using
a bad one.
So let's look at the analysis of
Mergesort, that's a bit of math but very
instructive because this really shows the
power of the divide and conquer method.
And allow us to take a problem that was
taking us quadratic time with methods
like insertion and selection sort, and get
it done in, in log N time with Mergesort.
So that's the proposition Mergesort uses
at most N lg N
compares and 6 N lg N array accesses to
sort any array of size N.
And the way to prove this proposition is
to from
examining the code, to write down what's
called a recurrence relation.
And all that is, it's a mathematical
reflection of what's going on in the code.
If we're sorting N items then let C of N
denote
the number of compares that we need to
sort the N items.
In order to get that done, we're sorting
the left half and the right half and
this notation ceiling of N over 2 and
floor of N over 2 that's the N over
2 round up and N over 2 round down, that's
the size of the two sub-arrays, and
we're going to call the same routine for
that
size, so the number of compares you need
to.
For that is C of N over 2, ceiling of N
over 2
for the left and ceiling of, floor of N
over 2 for the right.
And then for the merge, we need at least,
at most N compares.
If neither one exhausts, we need exactly N
compares.
And so and that's true as long as N is
bigger than 1.
If there's only one thing, we're not
doing any compares at all.
So this is a mathematical formula that we
derive by examining the code but it
completely describes mathematically
what we an upper bound on the number of
compares that are going to be needed.
And similarly for the number of array
accesses, if you count up the number of
times you're accessing an array for a
merge you could be at most six in.
So these are mathematical formulas and
there's techniques
for solving them and we won't go into
that.
This is not a course on discrete
mathematics.
But what we then do is show how to solve
the recurrence when N is a power of 2.
And then it turns out that it holds for
all
N, which we can prove by induction from
the recurrence.
So if you have this recurrence [COUGH]
which
is similar to the ones that we're talking
about.
It's exactly the same when N is a power of
2 let's, let's look at this one.
If
D of N is 2D of N over 2 plus N with D of
1 equals 0, then D of N equals N log N.
We'll look at three proofs of that, just
assuming that N is a power of 2.
If N is a power of 2, then N over 2
is also a power of two, so the recurrence
makes sense.
So this is just a graphical representation
if we
want to compute D of N we want to compute
D
of N over 2 twice.
So that's 2 and then the extra cost
for the merge is N, but if we're going to
do this twice then we have 2N over 2.
So let's, we have 2N over 2s and then for
each one of these we have divided into N
over
4s and each one of those 4N over 4s has an
extra cross for the merge of N over 4.
Well 2N over 2 is N, 4N over 4 is N and we
keep going down, doing that til
we get down to D of 2 and we always for
the extra cross for the merge, we have N.
And how many stages do we have here?
Well, it's the number of times you divide
N by 2 to get down to 2.
That's exactly log base 2 of N, so the
grand total of
all the costs for the merge, which is
where the compares are,
is log N times N, N log N.
It's kind of a graphical
proof or a proof by picture that that
recurrence has that solution.
Here's a little bit more mathematical one:
we write the recurrence down,
and then we divide both sides by N.
So then this is D of N over N equals D of
N over 2 over N over 2 plus 1.
So it's dividing by N.
So now, this is a recurrence that
telescopes.
The first term on the right hand side is
exactly the same
as the left hand side so we can apply the
same formula.
And all it does is divides by 2 again and
then throws out another 1.
And we keep doing that until
we get down to D of 1 which is 0.
And when we've done that, we've thrown out
lg N 1s.
So we get D of N over N equals log N, or D
of N equals N log N.
That's another proof by expansion.
Or using either one of those techniques
you could just get the idea that D of N is
close to Log N or you can write a program
to expand the recurrence and find that.
And then once we have the idea that D of N
equals N lg N, we can plug back into the
original formula.
With the inductive hypothesis that D of N
equals
N lg N, we want to show that D of 2N
equals 2N lg 2N, using the recurrence D of
2N equals 2D of N plus throw out the 2N.
Plugging in N log N we get the desired
result.
We use this same idea on our initial
recurrences
for comparison array accesses to show that
the running,
the number of comparison array accesses is
proportional to N log N for Mergesort.
So that's the running time Mergesort is
fast
other thing that we usually want to know
is memory.
And one of Mergesort's characteristics is
that in
practical applications, it uses extra
space proportional to N.
That is, we need that extra auxiliary
array for the last merge.
We took two sorted subarrays and we talked
about an abstract
in place merge but we didn't have an
actual in place merge.
We were using an extra subarray.
So N place is important.
A lot of times, we're sorting everything
we have.
We want to fill up the memory with stuff
to sort and then sort it.
And search and selection in shellsort are
in place, they don't use any extra memory.
But Mergesort you can only sort really
half of what you can
fit in memory, because you need that
auxiliary array for the other half.
If you want, again, if you think that the
things we're studying
are easy, think about the idea of actually
doing an in-place merge.
People have come up with methods for
getting this done.
So it's theoretically possible, but the
methods are
generally too complex to be useful in
practice and
their not used.
But there could be out there some easy way
to doing in place merge.
That's another great algorithm waiting to
be discovered.
Now there's a, a number of practical
improvements that we can
use to make Mergesort even more efficient
than the simple one
that we've looked at and we'll take a look
of those
because they're examples of techniques
that we can use for other algorithms.
First thing is that Mergesort is too
complicated to use for tiny arrays.
So say the subarrays are only of two, or
three, or four there's too
much overhead with the recursive calls and
so forth to get that done efficiently.
And what's worse is, the recursive nature
of the sort definitely
means that there's going to be lots of
subarrays to be sorted.
So, one improvement that we can make is to
use insertion sort, and just
cut off and use insertion sort which is
simple and efficient for small subarrays.
So that's adding this one line of code to
Mergesort will make it quite a bit faster.
Maybe 20% faster.
The second improvement that we can make
that'll improve the performance
for cases when the array is partly sorted,
is to just
stop if it's already sorted.
And that's going to happen in the case
where the biggest element in the
first half is less or equal to the
smallest item in the second half.
That means it's done.
So that's easy.
We just put a test in the recursive
Mergesort for that,
through this one line of code, to check
whether we're done.
That way, for example, if you were to call
Mergesort for an array that's already in
order it would
just do this test every time and it would
be done in linear time.
That's pretty helpful although not, not
totally helpful
but there's a lot of situations where
that's helpful.
The other thing that's possible to do and
it's a little mind bending so recommended
only for experts.
Is to save a
little bit of time you don't really have
to copy over into the auxiliary array.
You can kind of switch the role of the
input
and the auxiliary array every time you
make a recursive call.
You still need that array but
you can set up the code in this way which
[COUGH]
sort, to sort an array, put the result in
the other one.
To merge an array, put the result back in
the first one.
So it's recursive argument switchery to
get the job done.
And it's effective, it means you don't
have to actually
move items, and that saves a little bit of
time.
So here's a visualization
of what the practical Mergesort might look
like, and this is with
big cutoff to small subfiles.
So you
got a visual feeling of how this sort gets
the job done.
So it's the first little chunck and then
the next little
chunk and then merges those together, and
so forth and so on.
It's a good visual representation of
how Mergesort gets its job done.
That's the basic Mergesort algorithm
that we're going to look at different
versions of in the next.