with mergesort is a good opportunity to
take a look at the intrinsic difficulty in
the sorting problem, now that is called
complexiting and we'll look at that next.
The idea of complexity is it's a frame
work for studying the efficiency of all
the algorithms for solving a particular
problem. That's called Computational
Complexity. And in order to do this
sensibly, we need what's called a model of
computation. The operations that the
algorithms are allowed to perform. For
sorting that's kind of straight forward,
what we're going to do is have a cost
model where we count the comparisons. Now
in framing of the difficulty of problems
were only two things. One is an, what's
called an upper bound which is a cost
guarantee that's provided by some
algorithm for solving the problem. That's
an upper bound and how difficult it is to
solve the problem. We have an algorithm
that can solve it it's the least that
easy. And then we also look for a lower
bound which is a limit on the cost
guarantee of all algorithms. No algorithm
can do better. Now, what we seek ideally
is what's called an optimal algorithm
where we prove that the upper bound and
the lower bound are the same. That's an
algorithm that's, that we know that has
the best possible cost guarantee. That's
the idea for solving any problem. So, for
sorting, let's look at what each of these
are. The model of computation is what's
called a decision tree, tree. And what
that mans is that all we can use is
compare, that's the only way we can access
the data. So, our cost model is the number
compares. Mergesort provides, provides an
upper bound, that's an algorithm that's
guaranteed to get the sort done in time
proportional to N log N. And what we'll
look at now is the lower bound. There's a
trivial lower bound which says you have to
look at all the data, that's N and we'll
look at a better lower bound and see that
mergesort is optimal. So, here's the basic
idea for proving a lower bound for
sorting. Let's say, we ha ve three
different items, a, b and c. Whatever
algorithm we have is going to, first, do a
comparison between two of the items. Let's
say, there a and b. And then there's two
cases. Either it's yes or it's not yes,
let's, let's say, they're distinct. And
there will be some code between the
compares but either way then there is
going to be a different compare. If it's
less than b, maybe the next compare is b
against c. And if you find that b is less
than c and a is less than b, then you know
that they're in the, any algorithm that
does that knows that the items are in the
order a, b, c. If b less than c goes the
other way, then it takes another
comparison to determine the order. In this
case, if c is less than b and a is less
than c then those three compares show that
the order has to be a, c, b and if c is
less than a, then it's going to be c, a,
b, those three compares that c is less
than a, c less than b and a is less than
b. The only possibility is c, a, b. In
continuing on the right perhaps the next
compare is a less than c and maybe if c is
less than a, then another compare, b less
than c. So, in this case, if you go from
top to bottom in the tree with three
compares at most you can determine the
ordering of the three different items. The
idea of the lower bound generalizes this
argument to figure out a number of
compares that you need for a minimum to
determine the ordering among N items. Now,
the height of the tree, as I just
mentioned, is the worst case number of
compares. Out of all the orderings the one
that's further stand in the tree that's
the worst case and so the algorithm, no
matter what the input is, the tree tells
us a bound, the number of compares taken
by the algorithm. And there's got to be at
least one leaf for each possible ordering.
If there's some ordering that is not
appear in a tree corresponding the
particular algorithm then that algorithm
hasn't can't sort, can't, can't tell the
difference between two different
orderings. So, the lower bound as a
proposition, that uses the decision tree
like that to prove that any compare base
sorting algorithm has to use at least log
base two (N) factorial compares in the
worst case. And by Stirling's
approximation, we know that log base
two(N) factorial is proportional to N log
based 2N. And then the proof is
generalizes what I talked about on the
decision tree on the last side, slide. We
assume that the array consist of N
distinct values there's a position created
that describes the performance of any
algorithm to compare sequence done by any
algorithm to determine the N factorial
different orderings. So, this three has to
have at least N factorial leaves and if
the three of height h, it has utmost two^h
leaves. The only, the, the tree that has
the most leaves of height h is totally
complete and that one has two^h leaves.
And those observations give us the lower
bound. Two^h has to be greater than or
equal to the number of leaves. And the
number of leaves has to be greater or
equal to N factorial so that implies the
height of the tree has to be greater than
or equal to log base two(N) factorial
which is proportional to N log N by
Stirling's formula. That's a lower bound
on the complexity of sorting. So, we knew
that the upper bound was N log,
proportional to N log N and we just proved
that the lower bound is proportional to N
log N and that means that mergesort is an
optimal algorithm. That's the first goal
of algorithm design is to try and find
optimal algorithms for the problems that
we need to solve. Now, you have to take
these results in context. Really what we
proved is that mergesort is optimal with
respect to number of compares but we
already know that it's not optimal with
respect to space usage. Mergesort uses
twice as extra space proportional to the
size of the array it has to sort. And
simple algorithms like insertions or dump,
they've they don't use any extra space at
all. So , what we want to take from these
theoretical results is, is a guide when
we're looking at implementations and
trying to solve practical problems. In
this example what it tells us, what theory
tells us is don't try to design a sorting
algorithm that guarantees to use
substantially for your compares than merge
sort. Say, one-half N log N compares. Is
there a method that use one-half N log N
compares? The lower bound says, no. And
that's a very useful thing because
otherwise, we might try to define such an
algorithm. On the other hand, maybe there
is an algorithm that uses N log N compares
and also uses optimal space. It's optimal
with respect to both space and time. And
that's what we're going to look at soon.
The other thing is that the lower bound is
for the particular model of computation
being studied. In this case, compares. It
might not hold if the algorithm has more
information about the keys, for example,
if it's known that the input is almost
ordered, we saw that insertion sort can be
linear time for files that are almost
ordered. Or it's something about the
distribution of key values if there are a
lot of equal keys we can get sorted, get
it sorted faster than, N log N. And maybe
the way the keys are represented. We'll
look at different methods that take
advantage of such properties. So,
partially ordered arrays we may not need N
log N compares. Duplicate keys, we may not
need N log N compares, we're going to look
at the method that I guess that down in
linear time and a lot of situations. And
later on, we'll look at digital properties
of keys where we can use digital character
compares instead of whole key compares and
got a faster sort for certain practical
applications. Computational complexity is
very useful way to help us understand
properties of algorithm and help guide our
design decisions.