Next we'll take a look at comparators
which is a Java mechanism that helps us
sort. The same data on different sort
keys, different orders. And you're
familiar with this. Your music library
maybe I, at one point, you sort it by the
artist's name. In this case we're looking
at the b's. But in another situation, you
might want to sort it by song names to
look through it by song names. That's the
same data using different sort keys. How
do we arrange to do something is natural
as this in our Java sorts? Now, we use the
fourth in order to be able to implement
sorts that can sort any type of data, we
use Java's Comparable interface. And that
concept is that there's some natural
ordering of the data that you'll want to
use most of the time, that's what the
Comparable interface is all about. But
there's a different interface called the
Comparator Interface which is a way to
help a sort, using some alternate order or
many different orders on the same data.
And the Comparator interface again just
says that it's going to implement a method
compare() that compares two different keys
of the given type, of the generic type.
Again it has to be a total order and this
is very familiar for example with strings.
There's many different ways that we might
want to sort strings. We might want to use
the natural alphabetic order or we might
want to make it case insensitive or maybe
there is just different languages that
have different rules of the ordering.
We're sorting strings but we're
implementing a different ordering, various
different orderings on that same data.
That's what the Comparator interface is
for. So the Java system sort will have a
different. [cough] method to implement
comparators. The idea is that you create a
comparator object and then pass that as a
second argument to Java's sort routine and
we can do the same thing for our sorts.
The idea is when a decouple, the
definition of the data type from the
definition of what it means to compare to
items of that type. With the natural
order, we had to put the definition
compared to within the data type. With
comparators, we can do that outside of the
data type even at some later time. Strings
were defined and as part of the Java
system but we can define our own ordering
on strings with the comparator. So in our
sort implementations we can change them as
shown in this example to support
comparators. To support comparators in our
sort implementations we'll pass an array
of objects and instead of an array of
comparable and then, there's a second
argument passed a comparator. Then, the
less method will take that comparator as
an argument and this is the one that
actually invokes the method compare two
different keys. This is a straightforward
modification to our sorts. And then
exchange of course rather doing comparable
has to use object. So with these
straightforward changes at the comparator
as argument to the sort and to less and
make array to be sorted array of objects,
it's easy to convert any of our
implementations to support comparators. To
implement a comparator you can use this
code as a model. I won't go through it all
in detail just to point out that this
implements two different comparators as
nested classes. Say, for this fictional
class Student, that's got two instance
variables - name and section. And the first
one called by name implements a comparator
for students and when you compare two
students by name, it's going to use the
string comparative method. If you're going
to implement it compared to students by
section, then it'll return just the
difference of the sections which is my
minus if less zero if equal then plus if
greater. And this code is straight forward
way to implement comparators that you can
use as a model. If you need to be able to
sort data on two different keys. So
[cough] here is just an example of what
happens if would those implemented
comparators for that class student using
the Java system sort, if you call array
that sort with your a rray of students and
you give it this by name comparator, it
will put them in order alphabetical order
by the name field. And if you give it to
by section comparator, it will them in
order by the second field very convenient
for all kinds of data processing
applications. And we came up with that
before when we're talking about using a
sort for the Graham scan. We needed to
have a comparison for points that orders
them by the polar angle they make, make
with the given point p. That's what we
needed for the Graham scan algorithm for
the convex hull. Points are defined data
type for geometric objects and so what we
need is code that will compute the polar
angle and use that as the basis for
comparison. There's an easy way to do this
based on CCW that is described here in
this text. Most of the time all you need
to do is do the CCW of the two points. You
either have to check whether [cough] the,
one of the points is above p and the other
one is below. But otherwise, usually it's
a CCW call in this code which again I
won't go through in detail as an
implementation of a comparator for two D
points. It implements the compare method
that takes two points as argument and with
just a little bit of calculation is able
to do the compare. So this code is the
basis for applying the sort, system sort
method or any sort method for the Graham
scan for the convex hull that we did at
the end of the last lecture. So that's the
basis for the Graham scan method for the
convex hull that we used at the last, at
the end of the last lecture.