Now we're going to take a look at what
happens when we have significant numbers
of duplicate keys which is not at all
unusual in practical applications. So, in,
in fact, often, the purpose of a sort is
to bring items with equal keys together
for like the example that I gave where we
had cities and time. There's a lot of
detailed data and the time and maybe the
whole goal of the sort is to group them by
cities so we can ship out the data for
each city, to each city and there's plenty
of other examples like that in data
processing where we find maybe remove
duplicates from a mailing list or all the
job applicants that we get, we might want
to sort them by the college attendant. So
the sort does huge files with huge numbers
of duplicate keys. So, a sort, it's
worthwhile to take a careful look at what
the implication of that is. So again,
typical characteristics we have a huge
file but small number of different key
values. So let's look at our algorithms in
that situation. So Mergesort, it doesn't
matter that much what the key values are
like and it's actually, we can show that
Mergesort always uses between one-half, N
log N and N log N compares. Quicksort
actually, they're up until the 1990s the
most widely used implementation took
quadratic time. For files with large
numbers of equal keys and that was
actually found by applications user and,
and that's the standard Quicksort that was
in all the textbooks almost all the
textbooks if you did not stop the
partitioning on equal keys it would run in
quadratic time. So we want to do better
than this. So the mistake happens if we
put all the items equal to the
partitioning item on one side which is a
natural way to implement it and the
consequence is if you have all the keys
equal, then partitioning doesn't really do
anything. You just peels off one key to do
file size n then you get a sub file size n
- one and then n - two and so forth and
the result is a quadratic tim e algorithm.
Our implementation, we stopped the
partitioning scans on items equal to the
partitioning item and then in that case,
when all the keys are equal, it's going to
divide it exactly in the middle. And then
in that case, when all the keys are equal,
it's going to divide at exactly in the
middle. And then in that case you get an N
log N compares. But actually when you
think about it, why don't we just put all
the items equal to the partitioning item
in place. That's, that's really a
desirable way to look at it and let's take
a look at that option. So the goal is so
called three way partitioning. So what we
want to do is get the array into three
parts so then now we have two pointers
into the middle. One that is the boundary
between the keys that are less than the
partitioning element and those that are
equal of the partitioning element. Another
one that's the boundary between the keys
that are equal of partitioning elements
and the one that is greater. And then in
the middle are all the equal keys and
that's what we'd like to arrange. Now
until the 1990s, conventional wisdom among
people implementing system was, wasn't
worth doing this. But, but actually it's a
problem that Edsger Dijkstra had proposed
in the 70s as an example of, of
programming problem. He was really
interested in analyzing correctness of
programs and showing that this how you
could convince yourself that this program
was operating as expected. But in the
1990s we figured out that really this was
going to be an effective way to sort. And
this was taking a look at the Qsort that a
user found was broken and, and now, this
method is incorporated into some plenty of
system sorts. So let's take a look at how
it works with the demo its more
complicated than standard Quicksort
partitioning. A bit more complicated
because there's more to do. So now we have
our i pointer which is right to the left
of stuff we haven't seen ye t and then, we
have two other pointers that maintain,
maintain these boundaries everything to
the right of gt is known to be greater
than partitioning element. Everything to
the left of lt is known to be less and
between lt and i is known to be equal. And
all the method does is maintain this in
variants so let's do an example or two and
see how that works. So we increment i and
then figure out what to do. So, now it's
less than the partitioning element. So,
what we want to do is increment lt's. So
now we have one that's definitely less
than the partitioning element and lt is,
is pointing at the partitioning element.
And so now in, increment both lt and i so
that's the first case there. So now we
have a second item b. That's less than the
partitioning element so exchange with lt
and increment them both. So, we're moving
the smaller ones than the partitioning
element to the left of lt and keeping lt
pointing on a partitioning element. Now,
what about when we get one that's greater
than the partitioning elements? So, in
that case, we exchange greater the one
over at the right with i and decrement gt.
So now, we have one over to the right that
we know is greater than the partitioning
element. Notice that we didn't increment i
because that element z that is over in the
right, really hasn't been compared to the
partitioning element yet. But we did
decrement gt so we made progress. So now
what happens here, now i is pointing to a
bigger one so we're going to exchange it
with the one at gt and decrement gt again.
And again, y is bigger, so exchange it,
decrement gt. Now we have the c, that one
smaller so that's the first case. So we'll
move it to the left of lt and increment
both lt and i. W is a bigger one, let us
to go over to the right. Now we have i
pointing to an element that's equal to the
partitioning element. And what are we
supposed to do then? Well, to maintain the
variant there we just need to increment i.
And again it 's pointing to one that's
equal of partitioning element increment i.
And now one more time and now it's
pointing to one that's greater so we
exchange that with gt and decrement gt and
i is pointing to the one that was there
and that ones smaller. So we exchange it
will lt and increment both i and lt and
now where the point, where the pointers
have crossed i and gt across there's
nothing that we haven't examined yet. So,
our partitioning is complete. Here's a
trace of Dijkstra 3-way partitioning for
his problem which is when there's just
three different values in the file. Our
problem we were treating partitioning,
equal of partitioning element as one value
less than as another and greater than as
another. And so this, this trace
illustrates how we always make some
progress and eventually we get the file
sorted. The implementation is amazingly
simple. The whole partitioning process for
three-way partitioning and the modern
programming language like Java simply
maintains the invariances described in the
demo. If we find one that's less we
exchange i and lt and increment them both.
If it's greater we exchange i and gt and
decrement that. Otherwise, we increment i.
Could, could hardly be simpler. In fact,
is simpler in many ways than these
standard implementation of Quicksort. In
fact, there's an argument for just using
this implementation of Quicksort and
forgetting about horse because it performs
so well in so many practical situations.
Here's a visual trace of 3-way Quicksort
for situation with plenty of equal keys.
And again, when there's a lot of equal
keys then there's going to be place where
one of those is chosen, it's partitioning
element then a big chunk of the array gets
handled just in a partitioning process.
Now, there's actually some deeper reasons
why this method is important and one thing
to do is to realize that the lower bound
that we talked about before depended on
the keys being distinct. So, worst case
for lower bounds is when the keys are all
distinct. But if we have a situation where
there are a lot of equal keys, that model
is wrong. It's not too difficult to get a
similar lower bound for the model when we
know that there are some equal keys. So,
for example this is a rather complicated
formula but not too bad but in a sense
that if you know that the i-th key, it
occurs xi times you can write down a lower
bound for the number of comparisons that
are going to be required in the worst
case. And, what's interesting about three
way partitioning is that the number of
compares that it uses is equal to this
lower bound within a constant factor. So
that's entropy-optimal and what that means
is whatever the distribution of equal keys
in there, this thing is going to use a
number of compares that's proportional to
the best that you could possibly do. The
proof for this fact is quite beyond the
scope of this course but it's still an
important fact. And the, the bottom line
is that if you randomize the order and use
three-way partitioning then there's lot of
applications where your sort routine is
going to be linear not N log N so it will
be much more faster than Mergesort and you
know, the methods for really a broad class
of applications. So, taking a look at
equal keys is carefully is something that
can lead us to very efficient Quicksort