Now we'll look at the problem that's
related to sorting called selection that's
also well solved by Quicksort
partitioning. This is a simpler problem.
We're given an array of n items that are
ordered and our task is to find the k-th
largest. There's lots of important
applications for this. So like if we
wanted to find the minimum item that's k =
zero or the maximum item that's k = n -
one or the medium that's k = n/2. And
there's many kinds of applications from
people processing data. I wanted to find
the top k or the medium or other order
statistics so that's what selection is all
about. Now, here's an example where we
want to use theory as a guide. What kind
of efficiency might we expect in a
selection algorithm. Well, first of all,
it's easy to see that we can solve
selection and in law at end time. How
would we do that? Well, we just sort the
array and then if we want to find the
smallest, we'll look at the first position
or the largest, we'll look in the last
position or the medium, we'll look in the
middle. In fact, if k is small, the
running time is going to be proportional
to n. Because if you're looking for the
smallest, you can just go through the
array and find the small or the smallest
in one pass through or if you're two,
you'll find it and two passes through. So,
you can imagine trying to look for a
selection algorithm that takes time
proportional to n and also the lower bound
is n because you have to look at
everything. If you don't look at
everything, you might miss the one item
that you're looking for. So, from these
observations it's clear that what we, what
we'd like is a selection algorithm that
takes linear time. But at this point, the
question is, is there a linear time
algorithm that works for every k? Or
possibly selection is as hard as sorting.
This kind of question plagued a lot of
people in this late 60's or early 70's as
these types of problems emerge for
computing applications. So, it's an
interesting question to think about for
sure. Well in his original paper in 1961
Hoare gave a solution to the selection
problem based on partitioning. And the
idea is just a version of Quicksort in a
way. We're going to do our partitioning so
that we get entry a(j) in place of the
array. Nobody to the left is larger,
nobody to the right is bigger. But then,
when we're doing selection, what we'll do
is just go in one sub array or the other
depending on where j is. If j = k, we're
done, we've found the k is the largest. If
k is to the left of j, then, we just do
the left sub-file which is set high to j -
one. And if k is to the right of j, we
just do the right subfiles that load the j
+ one and that's all this code does is
that it, we could do a recursive, a
recursive call but this just does it by
resetting the values of the parameters. Do
one partition then check whether you to
your k-th element is going to be on the
left part or the right part and reset
lower high accordingly. If it's equal,
then you found it and you return it and
you keep going until you get to a point
where you have only one element. That's
the a Quicksort like implementation
solving the selection problem. Notice
again that it depends on the random
shuffle at the beginning that's going to
be important for performance. Alright. So
there needs to be a mathematical analysis
to, to characterize the running time of
this program in the fact is that quick
select this method takes linear time on
the average. We won't give the full proof.
It's actually quite a bit more complicated
than the one just on for Quick sort. But
intuitively, we can see kind of what
happens each partitionings that maybe
splits the array approximately in half. So
that, that means you'd have, if you did
exactly and [inaudible] + n/2 + n/4 and so
forth which adds up to about two N compare
so linear cross. If you do the, actually
it doesn't cut it in half at exactly each
time only on average so you need a fuller
analysis like the one we did for Quicksort
and the bottom line of that analysis gives
the number of comparisons required as a
function of n and of k in terms of this
formula here and if you plug in k = n/2,
you get the result that the number of
compares required to fine the median
that's the highest value this formula can
take is two + two natural log of two. So,
linear time to find the k-th largest for
any value of k. Now again it's going to
use, this is a method that's linear time
on the average. It's actually going to be
quadratic in the worst case but again, the
chance of that it will happen with a
random shuffle is less than the chance
that we'll be struck by lightning. Its a
probabilistic guaranteed fast algorithm.
Now, from a theoretical standpoint that's
a little unsatisfied and in, in 1973,
there's a famous paper that found a
compared base selection algorithm that
guarantees to solve the problem in linear
time. This is areal landmark in the theory
of algorithms because for a long time,
it's not known, we knew we could have the
average case, the linear time but could we
find a worst case? And this paper found
such a construction. Now in practice, this
construction is, is rather high. So, the
method is not really used in practice. And
so, there is still the goal of a, of a
fast guaranteed linear time selection
algorithm maybe somebody in this class
will invent someday. This is another
example where we use theory as a guide.
It's still worth while to look for a
practical linear time worst case
algorithm. Well then, maybe somebody in
this class will invent that but until
something like that is discovered use the
quick select based on Quicksort
partitioning you can get linear time
selection when you don't need a full sort.
That selection of simple problem like
sorting that is well sound with Quicksort
partitioning.