Now we're going to look at binary heaps
which is an ingenious and very simple data
structure that's going to help us
implement all the priority queue
operations quickly. So, the idea of a
binary heap is based on the idea of a
complete binary tree. So, a complete
binary tree, well first of all, a binary
tree is either empty or it's a node with
links to left and right binary trees so
that's an example of a binary tree. A
complete binary tree is one that's
perfectly balanced, except possibly for
the bottom level. So there might be a few
nodes on the, on the bottom level and one
level lower than the bottom level. But
otherwise, all the levels are full. We'll
see how that looks in just a second. The
property of complete tree is that the
height of a complete tree with n nodes is
the biggest integer less than log base two
of N, and that's really easy to convince
yourself that that's true because the
height, if you add nodes one at a time
going from left to right on the bottom
level say, the height only increases when
n is a power of two. Complete binary trees
actually happen in nature. Here's an
example of one that goes one, two, three,
four levels at least, so sixteen pushes at
the end there. Alright. Now, the way we're
going to use complete binary trees to
implement priority queues is to first of
all, associate information with each node.
We'll put our keys in the nodes, and also
we're going to represent it with an array.
So, [cough] when we start putting the keys
in the nodes we're going to impose one
more condition that's called Heap
Ordering. And the idea is that the
parent's key is going to be no smaller
than its children's key for, and that's
true for every node in the tree. The array
representation, all we do is, we put we
start with indices at one, it's a little
less calculation. That way we leave a(0)
empty and then we just take the nodes in
level order. So first, we put the root.
Then, we put the two nodes on the fi rst
level going left from right. And then, all
the nodes on the third level, going from
left to right and so forth. This is
interesting because we can draw the tree
to get more intuition about what's
happening. But in the actual data
structure representation, we don't need
any links at all. It's just an array. The
way that we move around the tree is by
doing arithmetic on the indices. So let's
look at a few properties of binary heaps.
So that's complete binary trees
represented in array with keys in the
nodes satisfying the heap order property.
Well, first thing is that a(1) is the
largest key. It's larger than the keys and
its two children and they're larger than
theirs and so forth so it's the largest
key in the data structure. The other thing
is, as I just mentioned, you can use the
array in the seeds to move through the
tree. For example, if the node is at
position K, index K in the array, then
it's parent is a K over two and that's
integer divide. So the parents of say H
and G are both N. H is ten, G is at
eleven, N's at five so both of those are
ten over two, eleven over two, integer
divide is five. And going the other way
it's easy to see that the children of the
node at K are 2k and 2k + one. So we don't
need explicit lengths at all to represent
these data structures. We can just use
array indices. So [cough] that's the basic
setup or the invariant that we're going to
maintain in this data structure. And now,
what we're going to do is take a look at
just a couple of different scenarios that
where we violate that invariant
temporarily and then fix it. And that's
going to give us the flexibility that we
need to implement priority queue
operations. So one scenario shown here, is
if for whatever reason a child's key
becomes larger than its parent's key. So
in this case, we have an example where T,
the node T here, its value changes and it
becomes larger than its parent key P. So,
the heap order condition is satisfied
everywhere, except at this node. Well,
it's easy to fix this one. All we do is
exchange the key in the child with the key
in the parent. After that exchange, then,
that would have T up here and P down here
then the heap order condition is satisfied
at that node because the parent was
smaller, so that one's smaller. And so
that one is still smaller so T is after
its exchanged up here will be bigger than
both its children. But the heap condition
will be violated cuz T is still smaller
than S. So we have do it again, exchange
it with S. So we move up the tree,
exchanging the larger key with its smaller
parent, until we get to a point where its
larger than both its children. That's
restoring the heap order along the path
from the place where it's violated to the
root. You can think of that as kind of
like the well known Peter Principle where
a node gets promoted to a level where it
finally can't be better than, than it's
boss. It's a level of it's maximum
incompetence. And implementing that in
code is really easy. We call that the swim
operation, it swims up to the top. And if
we have a node at index K and we know the
heap condition is violated there, as long
as we're not at the root and K's parent, K
over two is less than A of K. Then, we
just exchange it with its parent, and move
up. That's the swim operation to eliminate
a violation when a key value increases.
[cough] So for example, this gives us a
way to insert a new element into a heap.
What we do is, we add a new node at the
end of the heap, so this one position
over. The thing is, remember represented
in array, one, two, three And so forth. So
the [cough] next empty position in the
array there's a place to put a new node.
And then we just declare that, that's part
of the heap and that node, well if it's
less than its parent, we're fine. But in
general, we have to check whether the heap
condition is violated and exchange it with
its par ent as long as it's smaller and
that's just perform the swim operation. So
if N is the number of items in the heap,
defined to be in the heap we're going to
increment it, store a new key there, there
and then perform the swim operation. So
that's a quick implementation of the
insert operation. And notice since it's
just going from bottom to top in the heap
it takes at most one plus log base two of
N compares. [cough] Now there's another
scenario where a key becomes smaller. For
whatever reason, a parent becomes key
decreases, it might become smaller than
one or both of its children. In this case,
the value at position two has changed to H
for whatever reason and that's smaller, in
this case, than both its children. So how
do we fix that violation? Well, that one's
also easy. We figure out which of the
children is larger. In this case, it's the
S, and we exchange our exchange that one
with the one that's violating the
condition. So that's moving the smaller
key down. After that exchange, then S is
in position two, and it's bigger than both
P and H. And the heap condition is only
violated again where H is sitting. And
again, we keep going until getting to the
bottom, or getting to a place where both
children are smaller. And that's maybe a
little bit what happens when a, a new boss
is hired from the outside and then the two
subordinates struggle to take over that
position and then the bros, boss would get
demoted to it's level of competence. And
again, that level of flexibility. Here's
the implementation of it. And again, it's
quite straightforward using the [cough]
index arithmetic to move around in the
heap. If we're, and that's called the sink
operation, cuz we're going down the heap.
If were at position K, then what we need
to worry about it is the nodes at 2k and
2k + one. And the first thing to check is
find out which one's bigger. It's either
2k or 2k + one and so set j accordingly.
So that's j now, is, after this st atement
is the larger of the two children. And
don't forget to check that we're going off
the end of the heap. And then if, [cough]
the K is not less than either one of
those, then we're done. If it is, then we
exchange with the larger of the two
children and move down the heap. Again,
just a few lines of code to eliminate the
violation when a key value in a heap
decreases. And that one we're going to use
to implement delete the maximum in a heap.
So delete the maximum, we have to do two
things, one thing is the size of the heap
has got to go down by one. The other thing
is return the maximum. Well, we know that
[cough] one that we want to return is the
one at the root. So we'll save that value
away to return to the client. And then,
since it has to go down by one the place
to get the to remove the element from the
heap is at the end of the array cuz it's
now going to have to not occupy that
position, so we take that element and
replace the root with it. So I move the H
up and actually, put the root value there
just exchange them but it's not longer in
the heap. Now, that element which went
from the bottom to the top is most likely
going to violate the heap order. It's
going to be smaller than one of its, both
of its children. So, we do a sink. [cough]
now in this case to implement the lead max
we save away that value at the root in max
and we eliminate loitering by nulling out
that vacated position then return the max
value. So that's an implement,
implementation of the delete max operation
for heap using sink where a key value that
decreases, go down, goes down in the heap.
So let's just take a look at what happens
with a, a real heap with the demo when we
do these things. And you'll have a good
feeling for how this data structure works.
So, we're starting at some point where we
have these ten keys in heap and it's heap
order. So we've drawn the data structure
with the links, so we have an intuition
for what's going on. But all the program
sees is the array and grey at the bottom
where T's in position one, P and R are
position two and three, and so forth. So
now, suppose that we're supposed to add S.
So to add it to the heap, that's going to
go in the position at the end. Then now
we've added it to the heap just by
incrementing N, putting it in there but
now we have to bring the heap order back
into condition. And so that's going to,
now that key is larger than its parent so
we're going to swim it up exchange it with
its parent as long as it's smaller than
its parent. So, first thing it goes up
exchange with the S, it's still bigger
than P. So we exchange it with the T and
now we're done because S in not bigger
than T and the heap order condition is now
satisfied everywhere in the heap. So, with
just two exchanges we insert that new
element in the heap in this case. I now
suppose the next operation is remove the
maximum. So, we're going to take T and
exchange it with the last element and then
declare that to be no longer part of the
heap. So now [cough] we have to bring the
heap order back because it might be
violated at the root so now we invoke the
sink where we exchange that node with the
larger of its two children until we find a
place where its larger than both its
children. So S is the larger of the two
children R and S and now H is still
smaller than both it's children so we
promote the larger, which is P. Now H has
no right child, just a left child and it's
larger than that one, so we're finished
with that operation. We've removed the
maximum and we still have our data
structure heap ordered and our n keys
stored in first n positions in the array.
Let's remove the maximum again. Again we
take it out by exchanging this time G with
the root and then [cough] decrease the
size of the heap by one. Just take that
out. Now, t he node of the root violates
the heap border so we have to exchange it
with the largest of it's two children, in
this case that's R. Again, G is not larger
than it's two children so we have to
exchange it with the larger of the two,
that's O and now we are done, we've
removed the largest again. Now suppose we
insert S back into the heap. So [cough]
that's adding it at the end, violates the
heap order exchange it with the parent
smaller and keep doing until we get to a
place where it's larger than its two
children. In this case, S goes all the way
up to the root. And it's all heap ordered
again. So that's a little survey of some
operations on a heap and you can see how
every operation is done with just a few
exchanges along the path from the bottom
to the top or the top to the bottom. Okay,
here's the complete Java implementation of
a priority queue using the binary heap
data structure. [cough] it's actually not
so different from the elementary
implementations that we looked at in the
last section. Our representation is an
array of keys and a size, that's the
number of items in the heap. [cough] for
simplicity, we'll show the code where the
client gives the capacity of the heap. We
can use resizing array, in industrial
strength implementation, the same that, we
did for stacks and other data structures
where we use arrays. So we'll build a new
array of keys and we have to use an ugly,
ugly cast because we can't have generic
arrays in Java. And that, so it's
comparable and, and we need one more than
the capacity to handle this thing where,
we don't use position zero. So the
priority queue operations, is the insert
and del max that we showed in the previous
slides, is empty, is just checking whether
n is equal to zero. We have the swim and
sink functions that we showed earlier. And
then we have helper functions less and
exchange, that access the array directly
so that the co de doesn't have to access
directly. That's a complete implementation
of priority queues in Java. And this is,
this implementation by itself is extremely
significant because, it's really very
simple, optimal representation of the
data. And only a little arithmetic with
array indices. But as you can see by
looking at this table, it gives us a way
to implement priority queues where, both
operations are guaranteed to happen in log
N time. Now, experts have worked to come
up with improvements on this and there are
slight improvements possible. We can make
the heap d way rather than just two way
and depending on the frequency of
execution of the uncertain del max
operations that might work out better.
There's an advanced data structure called
a Fibonacci Heap, where inserts are done
in constant time and delete max done in
log N time on an average over all the
operations. That ones generally too
complicated to use in practice. But still
again, using theory as a guide maybe
there's a way to, [cough] to decrease
costs a little bit from binary heaps. And
of course, we cannot get down to having
constant time for all operations. Why?
Well, we can sort with a heap by inserting
all the elements and then deleting the
maximum of getting a sort done and that
would be in linear time if we had this
kind of variation. If, if we have constant
time operations for both insert and del
max. But for certain applications, we can
get close to constant time for one or the
other operations and that'll be useful in
different implementations. Now, there's an
important consideration, that, in, that we
have to bring up related to the
programming language and [cough] this is,
a more general consideration than usually
we bring into focus in algorithms but it's
worthwhile mentioning. We're assuming that
the client doesn't get to change the keys
while they're on the priority queue. And
it's better not to ass ume that it's
better to arrange for that in our
implementations by using keys that are
immutable, who's values don't change.
There's many reasons that immu, immutable
keys are [cough] that programming
languages provide the capability to build
immutable keys and, and this is a fine
example of one. So and we'll talk more
about that in a minute. The other things
that, that, we didn't talk about in the
implementation should throw in, exception.
If the client tries to delete from an
empty priority queue and we should have a
no argument constructor, and use a
resizing array, to, account for gradual
growth and shrinkage in an industrial
strength implementation. Usually we
provide two implementations, one that's
max oriented, one t hat's min oriented so
that nobody get's confused and they're the
same except the less and greater switch.
And we'll see later on, there's times when
we want to add, expand the API and provide
other operations like removing an
arbitrary item from the priority queue, or
give the client in the API the capability
of changing the priority of an item. Our
sink and swim methods are good for making
this happen, but we'll, delay these
implementations until we need them in a
more complicated algorithm. So what about
mutability? So in every thing in Java is
implemented as a data type, a set of
values and operations on those values and
the idea of immutable data type, is you
can't change the value once it's created.
So that's kind of like, when you [cough]
when you, when you create a literal value
to be assigned to an integer, it has that
value. So here, here's an example say
using the data type for vectors might be a
way to implement vectors. So we put the
word final to means that instance methods
can't be overridden. And not only that,
instance variables are private, they can't
be seen from the outside and they don't
change. And so a constructor for an
immutable vector data type, it might take
an array [cough] as it's argument, and
that array has got values stored in it,
say doubles, and those are, those can
change but what immutable implementation
would do would be to copy those values
into the local [cough] data array instance
variable and then those values are not
going to change. And the instance methods
won't change them and the client can't
change them. So that value stays the same.
Lots of, implementations, data-type
implementations in Java are immutable,
like string is immutable. When you create
a string that value doesn't change.
[cough] if you want a new string, you have
to create a new string, using
concatenation or some other operation. And
the same with the wrapper types, like
integer and double, or color, and, what
lots of things. Whereas on the other hand,
sometimes, the whole purpose, of a data
type is to maintain a changing value like
a good example is like a counter, or a
stack. So you wouldn't put those things on
a priority queue cuz the value is changing
but the other ones you would. So the
advantages of immutability and again,
maybe this isn't the place to really sell
those advantages more for a programming
language course is that it, it really
simplifies debugging. We can be have more
confidence that our priority queue
operations are going to work correctly if
we know that the type of data that's on
the priority queue is immutable. If the
client could change the values, how do we
know that the heap border operation is
preserved? If we want the client to be
able to change values, we're going to
provide methods for that purpose as I just
mentioned. And there's many other reasons
that people use immutable data types.
There is a disadvantage that you have to
create a new object for every data type
value but for a lot of applications that
disadvan tage is not viewed to be
significant compared to the advantages.
Here's a quote from a one of Java's
architect, Josh Black. Classes should be
immutable unless there's a very good
reason to make them mutable. If a class
cannot be made immutable, you should still
limit its immutability as much as
possible. And many programmers live by
that kind of precept. So that's a basic
implementation of priority queues using
the heap data structure represented as an