Next we're going to look at the use of the
binary heap data structure to implement a
clever sorting algorithm known as
Heapsort. So here's the basic plan. What
we're going to do is we have our end keys
and we'll have them in an array. We'll
view that array as eventually being a max
heap. So what we have to do first is to
rearrange the keys in the array to heap
order it. So just make it so that every
key is larger than it's two children. And
for example, the largest of all the keys
is at the root. And then, the next phase
would be to take that heap ordered array
and get, get it to be a sorted result in,
in place. And again, the, heap is stored
in the array, with the first key position
one, next to position two and three and
like that. So the end result would be like
that, with, no keys in the heap, but all
the keys in the array in sorted order. So
it's a little exercise in abstraction.
Part of the array is the heap. Part of the
array is the sorted sub array. And
eventually we bring it down to the whole
thing being sorted. It's very little code
beyond the basic heap code that we've
looked at can get this implemented. And
that's called Heapsort. Let's take a demo
of how Heapsort works in our example. So
the idea is we're going to use a bottom up
method. So all that means is we start with
an array in arbitrary order and then we're
going to work from the bottom up to make
sure that it's heap order. Well all the
nodes with no children are heap order,
they are only a size one, the first one we
have to worry about is this one here the
root, the root. We haven't examined yet,
it's children are heap ordered so it's a
small heap of size three that may not be
heap ordered. In this case it's not
because one of the children is larger, so
that's where things are going to start. We
have a lot of one node heaps and then
we're going to have to perform the sync
operation on this one, that node five,
that's, in this case just to change it
with it's parent. And then proceeding in
that way, moving bottom up or moving from
right to left, the next thing we do is but
then worry about a three node heap that's
heap ordered and we're fine. Now we'll
move over to the T and again, that's the
root of a three node heap that's heap
ordered except at the root. We may need to
fix it with the sync operation. In this
case nothing is required because it's
larger than its children, so we have a
three node heap. And then we move one more
to the left, now we're looking at the R.
Again root of a three node heap may or may
not be heap ordered, we do have to do the
sync operation. In this case that brings
the X up. A three node heap. Now we go to
two. Now that's the root of a seven node
heap. We know the two three node heaps
that are the children are heap ordered but
we may have to correct the heap ordering
at the root so we do a sync on two. And
that's going to involve, exchanging with
the T, because T is larger than O. And
exchanging with the P because P is larger
than O. Now that heap is a seven node heap
that's all heap ordered, and then the last
thing is to do the root of the whole thing
and again, now the two sub trees are heap
ordered, that's what we mean by bottom up,
we took care of the heep ordering from the
bottom up. And so we'll do a sync on the S
and bring it into a heap ordering, so
that's with just a few exchanges we got
that whole array heap order, and now what
we want to do is take advantage of the
heap ordering in the array to do a sort.
And the concept is very simple. Right away
we have the maximum element in the array
right at the root, we want that to be at
the end so that's what we're going to do
and that's what we're going to do is just
put it at the end. We exchange the element
at the root with the last element. Pull it
off the heap and then that's our example.
We might have violated the heap order
condtion at the heap right now. So now we
have to do a sync operation on, on the E.
And so, it's larger than, it's both
children, and the larger of the two
children is T, so we promote the T. And
the P is larger, the two children promote
that and then finally, the E comes down to
the bottom. So now that's one step in the
sort, we got the largest element off. Now
the next largest element in the array is
now at the root of the heap. We're going
to do the same thing, exchange it with the
last element in the heap. Then now that T
is in its final position in the sorted
array, we take it off the heap. So now,
we've got a heap with nine elements and
two of the elements in the array are
already in their final position. And now
this one's not heap ordered, so we have to
exchange over the largest of its two
children. In this case that involves
regarding the S and the R. Now it's heap
ordered. So that's the end of the two
steps in Heapsort. And then we just keep
going. Pulling off the largest element
from the heap. Exchanging it with the.
Element in the heap in the largest
position in the array which brings that
element into its final position in the
sorted array. And then adjusting the heap
ordering with the sync operation. So that
E again is going to come down and now it
only goes down one step in this case. So
now R exchanges with M. It's in it's final
position and you can see down at the
bottom, the large elements in the array
filling in, in their final position, in
the, the left part of the array is
representing the heap. The R goes off the
heap, do the sync operation on the M, and
now we have a heap ordered array. So now
do the P, exchange that with the A. Take
it off the heap. Do the sync operation on
the A. Now we're going to do the O.
Exchange that with the E. Take it off the
heap. Do the sync operation on E which
involves promoting the larger of its two
children, until it gets to the bottom, or
a place where it's larger than both its
children. So now we have, just five
elements left. We'll, get the M. Do heap
ordering on the, heap of four and that
only involves one exchange. Now we get the
L. A exchange for the larger of its two
children. While, they're both the same, so
i t goes with the left one. That's the
heap of size three. Pull off the first E,
it's already heap ordered. Pull off that
E. And, now we are left with only one
element in the heap in this in the first
position, so there is nothing to do. So
with a series of in exchange and then sync
operations, we pull the sorted array out
of the heap. Okay. This, slide summarizes
the code for, heap construction. And as
you can see, it's a one liner. We go
backwards through the heap. Starting at N
over two because the, N over, half of the,
right most half of the array is just
little heaps of size one. We just go
backwards doing a sync starting at K. So
that's the first piece of code for heap
ordering an array with arbitrary values
and then these diagrams summarize the sync
calls that, that we just went through in
the demo starting at five, four, three,
two, one. As you can see, only one, two,
three, four, five exchanges are needed to
bring this into heap order. Then the
second pass again that's only a two liner,
we exchange the first element with the one
at the end and then decrement the size of
the heap and then do a sync operations.
And these diagrams summarize the sync
operations that we showed in the demo. On
every smaller heap, now we continue just
performing sync operations at the root
until we get a completely sorted array. So
given the sink implementation, we had done
a one liner for the first pass and a three
liner for the second pass so that gives a
complete implementation of heap sort with
the code that we have given so for, so
far. There's is one little detail when you
are sorting an array of course position
zero comes into account and we've been
building our heaps from position one. So,
but we can take care of that in the less
and exchange methods by just decrementing
the indices in those methods to have it
work as if the array were zero through n.
That's a little implementation detail, but
otherwise this is a fine sword
implementation, that actually is very
little code, and its got a place in, in
the theory of algorithm, that I will talk
about in a second. This is just another
trace without the data-structure shown, to
just show in our standard way, the
elements in black and red are the ones
that are touched and the elements in grey
are the ones that are not touched at all.
And to just show that this thing gets the
sort done with touching relatively few
elements. That's a trace. Let's look at an
animation, an animation with Heapsort is
interesting to watch so the construction
of the heap happens in a blink and now
it's pulling off the largest elements,
moving from right to left. So again, a
very efficient way to get a sorting job
done. So what about the mathematical
analysis? Well the mathematical analysis,
for the Heapsort part is pretty easy. N
times, we're doing a sink operation, and
the size of the heap is at most lg N so
it's N lg N. The construction, actually,
it turns out although it's a little more
complicated to prove, that it always uses
just a linear number of comparison
exchanges. And that's an interesting
result in itself. You can build a heap
from N values in linear time. And then,
and then lg N more time. You can sort from
that heap and that's significance be,
significant because it's the first sorting
algorithm that we've seen that is both in
place. And manages to get the sorting job
done with guaranteed analogs and compares.
Mergesort doesn't do that. It takes linear
extra space. Quicksort doesn't do that. It
takes quadratic time in a worse case even
though we make that unlikely by random
shuffling. It still takes quadratic time
in the worse case but Heapsort does both.
Now there is more complicated versions of
Mergesort and Quicksort that can do this
in theory but Heapsort is pretty simple
algorithm that gets both done, so in a job
interview somebody asks you what's an
in-place sorting algorithm that's
guaranteed N lg n? Your answer's going to
be Heapsort. Now in practice Heapsort is
actually not used that much for a couple
of reasons. And they might ask you these
on your job interview too. First thing is
the inner loop is longer than Quicksorts.
Like Mergesort there is more things to do
in the inner loop. There is that compare
are the two children bigger, then compare.
So there are two compares that get done at
N lg N times. And then there is some that
array index arithmetic. The other thing
that is probably more significant on
modern machines is. That the references to
memory are all over the place when it's a
huge array, so it's not a good algorithm
for a situation where there's caching
which is almost everywhere nowadays. It
doesn't have a local reference, like
Quicksort does. It's always refers to
something that's nearby something else
that I just referred to. So if a big block
of things comes into memory, there's no
more extra costs, whereas Heapsort is
going to look far away from the current
place as it goes down the tree and that
makes it slower in a lot of situations.
And on the other thing is it's not stable,
sometimes people choose to use Mergesort
in practice because of the stability but
Heapsort isnot stable for the usual reason
that it does long distance exchanges that
might bring items that have equal keys
back out of order. So that, that, that's
our full summary of sorting algorithms to
and completes our treatment of sorting
algorithms with Heapsort. And this is just
adding the Heapsort line to the table.
It's in place we don't use any auxiliary
array it's not stable, but its worst-case
guaranteed time is proportional to N lg N
as well as the average and, and the best
this is not a result but that's also the
case so it's N lg N guarantee N place, but
it's not stable, and we still have the
hope that someday somebody will develop a
simple in-place stable worst case N lg N
algorithm but we're not quite there yet.
And that completes our treatment of
sorting algorithms with the Heapsort
algorithm.