Welcome back. Today, we're going to look
at Priority Queues which is a variant of
sorting that generalizes the idea to
provide more flexible data structure that
we can use for all sorts of applications.
To get started, we'll look at the API and
some elementary implementations. So at a
week or so ago, we looked at collections
in Java and the idea of elementary data
structures where we insert and delete
items. And then, the data structures
differ on the basis of which item we choose
to delete. We looked to the push down
stack where we removed the item that was
most recently added, And the queue where we
remove the item that was least recently
added. And then, we talked about
randomized queue or bag where we might
remove a random or an arbitrary item.
Today, what we're going to talk about is
called the priority queue and for that, we
insert items, but when it's time to
remove, we consider the items to have a
total order and we want to remove the
largest or the smallest item. So this
little example if we insert P, Q, and E
then when we do remove max, we want to get
the Q out and for later, we insert X, A,
and M and then we removed max. The
largest one in there is X. We'll insert P,
L, and E and then, after a while, we
remove max P. So, that's our basic setup.
That's our definition of what a priority
queue is. So, the API will look very
similar to our stack or queue API with a
difference that we want to have generic
items that are comparable. So the Java
language for that is in the class header.
We say that our generic type Key extends
Comparable of Key. And that just means
that our keys must be Comparable and we
must have a compareTo() method that will
compare it to another key. Otherwise we
have a constructor and actually for some
applications, it's convenient to have a
constructor that takes an array of keys as
argument. Then, an insert() that puts
something in like push in a stack or
enqueue in a queue. Then delete the
maximum. I referred to delete the minimum
just to avoid confusion, we have the
implementation separate implementation
usually MinPQ, where we delete the
minimum. Then test isEmpty() and we also
sometimes have extra method that just
gives us the value of the largest key and
also size which is useful sometimes in
collections. You might also want it to be
iterable but we'll skip that for now.
There are lots and lots of applications of
priority queues. Even though it emerged as
a data structure relatively late in the
game now that we see that there are many
algorithms that are much easier to
implement when we think about the priority
key abstraction. We have data that we are
processing we can't process it all at once.
We have to save it some of way. And then,
what the priority queue tells us is -
let's organize it in some ways that we are
always taking the best one to process
next. And it turns out to be very close to
a generic algorithmic design technique
that we will be looking at in many, many
different applications. Today, we're going
to talk about event-driven simulation
which is an interesting idea that is based
on priority queues but it's also used in
numerical computation and we'll see in
algorithms for data compression and graph
searching that it's useful. And in many
other applications in Computer Science and
in scientific computing. It generalizes the
stack and the queue and gives us a data
structure that we can use to effectively
design algorithm of all sorts. So here's
just a particular client that will help
explain the idea. So our, our challenge is
let's say this is on the web we have
billions of transactions, you know, and they
are streaming through our data warehouse
or processor in some way. And just a very,
very huge number of transactions. In fact,
we couldn't possibly hope to even store
them all. There's trillions of them there
coming through as fast as possible. But
we're interested in the biggest ones and
so maybe it's the biggest amount of
dollars, or the biggest cost, or whatever
it might happen to be. And so we can pick
some numbers that we can store. I would
like to, to store the, the thousand
biggest ones. So, you can imagine a credit
card company looking for fraud - it's going
to care about keeping track of the largest
transactions. So, maybe we can store
millions or thousands of them. So that's
our parameter M - that's the number we can
afford to store but the total number of
items we couldn't possibly afford to store
them. So and this is just some test data
where we've got all, all these
transactions and so we are going to be
able to take in data like this and again
an unbounded stream of data. But let's
say, we want to keep track of the top five
[cough] values using the third column as
the value. So we're going to look at a
client program called TopM that takes the
command-line argument, how many and
this case, it's going to say five and then
it's going to take from standard input the
transactions and it will print out the top
five. So, that's a canonical example of a,
a priority queue client that we need to
design a program that can do that. So,
with the priority queue abstraction that's
not too difficult to do. So we are going to
use a min-oriented priority queue so
that's going to keep, it'll [cough] it'll
be one where we can delete the minimum
and, and it'll be generic so we'll have a
transaction type that holds this
information including natural ordering
where it's ordered by dollars that last
column. So, we'll build a new priority
queue, min priority queue or we'll have
the capability to delete the minimum. And
then we read from standard input. We read
the line, build the transaction from the
information on that line. And that will
fill in the fields and then, we put that
transaction on the priority queue. Now, if
the priority queue has more than M items
because we inserted that one, then we want
to delete the smallest one there and that
way, we're keeping track of the largest M.
Whenever we get a new one, then we
throw away the smallest one that's there.
So, even with this huge stream of items
coming through, we're only keeping track
of the M largest items and that's a fine
canonical client for priority queue. Now
how we are going implement or solve this
problem or you can think of lots of ways
to go ahead and solve this problem of
finding the largest M items in the stream
of N items. So, for example, you could
sort them. And then just look at the M at
the end but by sending up the problem, I
already kind of ruled that one out because
we don't have the space to sort them all,
to store them all. So sorting is out of
the question. We'll look at couple of
elementary priority queue implementations
that are straightforward. You know, keep
the items like we would in the stack and
then when we need to find the smallest or
the largest look at, look at them all. But
that's going to be too slow. M is large
and N is huge, and MN is going to be too
slow. What would what we we'll look at is
very simple and practical implementation
using a data structure called the binary
heap that gets the job done in time
proportional to N log M and only M space.
And that's pretty close to the best that
we could do in theory and is very
important and useful, practical
implementation and data structure.
Alright. So here's just an overview of two
elementary implementations for priority
queues using the example operations that I
gave before. So you can imagine keeping
the item, say, in a linked list or in
a doubling array and just keeping just an
order just as we would in the, in the
stack just keeping in the way that they
come in. And we'll put a new item at the
end of the array and remove it from the
end of the array. Or you could do it in a linked
list, and then when it's time to find the,
remove the maximum, you have to scan
through everything to find the maximum.
So, so, that's a one way you could
implement this with, with a linked list or
with the resizing array. Or you might to
say well let's try to keep things in
order. And then that might involve some
work with the, it's like insertion sort,
you find a place to put the new item and
then put it in the right place. And again,
you could do this with a linked list or with
the resizing array but then, with array,
you'd have to move all the larger ones over
one position to fit the new item in. When
we insert E and that's supposed to keep
them in order, we have to move over L, M,
P, and P to get the E and then so forth.
But the advantage of that might be that
removing the maximum is easy. We just take
away the one at the end. To remove the
Q - we know it's at the end to remove
the max. At this point, that's X - it's
right at the end, and P is right at the end.
So you can imagine the implementations of
priority queues using these two basic
strategies. Not much code involved. This
is a an ordered array implementation of
priority queues and it's quite straight
forward. We didn't put in the this is the
cheat version where we require the client
to provide a capacity but we could easily
change this to a resizing array. So
insert() just puts it at the end, and since
its unordered delete maximum has to go
through the entire array to try to find
the maximum when it refines it and the
changes that we're the one at the end and
then removes it the same way that we do
within the stack. It'll use less and
exchange just like we would in sorting
methods. So that's a fine implementation if
the priority queue was going to be tiny
all the time. So if you, without even
implementing it, you can understand this
table that if we use an unordered array
implementation we can get insertion done
in constant time but we have
to look at everything to delete the
maximum or even find the maximum. If we
keep it in order, we can find the maximum
or delete it at constant time but it takes us
linear time to insert. And since as
with stack and queue operations, these
insert and deletes might be intermixed in
arbitrary ways and there might be huge
numbers of them either one of these is
very attractive because they're going to
take N times the number of operations.
Whereas what we can hope for and what we
actually will achieve is to get log N time
for all operations, time proportion to log N
for all operations. With the clever data
structure and interesting implementation
we can actually achieve that goal. That's
the basic API and some elementary
implementations for priority queues.