Now, look at an interesting application of
priority queues that is actually
representative of whole family of a
critically important applications in
applications of computing. It's called
event driven simulation. And the idea is
we want to study some property of the
natural world by simulating it. And that's
something that's very, very common in, in
scientific inquiry nowadays. And this is a
very natural idea. And actually, the idea
goes back to Einstein. So, we want to
simulate the motion of N moving particles
that might collide with the priority.
This, this kind of stimulation is enabled
by priority queues. And without something
like priority queues, you couldn't do this
for a large number of particles because it
would require quadratic time and simply
can't be afforded for a huge number of
particles. So, and let's take a look at
how we can possibly make this happen. So
we use a simple scientific model called
the hard disc model. And then, this is
just for simplicity to get this done and
just part of a lecture. Clearly, these
things can be extended in many ways. So,
we're going to have moving particles that
either collide with each other and with
the walls. And each particle is a disc
that's got known position, velocity, mass,
and radius. And there's no other forces
involved. It gets more complicated if
there's more forces, like gravity
involved. And this point by itself is very
significant. As I mentioned, it goes back
to the study of physics with [cough] the
trying to understand the pressure and
temperature in Einstein's famous
experiment on a pollen grain showing that
their motion was brownian and random. So
whether it's individual atoms and
molecules or some bigger kinds of
particles. It's a complex dynamic
situation that is better understood
through computer simulation. And nowadays
that means priority queues. [cough] So, as
a wa rm-up, here's code to implement
bouncing balls without the collisions. And
this is an elementary programing exercise
that is the, the code at the left has the
effects shown at the right. So, we have a
data type called ball that represents just
one of the particles and has instance
variables that has the position and the
velocity. So, that's why we make a bunch
of them and then we have a, a while loop
which is just every 50 milliseconds clear
the, the whole drawing and then move the
balls a little bit and then draw them in
their current position. And then the only
to move [cough] operation does is to
update the position of the ball by the
velocity, which is just another number and
then it does the bouncing off the walls.
If it happens to hit the left of the wall
then you reflect the x-coordinate in the
right wall, you reflect the x-coordinate
bottom to top, you do the same for the
y-coordinate. So, this the is an easy
programming exercise given the right
display primitives. And it's a good
exercise in object-oriented programming
showing how just one implementation then
we can use that same implementation to
simulate a number of instances. So, that's
our starting point in terms of the code.
So this is the implementation of the ball
class. So, it's got position and velocity
as I mentioned, and every ball has a, a
radius. And then there is a constructor
and maybe we have a constructor that takes
arguments that would initialize the
position and the velocity or maybe
initialize them to a random position if
there's no arguments. And then, here's the
move method. And the move method again,
most of the times, just takes the x and y
coordinates and adds the current velocity
times the speed constant. The dt speed,
speed variable that's given as argument
dt. And then these tests are for whether
it hits the walls in which case, you have
to flip the x or y velocity. And then
draw, it's just using standard draw. Just
draw the ball. So, that's all the code for
doing the bouncing ball simulation. Now,
what's missing in this is what happens
when the balls collide with each other.
And to cope with that we need to do both.
A little bit of high school Physics and a
little bit of basic Computer Science. The
Physics problem is exactly what happens
when two balls hit and they bounce off
each other according to some
well-understood physical process, and
that's the high school Physics. And the CS
problem is how and when to we exactly do
these computations for each of the balls.
And how can we do it efficiently that is
in, in log N time versus quadratic time.
Because if we have a computational process
that takes quadratic time, then it's not
going to scale, we're not going to be able
to do large number of particles.
Simulations in the real world, usually, we
wind up doing huge amounts of data and we
cannot have a quadratic algorithm. This is
just first indication of that of why if
you want to do this simulation, you better
know about some data structure like
priority queues. If you try to do it
without it, you're not going to be
successful. Alright, so, let's take a look
at what happens. So there's a number of
things that you might consider trying. So,
one idea is the so-called time driven
simulation. And we just say, we're going
to update everything every dt seconds.
Then we go ahead and then we could check
if there's a collision, if the two balls,
pieces of the two balls are occupying the
same space. And if there is, then we could
roll back time just a little bit and I'll
try to figure out exactly, the moment of
which they collided and then figure out
how the position and velocity should
change accordingly and then continue the
simulation. But this has a huge problem.
The first one is that you have t o check
all pairs of balls for overlap so that's
quadratic, so it's going to be really,
really lot of overall texture you're not
going to be able to do it for a huge, huge
value of N. But the other thing is even if
N is small if you do a very small dt, then
you're just doing this calculation over
and over again and there's just too much
computation moving the balls little bit at
a time. On the other hand, if you try to
improve things by making dt too large you
might completely miss a collision as shown
in the example at right. So figuring out
the value of dt that would really work is
a huge problem for the time driven
simulation. Instead, what we want to do is
called an event driven simulation. And
this is a very general concept that's
useful in all kinds of context. And we are
going to change things when something
happens. So, since the only thing that
matters is collisions, we are going to
figure the particles move in a straight
line, between collisions. And what we are
going to do is focus only on the times
when the collisions are going to occur.
And the way we are going to that, is to
maintain a priority queue and that
priority queue is going to have all the
possible collisions that could happen in
the future and they're going to be
prioritized by time. And when we remove
the minimum element from the priority
queue, that's the next collision that we
have to deal with. And so we have two
phases, we have prediction and resolution.
So, that's sometime t, we can take two
particles. We know their position and
velocities shown at the bottom here and we
can predict exactly the moment, which
they'll collide assuming that something
else doesn't happen to them in between and
then so they will put that predicted
collision time on the priority queue and
later on, when that time comes to pass we
will be right at moment when they collide
and we can figure out what to do. Now,
there is a possibly that something else
happened to t hem in between and we'll
talk about that change, too. So, we have
to do collision prediction, which is given
position, velocity, and radius when's it
going to hit with another particle or, or
the wall. And then there's resolution
which is to figure out how to change the
velocities of the particles according to
physical laws. Now this part I'm not going
to talk about in that much detail right
now because it's high school Physics. And
so, I think most students have had high
school Physics and will be able to do, do
this Math or at least be convinced that
the code that does this Math is correct.
So, if you know that you have a particle
that's at a certain position or x or y and
has got a certain velocity, the x in the
x-direction and y in the y-direction, then
you can from the distance to the pro,
vertical wall you can figure out how many
seconds this is going to take until it
hits it. It's basically that distance
divided by the by the velocity. And so
that's the prediction. And then, the
resolution. When it hits the wall is, is
just going to change the velocity. So
that's in, you know what the position is.
So that's just an example of collision, of
collision prediction, when's it going to
hit the wall and resolution what do you do
when it gets to the wall. When you have
two particles there's definitely more
math. And again, this is high school
Physics. And we're not going to test on it
or even go through the details. But it's
just a little bit of arithmetic with the
velocities and positions to deal with what
happens when, when how to predict when a
given particle is going to collide with
another given particle knowing their
velocity and position. So, you have to
take both velocities and divide their
distance by those and, and so forth. So
there's simple formulas to tell us what to
do and we can also figure out the formulas
for what we do o nce they do collide. And
again nobody's claiming that this is easy
but this is the Physics part and it's
worked out and it comes from Newton's
Second Law. And, and, anybody taking high
school Physics will, be able to deal with
these formulas and the rest of this may
have to go to a reference book to get up
to speed on them. [cough] but once it's
reduced to code we can be, it might have
some trouble debugging at first but at
least we can be convinced that it works.
But now, let's look at the computer
science code. So, this is just extending
our ball data type that we use for the
bouncing balls that didn't collide to take
in, into account these extra things. So,
ours will have mass, so there will be some
big heavy ones that make things more
interesting. And there's also a variable
called count, which is the number of
collisions of particles have been involved
in. And that's useful for a couple of
purposes. So, we're going to need a bunch
of procedures which do the prediction and
the collision resolution. I want, what's
the, given a particle what's the time till
we hit that particle? What's the time till
we hit vertical horizontal wall? And the
same thing is if we're at the point where
we're hitting a particle, what would we
do, the, the same way with the vertical
and horizontal wall. So, that's the
skeleton. We need those procedures that
implement those Physics rules for every
particle. And, and this is what they look
like and again this is high school Physics
so we're not going to do it in detail
other than to point out it's really not a
huge amount of code. Lots of the xs and
the ys and the vs but really not a huge
amount of code. And the other point is
we're going to return infinity if there's
no collision at all so that it's going to
keep, keep that on the priority queue,
that ran on the priority queue forever.
Okay, so that's the procedures that we
need and then they're similar ones for the
horizontal and vertical walls. So now,
let's look at the main loop for the event
driven simulation. So, the first thing is
we're going to for every particle we're
going to compute the next time that it
might hit every horizontal and vertical
wall. Well, actually if it's going away
from a wall, it's not going to hit it so
that would be infinity. But if it's going
towards a wall, then we'll compute the
time. And then that's a time in the future
and we'll put that event on the priority
queue with that time as the key. And then,
we'll do the same thing for all pairs of
particles. So, we do have a quadratic
initialization phase that we perform just
once to get the priority queue filled up.
Now, all collisions are, might not happen
so we might have two particles that are on
a collision course that and we're going to
predict that point for both of those
particles, you know, even right at the
beginning. But it might be the case that
there's a third particle that knocks one
of those out before that thing happens and
that event would be invalidated. So, the
simulation has to be careful to take that
into account. But that's not difficult to
do. So, here's what the main loop is. So,
we're going to take the next event from
the priority queue. That's the next
collision that's going to happen from all
our calculations. There's one collision
that's going to happen next. Then, we test
whether that event has been invalidated.
And we do that by using that count field
in the particle. So, then that tells us
what time it's going to be next. So, then
we have to go through all the particles
and change their positions on a straight
line trajectory, where would they'll be
after that much time? Then we have to take
the two particles that collide and change
their velocity. They bounce off one
another. Now those two particles'
velocities have changed , essentially that
invalidates the future collisions
involving those. And then we, what we have
to do is for those two particles is go
through and predict the future collisions
with any walls and collisions with any
other particles. And put all those new
events on to the priority queue. But
that's it. You got two particles, change
your velocities figure out the future
collision of those particles with the wall
and update the priority queue and then the
main loop is take the next thing off the
priority queue and keep going. That's the
code that we'll look at next. So we have
a, a, a bunch of conventions just to
reduce the code. And if we this the, the
thing called event which involves it says
between two particles, something is going
to happen at a certain time and we're
going to adopt the conventions that, if,
neither particle is null then we're
talking about two particles. If one of the
particles is null then we're talking about
a wall, a vertical or horizontal wall. And
if both particles are null we're saying we
just want to redraw things. That's a bit
of a hack, but it cuts down on a lot of
code. Our compared to is by time. And then
again, we need an, is valid to check about
intervening collision. And then here's the
skeleton of what's going to happen with
the collision system which is the key
thing is this prediction method that takes
a particle as argument, and adds to the
priority queue, all the possible
collisions involving this particle. So,
it's going to go through every particle
and call the time to hit method for that
particle. And then, it'll put an event on
the priority queue for that time, this
particle with that particle. And then,
it'll also put an event for the vertical
wall and the horizontal wall, again, using
this null convention to say that the event
second argument null is vertical. First
argument null is horizontal. So that's a
key method t hat gets used in the
simulation for each of the two particles
that are going to collide. So, now we can
look finally at the main event driven
simulation loop. So there's build a
priority queue. There's do this prediction
for every one of the particles. And then,
also we're going to put as the first thing
that happened always a, an event that says
redraw everything. So that's just a, a way
of make suring that the simulation keeps
proceeding. It's an easy way to get things
drawn. Okay. So, now the main loop is
while the priority queue is not empty
we're going to pull off an event. We're
going to test whether it's valid. And
that's just checker if anything happened
with those two particles. We're going to
pull off the two particles and then we're
going to all, we're going to move all
particles by the amount of time that has
elapsed since the last event. And then,
we're going to test which of the four
types of events that it is. It's either
redraw, bounce, B of A or, or bounce off a
vertical wall or, or a horizontal wall.
And then we'll go ahead and do the
predictions of each of those particles, A
and B, against all other particles. That's
the pretty much all the code for the
simulation. So this is data driven code.
So, one thing we can do is just run it for
a 100 balls in random position at random
velocity. But what's nice about data
driven code is now that the code's working
and again we, we're not saying that this
is a trivial code to write but it's
definitely manageable. And it's enabled by
priority queues. Without priority queues,
it would be quite a bit more complicated
to figure out how to do this. And also, it
wouldn't be reasonably efficient at all
for large data sets. So, that's a, a
simple simulation to just generate random
positions. People might be interested in
this one. Now this isn't exactly precisely
wh at would happen in the real world
mainly because we didn't put in the
simulation what happens when three
particles are touching or there's two
touching in another one hits them. And
also nobody racks up a, a set of billiard
balls such that all fifteen are touching
in all places. So life can be complicating
when you try to simulate the natural
world. This is a little bit about
Einstein's experiment. If you got one big
particle like a pollen grain and lots of
little particles like atoms molecules and
bouncing against it the big one is going
to move about randomly. And then this is
another famous physics experiment showing
diffusion. And there's many other things
that you can do with this basic collision
system. If you have huge numbers of
particles and you measure the number that
hit the size and the frequency with which
they hit they sides you can do experiments
relating temperature and pressure and many
other things or do three-dimensional
versions. Again simulation of the natural
world is an increasingly important
application of computing and need
efficient data structures like priority
queues to get it done.