Now, we're going to take a look at ordered
symbol table operations using the binary
search tree data structure as the
underlying implementation. Well, each one
of these operations are fairly straight
forward but just to check our ability to
manipulate this data structure, we'll take
a look at each. Suppose, we wanted to find
the minimum key in a binary search tree,
or the maximum key. Well, just looking at
one example you can see almost immediately
what to do to find the minimum, we move
left from the root until we find a null
key, that's where the smallest key in the
data structure is. To find the maximum, we
move right from the root, until we find a
null key. What about floor and ceiling?
Well, those are a little bit more
complicated and we'll have to, not quite
the same as in the ordered array for the
binary search so we have to do a little
bit more work for that. So just for
example, let's take a look at the problem
of computing the floor. So, what we want
to find is so say, we're seeking the floor
of G. So, that's the largest key in the
data structure that is less than G. In
this case, the answer is E. So let's just
take a look at what we have to do in the
tree, the path we have to take in the tree
to figure that out. Well so, we are
looking for the largest key that's less
than G. And have S well, that key is
definitely going to be in the left
subtree. Its not going to be bigger than S
because S is bigger than G so we go to the
left. So now, we are sitting at E. And so
what's the largest key that's less than G
in this, in this tree here. Well, it might
be E but there's no way it's to the left
of E because those keys are all smaller
than E and therefore smaller than G. So, E
is a key candidate. But it might also be
in the right so we move to the right in
this case. Alright [cough]. So that's
[cough] if K is equal to the key at the
root, the floor of K is K. If K is less
than the key, it roots i n the left
subtree. That's the one we just did. If
it's greater than the key at the root. The
floor of K is in the right subtree, if
there is any key smaller than K in the
right subtree. So, in this case, there's
no key smaller than G in the right
subtree. So therefore, the answer is E.
So, our code has to check for these three
cases. And here's the code that does it.
It's not that much code. It's just
complicated code to understand. So if we
find our key, that's the floor. If we're
going to the left we find the floor, the
one on the left. And in on the right we
have to do a, a little bit of tricky code
to make sure that we return the floor on
the right subtree, if there's some tree
there. If there's, if there's no node
there then, then, then we, we return the
root itself. So, that's a, a
implementation that, that code is
definitely tricky and a similar code for
ceiling. So now, what about operations
like rank and select? How many keys are
there less than a given key? And, give us
the seventh largest key to facilitate
implementing those operations and also
size all we do is keep an extra field in
each node, which is the number of the
nodes in the subtree rooted at that node.
So, this tree has got eight nodes in it.
This subtree has six nodes in it and so
forth. And those counts are going to not
only enable us to immediately implement
the size function, just return the count
at the root but also, they'll give us good
implementations of rank and select. So,
let's look at those now. So, we add
account field to every node and then to
implement the size function well, if it's
null, we return zero. So a client might
call us for a null tree or [cough] or an
empty tree. Otherwise we return, x.count,
which is the number of nodes in that, in
that subtree by definition. The way we
maintain, there's a number of ways we can
maintain the thing but the one that we'll
adopt un iformly because it adapts to more
complicated situations is just before
we're done with the put operation we'll
say, okay we've done all our work and
before we return the pointer to the given
subtree we're going to take the size of
what's on the left and the size of what's
on the right and add one for us and that's
going to be our count. So, whether or not
there was a new node added we don't have
to test for that this recursively takes
care of the problem of maintaining the
size in every node when there's a new node
inserted. And, it also handles more
general situations, as we'll see later on.
So, that's how to maintain size. So now,
how do we implement rank? Well, it's a
little like floor. It's an easy recursive
algorithm, but there are three cases. So
let's look at the, at the three cases. So,
we want to know the number of keys less
than K. So [cough] we're going to have a
recursive algorithm for our given key. So,
let's, one of the easy ones is, if our key
is equal to the, if were [cough] to the,
the key at the current node then the
number of keys less than our key is the
size of the left subtree of that node. So,
if we're looking for the rank of E say,
how many keys are there less than E
there's exactly two, that's by definition
in the data structure that's the number of
keys that are less than E. So, that's that
one for rank. What about the [cough]
starting at the root if we have the case
where E is less than S. So, the rank of E
in this whole tree is the same as the rank
of E in the left subtree. So, there's that
case and then if we're going to the right,
then we have to add one for the root and
one for the left subtree of the root and
then find the rank of us on the right. So,
that's an easy recursive algorithm for
finding out the rank. And it's definitely
an instructive exercise to check that you
believe that, that method works. The other
thing we h ave to do is iteration. And
iteration is a fundamental operation on
tree structure. And it's based on so
called in-order traversal. And that's also
a simple recursive algorithm. Traverse the
left subtree enqueue the key, traverse the
right subtree. So, to iterate we're going
to maintain a queue of keys. And then,
we're going to call this recursive
in-order [cough] method. And that method
is going to add all the keys in the tree
to the queue. And then we'll just return
that queue. And that's, a queue is an
iterable data structure, and the client
can iterate that. And, in order, it's just
a simple recursive method. Put everybody
to the left on the queue then put the root
on the queue, then put everybody to the
right on the queue. And to believe this
method, you just have to think recursively
and prove by induction that this in order
method puts all the keys in the data
structure on the queue in their natural
order. First, it puts all the ones to the
left on the queue. If that, that happens
in their natural order, then the next
thing that has to appear is the key at the
root. And then if the ones on the right go
in their natural order, and then, by
induction, they're all in their natural
order. That's a very simple implementation
of an iterator for these symbol table with
comparable keys. So we have to again prove
that property by induction. And that's
easy to do. The diagram at the right gives
another simple way to look at it
pictorially. All the keys that are smaller
on the left we are going to put them out,
and then we put the key at the root and
then we put all the keys on the right out
in order. And then that key is going to
have all those keys in order by induction.
So, here's the operation summary for
ordered symbol table. And the quick
summary is that every one of those
operations, while ordered iteration is
optimal, it just gets them in linear time.
And all the res t of'em take time
proportional to the height of the tree.
Now, if the, the keys are inserted in
random order, we know that height by
analysis, is going to be proportional to
log N. Or if it's some application where
the order of insertion of the keys is well
modeled by random order and that's not
unusual at all. A binary search tree is a
simple and extremely effective data
structure that can support all of these
operations in a quickly, much better than
binary search in an ordered array which is
not dynamic and slow for insertion. So,
that's a look at binary search tree
implementations of ordered operations when
keys are comparable.