Welcome back. In this and the next few
lectures, we're going to look at symbol
tables. A fundamental and extremely
important data type that have led to all
kinds of fascinating implementations and
we're going to see at several of them in
this course. To begin, we'll take a look
at the API and some elementary
implementations and various operations
that people want to perform on Symbol
Tables. Start with the API. The idea
behind symbol tables is to implement the
following abstraction. We are going to
have keys, like our keys in priority
queues but, the whole ideas that we are
going want to associate, values with each
key. So two operations that we're going to
perform in symbol tables is the insert
operation where we're really putting a
value, a key value pair into the symbol
table, a value with a specified key, and
then given a key we want to search for a
corresponding value. Those are the two
basic operations. Now the keys and the
values can interchange roles. And that's,
that's why we, have the abstraction to
separate them. So for example, a domain
name server might have a look up where
you've got a table that's got an IP
address, and a URL associated with that IP
address. And different clients might want
to use this data in different ways. One
might want to use the URL as key. Given
the URL, give us the corresponding IP. The
address. Another client, might want to use
the IP address as key, have an IP address,
give me the corresponding client. So those
are just a couple of examples. This is a
very fundamental and basic abstraction. In
the list of applications is huge, in fact
almost any computer application system is
going to have symbol table or multiple
symbol tables at its core, all the way
down to the basic memory system of the
computer or the networking system that
your computer accessed information depends
on. You can think of it intuitively, as,
like a dictionary. Well, there used to be
books, and people would open up those
books to look for a word, to find the
definition. Nowadays, you're more likely,
to do that online. Or, when you're trying
to find a song to download, you provide
the name of the song. And then a value
will tell you what computer to go to, to
get that or in commercial computing, the
key might be an account number, and the
value might be the transaction details,
for that account. Web search is something,
we all do multiple times every day. And
the key is a keyword, or a list of
keywords. And the value is a list of
places where that keyword is found. And
there's many, many other applications,
including scientific applications where
say in genomics people use simple tables
to keep track of finding markers in the
genome and again many other applications.
So, its a very fundamental concept and we
will look at plenty of applications. But
first we want to look at some algorithms
so the way that it's convenient to set up
a symbol table is to implement the
so-called associative array abstraction.
And the idea behind that is to think about
just associating one value with each key.
And well it's like in Java array of
integers say. We're only, our keys in that
case are indices that are restricted
between, to be between zero and the array
size. But we're only associating one value
with each index. We think of storing the
value in the array position given by that
index. And a good way to think of a symbol
table is as shown in the right here. When
we put a key value pair onto the symbol
table. Think of that as using the key to
index an array, and storing the value
there. Now this, isn't legal in Java if
key is not an int. And, and we're going to
do this generic. It can be any type of
data. But, it's a good way to think about
it. And then, to retrieve it, you just
give that same key, and it'll return the
value. So that's our, two primary
operations. Put a key value pair into the
table. So that is associate the value with
key, and then get the value paired with
the key. Now th ere's particular rules for
Null that I'll talk about in a second. And
then to properly maintain the symbol table
in a dynamic situation in many clients you
want to support and delete operation and
contains is, is simpler operation than
depth. It's convenient for many clients
where it just tells us whether there's
some value paired with that key in the
table isn't in size. And then another
thing that you might want to do is iterate
through all the keys in, in the table. So
those are the basic operations that we're
going to want to implement to get the
associative array abstraction. And then
there's many, many possibilities for
clients and we'll look at some later on.
Now there is a couple of conventions
around null. And these are not critical,
but they make it bit more convenient for
several implementations. So we are not
going to allow null values, we cannot
associate null with any key. And then we
are going to adopt the convention that the
get method returns null, if the key is not
present in the table. And also the
associative array abstraction is the put
method, well, overwrite an old value with
a new value. So these are our
consequences. So, it's, the contains
implementation is the same for all our,
symbol typal implementations. If get
returns, a non null value, then there's a
value corresponding to that key in the
table if it returns null. It's not get
returns null keys not present. And the
other thing that we could do is we can use
null in some situations or temporary
situations to implement a lazy version of
the delete operation. We can associate the
key with null internally and then a client
won't know the difference whether that's
in there or not. And some algorithms take
advantage of the ability to use null in
this way. These are just conventions and
somewhat details but it's important to
point them out at front. So now, we're
going to want the value to be any generic
type at all, but the key type we have to
make some natural assumptions about them.
And actually there's different assumptions
that we make in our implementations
depending on the application. Though one
of the most useful ones is to have
comparable keys. Just as in sorting
algorithms we'll assume that the keys have
values that have come from a total order.
And we can use compare to, to compare
whether one key is less than, than other
or not. This is for two reasons. One is we
can get more efficient app implementations
if we can use the ordering of the keys to
help us find our way around the data
structure. And the other reason is that we
can support a broader set of simple table
operations that are very convenient for
many clients. And it's very typical for
keys to come from an ordered set. Now, for
example in the dictionary application or
if keys are stings or numbers. Or account
numbers or many other situations. So if
they're going to be comparable we might as
well take advantage of it. Both to get
more efficient algorithms and to be able
to take advantage of a broader set of
operations. Now in other situations, maybe
they're not comparable. And all we're
allowed to use is to, use the equals
operation. That is everything every type
of data in Java has to support and equals
operation that reads out to test whether
they're equal. And there's another family
of methods where there's no ordering. Then
there is a special method called hash code
that helps us [cough] inject randomness
into the process and that's built into
Java and also some classic algorithms
depend on that. We're going to start out
with the comparable mostly. And again, as
with priority queues, the best practice is
to use immutable types, and experienced
programmers know this and it's not
difficult to arrange for the natural types
of data that people are going to use for
simple table keys. Unreasonable to expect
the implementation to work well if the
client can change the values of keys that
are in the table. If you want that, you
have to provide that as a specific
operation. In the case of symbol tables ,
we are not going to do that. You have to
remove it and put it back in. Alright, so
there's equalities. Now, equality again
we're getting into programming language
issue but it's still it's important to be
explicit about what's going on with,
equality. How do we test if two objects
are equal? So, the job has got
requirements as for compared to in, here's
the basic requirements about equals. There
is a method that all Java for equals, but
the default implementation is simply to
test whether the references are equal. Are
those precisely the same objects or not.
Usually in applications when we want to
have something more general than that and
have a concept of a value or like a key in
our case. And then we want to know if two
references refer to objects that have the
same value and we want to call that equal,
that's what equals is about. So anyway
we're required to make sure that X is
always equal to X and that, X = Y is the
same Y = X, and if X = Y, Y = Z, then X =
Z. So that means that mathematical terms
equals is called an equivalence relation.
And also no, no object is equal to null.
So those are absolute requirements for
Java. And again, the default
implementation is to check whether they
refer to the same object. And that's
rarely what we want. Java systems programs
maybe want that. But client programs
usually have customized implementations
that are based on comparing some sort of
value and the standard built-in types of
the Java language are going to have those
customized implementations and we can rely
on them doing what we expect. If we're
going to implement our own types and then
use those types as keys and symbol tables
you have to exercise a little bit of care
and we'll talk about that briefly. Say we
have this simplified date implementation
we talked about before it's a mutable type
and every day it's got a month a day in a
year. It seems like it should be easy to
implement equals basically, we're just
going to check that all the significant
fields are the same. Two dates should be
equal if they have the same day, month,
and year. And if any one of those are not
the same value, then just return false. So
that seems as if it should work. But that
doesn't have all the characteristics that
we need in a job implementation. And so
all of this code in red shows a model for
what you might do if you're going to
implement your own type of data equals for
your own type of data. So we shouldn't use
it in connection with inheritance so we
don't use inheritance that much so I won't
talk about that The type of the argument
in the equals must be object, do you think
it should be date? And experts debate
about that, and people who are interested
can look on the web for that kind of date.
If it is the case that you happen to be
testing two objects that are the same
object for equality, you might as well,
optimize everything and just test that. If
Y is a reference that's pointing to the
same object as this object just returned
true because, if you're going to test the
values they're going to have the same
values anyway. And that's a good
optimization for lots of, situations. Why
go through all that risk to that code if
you know right away they're, equal.
There's this test for null, that has to be
there. And if not there can lead to
nefarious plugs and, and, unusual
problems. So on your equals test you'd
better, test that, the client didn't give
you null. They have to be in the same
class. And while there's a couple of
different ways to check about the same
class, and that's another religious
debate. That we'll ignore. We'll use, get
class and that's something that's got to
work or they'll get, they'll get an
exception in this later code. Because
since Y had to be an object, now we have
to, cast it to a date. And then it better
be the right class, or else it's not going
to have these fields, that, we can test
for. So, details but anyway, you can use
this code as a model to implement equals
for any data type that you might wind up
using as a simple table key. Okay so
that's a standard this is just in words
the standard recipe for user find, type
optimize for reference equality, check
against null. Make sure they're the same
type and do the casting, and then compare
all the similar, significant fields. It
could be that if one of the fields is an
object, then you use that object's equals,
which reapplies the world the rule
recursively. And then if you ever feel
that it's an array you can go ahead and
try applying it to each entry. And there's
implementations in Java. You don't want to
use A, A. = B. That checks if those arrays
are the same objects. And that's not what
you want you want to check that all the
values are the same. And if it's array of
objects you can see that testing for
equals can actually involve a lot a code
and a lot a cost. Alright so and certainly
you want to follow some of these best
practices. So fields that are most likely
to differ. Those are the ones you might
want to compare first. And your also going
to want to make compare to consistent with
equals. The rule generally if we're have a
comparable types we'll use to compare to.
If we don't have a comparable types then
we'll use equals. Okay, so now let's look
at a couple of test clients before we look
at any particular implementation. So this
is a test client so symbol tables are ST
is the type, symbol table, they're generic
on key and value. And so this, this
statement builds a new symbol table with
string keys and integer values that's
going to associate integers with strings.
And so what the test client is going do is
going to a just go in a loop as long as
standard n is not empty, and it's going to
read strings, read a string off standard
input, and then put it in the symbol table
associated with the value I where did it
appear in the value input. So this is an
index same client where we associate each
string with its position most recent
position in the input. And, notice it's an
associative array implementation so for
example, we have two Es and at the end E
is a associated value twelve. The place
where it most recently appeared. We could
also keep these things in a bag and do a
client that does all the positions that
appeared. This is a simple indexing client
that we use for our traces. [cough] For
analysis for bigger problems we'll use a
client called the frequency counter
client. And so that one is going to read a
sequence of strings from standard input
and print out the one that occurs with
highest frequency. So, so for this small
data from the beginning of Dickens' Tale
of two Cities if we run a frequency
count-, or the frequency counter client.
And this first argument is just ignore
words of fewer than this many letters.
It'll say that the most frequent word
where there's no word that appears more
frequently than it which appears ten
times. And we'll want this client to work
well for huge data sets so Liepzeig is a,
a data set from the web of about twenty
million words. About half a million
distinct ones and in that Corpus, the word
government appears about 25,000 times. So,
if you have a quadratic time algorithm for
implementing simple tables or linear time
for each operation. You're not going to be
able to run this client in a reasonable
amount of time for a big amount of data.
So that's the client that we're going to
use for analysis. Here's the code for that
frequency counter client. Again, it's
similar to the other one, we're creating a
simple table that associates strings with
integers. We take that command line
argument which is the minimum length that
we care about. We will read a new word.
We'll ignore the short strings. Just trap
out if the word length is too small. And
now the integer we are going to associate
with each word is the frequency of
occurrence of that word in a symbol table.
So if word is not in the symbol table,
we'll put it there with a frequency of
occurrence of one. That's the first time
we saw the word. If it is in the symbol
table, we will just over write. The old
value, which is ST get word, with the new
value, ST ge t word plus one. So increment
the frequency in the symbol table. So
that's, read, this loop reads in all the
data and associates each word with its
frequency of occurrence. And then we'll
have a client that uses the iterator,
going through all the keys in the symbol
table. It'll get the value associated with
each key. And if that's bigger than the
maximum found so far, we'll save that
away. And then print out the, the word
that occurs the, the most often along with
its frequency. So this is a useful and non
trivial client that's enable by symbol
table. And, but it won't work well unless
we have an efficient symbol table
operation. And we'll use this client to
compare different symbol table
implementations. So that's the symbol
table API. And next, we'll take a look at
implementations.