Welcome back. Next we're going to talk
about Binary Search Trees, a classic data
structures that'll enables us to provide
efficient implementation of symbol table
and out rhythms. [cough] Let's look at the
basic Binary Search Tree data structure
with Heaps we talk about implicit
representation of trees with an array. For
Binary Search Trees we're going to talk
about actually explicit tree data
structures. A binary search tree is a
binary tree in symmetric order. Let's look
at the meaning of those words. So, a
binary tree is an explicit data structure.
It's got what we call nodes which contain
information and every node's got two links
to Binary Trees that are disjoint from one
another, a left tree and right tree
associated with each node. Each node has a
left tree and a right tree. Links can be
null. Left tree can be null and right tree
can be null or both. We refer to every
node in the tree as the root of a sub-tree
and [cough] referred to, the nodes below.
Each node is its children so this is the
right child of the root. And that's a left
link, and so forth. So that's the
definition of a binary tree. A binary
search tree, each node has a key and every
nodes key is larger than all the keys in
its left subtree and smaller than all the
keys in its right subtree. This is a
different ordering than we have to heap if
we have a node larger than both its
children, this one, every node is between
the values, the value of every node is
between the values of the nodes in its two
subtrees. So the nodes to the left of e
are smaller and nodes to the right of e
are larger. [cough] now we're going to use
these to implement symbol tables and
there's values associated with each key
when appropriate, we'll write the values
in smaller numbers next to the keys. But
usually, we're just going to worry about
the keys and we'll keep the values, in the
nodes along with them [cough] so that's
binary search trees. A binary tree in
symmetric order that's the data structur e
that we're going to use to implement
symbol table operations. So how are we're
going to represent binary search trees in
Java? Well, we're going to extend our
implementations of linked list structures
to have two references instead of just
one. So first of all, is the, there's a
node at the root. So, a binary search tree
in Java is just going to be referenced to
a root node. And every node's got four
fields, a key and a value, and references
to the left subtree, that contains the
smaller keys, and the right subtree that
contains the larger keys. So, here's what
the, [cough] code is based on. The, inner
class that we used to implement nodes has,
one, two, three, four instance variables.
All of which are private as usual. A key
of type key, a value of type value and
then references to a left and a right
node. For convenience, we'll provide a
constructor that takes the key and value
as argument and fills in the key and value
instance variables then the left and right
links are initialized to null. And our
data structure then will be a root that
points to a node in the tree and then that
node will point to subtrees and that will
be the data structure that we use for
symbol tables. So here's the skeleton of
our symbol table implementation. It's for
comparable keys associated with values and
those are both generic types. The only
instance variable is a link to the root
node called root. The inner class node is
the code that was given on the previous
slide, and then we'll need implementations
of put and get, and we'll also look at an
implementation of delete, and an iterator
as well. So that's our skeleton
implementation, let's look at the keys. So
let's look at search first. So here's a
binary search tree let's do a demo of what
different searches will look like in this
tree. So there's a tree so S is at the
root everybody to the left of is less than
S over to the right is bigger. So this is
a dynamic data structure that kind of
follows the same rule as binary search. So
to look for a, to do a search for the key
H in this tree, we start at the root and
we compare our key against the key at the
root. And in this case, H is less so all
that says to us is that if H is in the
tree, it has to be to the left cuz
everybody to the right is greater than S.
So we move to the left and compare H
against the root of the left subtree. In
this case that's E. Now H is greater so
that says we should go right. Now we can
pair H against the root of the right
subtree of E, and that's R and it's less
so we have to go left cuz everybody to the
right of R is bigger and H is smaller. And
eventually if the key is in the tree,
we're going to hit it. In this case we, we
find H as the left sub tree of R in
[cough] that's a search hit and then for
the get operation, we can return the value
that's stored in that node along with the
key H. What about an unsuccessful search?
Well the same rules follow. If it's in the
tree, it's gotta be according to the left
or right, according to whether it's
smaller or larger than the key at the
route. In this case, if we're searching
for G, it's gotta go left, because it's
less than S. When we come against the E,
we gotta go right because it's bigger than
E against the R, we have to go left,
because it's less than R. We come against
the H, we have to go left. And then we
come off a null link, and all that says is
that there's no place in this tree where G
could be so G is not there. So that's a
search miss. And the get operation would
return null in that case. What about
insertion? Well, to insert a new key, all
we do is follow the same steps as we did
for search. That following off that null
link and again, we'll just, for G, travel
down the tree until we come to the, null
link. Really, what we're saying is when we
go to the left link of H, it says, if G is
in the tree, it has to be down this link.
Since it's not there to in sert G, all we
need to do is just put it there and that's
how we insert a new node into a binary
search tree. Alright, here's the code
corresponding to the process that we just
demo. And it's quite straight forward
simple code as simple as binary search
really. We start at the root then we set
variable x to be the root and that's going
to be the pointer to the current node as
we move down the tree. As long as our, our
current node x is not null what we'll want
to do is a comparison between the key at
node x and our search key. If our search
key is less, we go to the left. If it's
greater we go to the right. And if it's
equal we don't even have to test that,
that's why it's in grey. If it's not
greater or lesser it has to be equal, than
we return the value right at that node. If
we get to the bottom and our current node
is null and that's falling off the bottom
of the tree we return null and that's
equivalent to saying our buyer convention
that, that key is not in our data
structure, or not in our symbol table. So
that's very straightforward implementation
of the get operation for symbol tables
with a binary search tree representation.
Now, what's the cost? Well, we went down a
path in the tree so it's one plus the
depth of the node in the tree. [cough] So
what about search well search for put
there's two cases. If the if we're
supposed to associate a value with a key.
If the key's already in the tree then
we're just going to reset the value. If
they key's not in the tree then we add a
new node at the bottom. So now it's a
little bit tricky the way that we
implement it since we're using we use a
recursive implementation. And the reason
we do this is that it generalizes to give
us more efficient data structures later
on. So, what we'll do is use a recursive
implementation that as it moves down the
tree it'll return a link up higher in the
tree. And so when we insert a new node L
say in this tree we go down that path, we
create a new node and then return the link
to that node higher up. There's ways to
implement that don't involve this, but
its, the code is so simple and it extends
to more powerful data structures later on
that we'll introduce this right now and,
and you'll see how it works. So here's
the, this is very concise recursive code
but its tricky because of that last point
so its worth reading carefully. So, we're
going to use a recursive method put. That
put a associate a value with a key in the
tree. And that recursive [cough] method is
going to return a node. So the client
method put of course, just is supposed to
do the association so it has a void
return. But what we'll do is invoke a
recursive method starting at the root and
whatever link gets returned, we'll set
that to root. So right away, we can see,
let's suppose that we have an empty tree
where root is null. So then if we put with
null as the first argument, then null is
the first argument. What we do is we say
if, if the argument is null, return a
reference to a new node that associates
key with value and then that one has null
links. So in this case, that first call
will return a link and whatever link gets
returned, that will be set to root. So,
without any extra special code we insert a
node into an empty tree. And that works,
again, recursively say we have one node in
the tree, and we have a new key to
associate. And let's say that key is less
than the key at the root. So, so now we do
put in it's actually a link to that one
node that's got two null links. So it's
not null so we'll compare our key against
the key in that node. If that comparison
comes out left, here's how we do the
insert. We change our left link which is
right now it's null to whatever put
returns. So what's put going to return?
Well, that left link is null, so what's
going to happen is, in that call x is
null. It's going to be cre ated a new node
and the link to that node will be returned
and that's the link that we'll put in the
left. This is a very concise code that
otherwise we'd have various cases about
saving which link we went down in order to
reset that later on. So now the best way
having looked at those small examples, the
best way to understand this code is
recursively. Let's believe that it works
for small cases which we have just done.
So, lets see what the code does. So if x
is null, we want to create a new node and
return the link to that node. So, even if
it's a huge tree down at the bottom, we
just came of a null link. We just want to
create a new node with our new key and
return a link to that node, that's all we
want to do. Now, we can assume that put is
going to return a link to a sub-tree that
contains our new key and if our new key is
smaller than the key at the node that,
that we're processing now, then [cough] we
want to insert the new key value there and
the new node on the left otherwise, we
want to insert on the right. Most of the
time, the link that we get back will be
same as the link that we put in but for
the bottom node it will be different. So,
if put works properly inserting a new node
on the left, then that's what we want our
left link to be. If it works properly,
putting in the subtree on the right,
that's what we want our right link to be.
And by the way, if we find a key that's in
the tree already, then we just want to
reset the value. And in all of these cases
where we're on a node that already
existed, we just want to return the link
to that node. Again, when we look at more
sophisticated values we'll be returning
something else. So it's worthwhile you
know, checking that you believe that this
code implements the simple binary search
tree algorithm that we demoed where when
we fall off a null link we created a new
node and replaced that null link with the
new node . So that's insert for a binary
search tree in a symbol table. And again,
the cost of this is the number of compares
is equal to one plus the depth of the
node. We just go down a path in the tree.
Now, what's interesting about binary
search trees is that there are many
different binary search trees that
correspond to the same set of keys. So the
number it compares is going to depend on
the order in which the keys come in. And
that's a key feature of binary search
trees that we'll come back to again when
we look at more sophisticated data
structures. So it depends on how the keys
come in. The shape of the, of the tree
could be well in the best case so it would
be perfectly balanced. And one of the
things we'll look at is algorithms that
come very, very close to achieving that
goal. The typical, typical case it'll be
sort of balanced. Now but one problem is
if the keys come in and, and really
unfortunately, if they come in, in a
natural order. Like if they come in, in
order, that's the worst case. We don't get
any benefit from having it in a tree
shape. It's no different than a link list.
So we'll, we'll come back to dealing with
that worse case in the next lecture. But
the point is, the tree shape depends on
the order of insertion. Now, but let's
look at what's happened or visualize what
happens when keys come in, in random
order. So the tree grows from the bottom
in the little side to side motion it's
just accommodating room for each new key
as it's added. But you could see that even
for this case which is hundreds of keys,
the length of the path from top to bottom
is not so much. In this case, the maximum
distance from the top to the bottom is
sixteen the average is only nine and the
best you could in a perfectly balanced
tree it would be seven. So it's pretty
well balanced which means that our search
and insert cost in this case for 255 keys
is only going to be sixteen quite a bit
less. So one remark before we do the
analysis is that actually binary search
trees correspond exactly to Quicksort
partitioning. In the binary search tree,
we have a node at the root and we have
everybody smaller to the left, and
everybody larger to the right. In
Quicksort partitioning, after the random
shuffling we have the partitioning element
and then we process everybody to the left
independently of everybody to the right.
So it's a [cough] there's a direct
correspondence. If there is no duplicate
keys Quicksort processes them and referred
them out in BSTs and if there's no
duplicate keys there's a one-to-one
correspondence between what happens with
Quicksort and what happens with binary
search trees. And we point that out
because that helps with the mathematical
analysis. In fact, this correspondence
with Quicksort partitioning tells us we
can take that proof and prove that if you
insert in distinct keys into a BST, in
random order, then the expected number of
compares for a search and an insert is two
natural log N. So again about 1.38 log
base two of N almost the best that you
could do. It also has been shown actually
not that long ago, that the expected
height of the tree if they're inserted in
random order, the height that's the worst
case length of a path in the tree. This is
the average path in a tree, this is the,
the worst of all the keys. This is about
four natural log N. So, if you have the
keys in random order the binary search
tree gives efficient search and insert.
Now but there is this problem that the
actual worst case height if the keys come
in, in order and reverse order and other
natural orders that the time could be
proportional to n. So, we have this
summary which is looking pretty good,
because we have the average case for both
operations, the search and insert, to be
1.39 log N and that's probabilistic if
they are in random order, its extremely
likely to be there. But the problem by
comparison with sorting is, we don't get
to randomize the order the client is
providing the keys. So we're going to need
something better to provide the guarantee
than just randomly ordering the keys.
That's what we're going to be looking at
next when we look at more efficient
algorithms. But first we're going to look
at the implementation of order and
operations with the binary search tree
structure. It expands like binary search
to handle all these convenient client
operations in a very natural manner.
That's the implementation of binary search
trees for symbol tables. They give
sufficient implementation of both search
and insert.