When keys are comparable and we can put
them in order. We saw that we can use
binary search to get an efficient symbol
table implementation. But we can also
provide a lot of convenient functionality
for the client that's what we are going to
look at next. So this is just an example
of an application that might try to
associate keys with values. An
illustration of all the different
operations that a client might want. So we
already looked at the Get operation so we
might want to know what city is associated
with the event that happened at time nine
o'clock, thirteenth and so that should
return that value. But there's plenty of
other things that we might want. Like, for
example, what's the earliest time? That's
the min or what's the latest time? That's
the max. What about, being able to iterate
between, among all the keys between two
given times? That, certainly is
convenient. Then there's, what's the
seventh largest times, that's select that
like a median, it generalizes min or max?
Which key is that, happens second or
seventh? So that's, order statistics, a
dynamic thing what happened, whats the
closest time, thing that happened just
before, five past nine. Certainly, plenty
of clients might want, want that. So this
one is, I've only got ten tickets to sell.
So that's the cut off point for, selling,
seven tickets that's the cut off point.
For, anybody after that time doesn't get a
ticket. And, and this one might be, if
there's a time cut off. I'm not going to
sell tickets to anyone that came after
that time. And then the corresponding one
is, what's the first thing that happened
after that time? That's call in to the
radio show, I'm going to take that caller,
the first call that comes at nine:30. And
so forth. So then see how many things
happen between nine:15 and nine:25. And
how many calls were there before
nine:10:25? So you can see that there's,
all of these operations are quite natural
when we have the, table in sorted order.
And that's what we have for our binary
search implementation. So we can,
implement these, efficiently and they are,
convenient and useful for the clients. So
typically for ordered simple tables, when
keys are comparable will provide a much
wider interface it's very useful for many
clients. So we say that we're dealing with
keys that are comparable by simply adding
this extents comparable key to our
declaration. Same way we did for sorting
methods. So all that means is that our
implementations can use compared to but
for the client it means that all these
operations have meaning. Give me the
minimum key, give me the largest key, and
then I can get the value associated with
that using that. Give me the largest key
less than or equal to this key value or
the smallest key greater than that key
value, give me the number of keys less
than that key. You can actually implement
priority queues this way. Delete the
minimum key, delete the largest key. Now
usually we argue against why the interface
is just adding operations to an interface,
usually our reason for doing so is that we
can't guarantee that all the operations
can be performing efficiently. In this
case, as we'll see, ultimately we have
ways to guarantee that all the operations
can be formed efficiently. And they're so
convenient for clients. It's certainly
worth adding them. So we have iterate
through all the keys, and iterate through
all the keys in a given range, and count
the number of keys in a given range. All
of these operations are very useful for
clients and we'll see plenty of examples
later on. So we have to greatly expand
our, our table. What, what are going to be
the cost of all of these things. And this
is a big difference between the binary
search implementation where the keys are
kept in order in an array, in the
sequential search implementation, when
they're all in a link list. So, for
example, to provide order and iteration,
you have to get them sorted. And that's,
going to be a lot of work, and take N lg N
time. Whereas binary search, you just
iterate through, the things in order. The
give me the seventh key we just go and
look there, they are in order. Rank
operation, that is essentially what binary
search provides. That's the, our basic
implementation is providing rank. Floor
and ceiling that's again is an outgrowth
of the rank operation. Minimum and maximum
well again those are like select. Their
just right there, you look at the first or
the last. To insert or delete however
takes linear time. To maintain the sorted
array in dynamic fashion is going to take
linear time you have to go through the
whole thing. And so that's really are the
key to thinking about what are symbol
table and symbol tables in general. How
could we guarantee that all operations are
fast? Binary research is pretty good but
that's a major flaw. It can't maintain a
dynamic table efficiently with binary
search and that's going to be your focus
in the next lecture