Next, we'll look at some elementary symbol
table implementations. These are so simple
that we won't go into much detail. But
still, it's worthwhile to take a look at
them to set the stage for the more
advanced implementations we'll consider
next. Well, one thing we could do is
maintain a link list. We could keep it in
order or keep it unordered, this version
keeps it unordered. So, we are going to
have nodes in the link list, that have key
value pairs, they have every key in the
symbol table and a value associated to
that key. For search, we have to, since
it's unordered, scan through the whole
list to find a match, a key that's there.
For insert, I would also have to scan
through all keys to find the place to
update a value, if it's a value that's
already there. And if there's no match,
then we could add it to the front. So
here's our simple client for traces. So if
we associate S with zero, we just had it
that's our one node link, link list that's
got that information. Associate E with one
that's not there, so we just add it to the
beginning of the list. A with two, R with
three, C with four, H with five, and so
forth. So now, when we associate E with
six, we have to search through the list to
see if there's an E. In this case there
is, and then we update, just update that
value. That's the associative array
abstraction. It's possible to implement
symbol tables that allow multiple values
with the same key and so forth. And that
leads to different types of clients,
different types of implementations. We're
going to stick to this associative array
abstraction and no duplicate keys in the
symbol table because it both simplifies
implementations and leads to simpler
client code. Okay, X7 is a new value A8 we
found A in there and update the value
eight and then M9, P10, L11 are all out
there, and they go at the beginning, and
then the last one changes the value at E
again, twelve. So, this is a, a simple
implementing this as a example of link
list processing. Slight modification of
our stack and queue code. And we will skip
the details and just a note that what's
the cost of implementing this. Well if
there's been if there are N things on the
symbol table, you have to, for both search
and insert look all the way through. And
if everything's random then on average,
you only have to look halfway through for
a successful search. And well, you still
have to insert another issue is for many
clients if the keys are ordered it's nice
to be able to iterate through the symbol
table in order and this one by definition
doesn't provide that. And this one just
uses equals. So, the keys don't have to be
comparable for this it just uses equals.
So our challenge is to look for methods
that give us more efficient
implementations than search and insert
searching operations. And we've already
looked at an algorithm that can do this
and that's binary search. So for binary
search the now, what we're going to do is
use an ordered array. And actually use
parallel arrays, one for the keys and one
for the values. And the idea is to keep
the array of keys in sorted order. And
then find the index associated with the
key that we're searching for using binary
search and then use that index to get the
value that's associated with that key
that's stored in the parallel array. And
we looked at the binary search algorithm
earlier in the course. And so, for
example, if we're doing a, if these are
the keys in our symbol table. And we're
doing a search for the index where P is
stored. We look at the middle. P is bigger
than L, so we look to the right. Look in
the middle of the right half. P is less
than R so we look to the left. Continue
until we find P. When we find P, we return
its index, and we use that index to get us
the value that we need or another way to
look at this is that implements the
function, how many keys are there that are
less than K. So, for example, for queue
that's unsuccessful search and you can
figure out from the last index when you
don't find your the element that you're
seeking you can figure out the return
value, which is the number of keys that
are less than it. So, that's a trace of
implementing binary search to find the
rank of a key in an ordered array, and
again, for successful, you can use that
rank to return the value and for if it is
unsuccessful, you can use that rank to
figure out where to insert the new key.
Alright. So, this is the code for the get
operation in this rank, which is binary
search. So this is precisely the binary
search curve that we looked at before. So,
let's look at again. So if the whole table
is empty, return null. Otherwise, we call
rank and that could gives us the number of
keys less than the current key. And so,
that is where we look to check to see if
that key is there. If it's there, then we
return the value with the same index in
the parallel array. If it's not there,
then we return null, saying the key's not
there. Now, the problem with minor
searches well, not necessarily a problem
but the situation is that if when it's
time to insert a new element, we have to
move everything larger over one position
just like an insertion sort. So, if the
table has A, E, R, and S and we have to
insert the value C, then we have to move
the E, R, and S over one position to put
the C and then put the value associated
with C if they're the same thing in the
values array. Move all the values
associated with those keys over one
position and put the associated value in.
So, this is a trace of what would happen
for our trace. And, and again, every
insertion involves, involves making a new
position by moving all the larger keys
over one position do the same thing in the
values array. And if it's changing the
value associated with a key that's already
there, then it's just a matter of finding
where the key is and changing the value at
that index. So, those from that trace is
pretty easy to see what's involve, what's
involved for the code and we'll skip that
code. And just take a look at the
comparison between this elementary
implementation for symbol tables with the
sequential search in an unordered list.
So, one thing is we're using a different
key interface. We're taking advantage of
the fact that the keys are comparable to
give us an efficient search. Ah., we can
do search in worst case in average case,
in time proportional to log N. That's what
binary search provides for us. And this is
a fine data structure for symbol tables
where there's where, that are relatively
static, where the values don't change
much, and most of the operations are
search. It's hard to beat binary search.
On the other hand, in a dynamic situation
where there are a lot of inserts. This
method is going to be problematic because
the cost of its insert is linear and
proportional to N/2. If you have a huge
number of operations and everyone who is
proportional to the symbol table size,
then you're just not going to be able to
support huge numbers of keys. What we want
is efficient implementations of both
search and insert. Those are elementary
implementations. Next we'll look at more
advanced ones.