If our symbols table's really going to be
dynamic, we need to be able to delete key
valued pairs from the table. As we'll see,
all symbol table implementations have,
lead to complications when we try to do
this operation. Binary search trace is our
first example. So we need to fill in this
one table. What's, what's the cost of
deletion in a binary search tree? How are
we going to really do that? Well let's
take a look at a very lazy approach which
we set up for in our basic conventions for
simple tables. What we can do to remove a
node with a give key is just mark it with
a tombstone. Say, well, we'll leave the
key in the tree to guide searches, but we
won't, count it as being in the symbol
table. And actually you can, make some
progress with this kind of method. Leaving
tombstone throughout the tree. And, make
sure that you keep, as long as there
aren't too many deletions, you can keep
the search costs, and deletion and insert
costs to be logarithmic. But it definitely
becomes, inconvenient to manage large
numbers of tombstones in highly dynamic
situations with large numbers of keys and
values. Eventually you're going to get an
overload of memory and you're going to
have to rebuild the thing or clean out the
tombstones in some way so we need to look
for a better way. This is a general method
that people often use on all different
types of implementations, but in modern
systems it's rather unsatisfactory. Also
got a simpler problem. What about deleting
the minimum? Well actually, that's maybe
not too difficult to delete the minimum in
a binary search tree. Again, we just go to
the left until we get a null left link.
And then, what we can do is just return
that node's right link then that old node,
nobody's pointing to it, so it's available
for garbage collection. And then we use
our usual trick of returning the link that
we went down to update the other links
after the recursive calls. And also we
have to update the counts, something
happened down below and we used that code
to update the counts, in a co nsistent
way, so this code implements deleting, not
too bad at all. If x. Left null, return x
right. Otherwise x left = delete min x
left. And then when you're done with that,
it fix the count so maybe a node got
deleted down there, but always, the
invariant is that the count of the node is
one + size of the left and right. And then
return x and fix the links and the counts
on the way up. That's a fine
implementation for delete min, and it also
works for delete max. And that's the basis
for a general method for deleting nodes
from BSTs known as Hibberd deletion. So,
that's the second case, the first case for
Hibberd deletion is what we want to do to
delete a, a node with key K, is we search
for the node that contains the key, and
the easiest case is that node has no
children. So to, to delete a node that has
no children just return null. And then go
back up to update the counts as usual,
that's the easy case. The next most
difficult case is like the delete min case
we find a node T that contains our key, so
like deleting R in this tree, it only has
one child. Just go ahead and return the
link to that child and that updates the
link and everything works fine and then
the node that the leads that available for
garbage collection that nobody's pointing
to it. And then again update all the
accounts after the recursive calls. Zero
children no problem one child no problem.
The problem is what happens when there is
two children. So say we want to delete
node E in this tree. We have only one
link, and we can get rid of the node but
we have only one link pointing to it. But
we have two links pointing down from it.
So what are we going to do with those two
links? Well the Hibbard deletion mechanism
which is pretty old. 50 years ago, it was
proposed. Says, go ahead and find the next
smallest node in the right subtree of that
tree. So in the case that's H and what's
that node? Well it's the minimum in T's
right sub tree. And we know how to delete
the minimum. So we just find that minimum
node and, in this case it's H, and we put
that node in T spot and then delete the
minimum. So, find the H that's the
minimum, hang on to it, and then delete
the minimum NT sub tree and then, so we
take the E, replace it with the H, delete
the H, and then everything is fine. It is
still a BST. So we, essentially we are
finding a node that has only one link,
deleting that node, and then replacing the
node that we need to delete with that one.
That's Hibbard deletion. It's a little bit
asymmetric. Why are we using the successor
and not the predecessor? No real reason.
And it's not really satisfactory because
of that, and we'll come back to this but
it works. So this is the code for Hibbard
deletion. So we search for the key. If
it's got no right child, we're fine. We
just return, x out left, and that handles
both cases zero and one. If it does have a
right child, then we do this, find the
minimum, on the right. Delete min on the
right and then fix the links and then
update our count that covers all cases. So
actually not that much code, it's
complicated but not particularly more
complicated than other code we have seen
like rank and floor and ceiling and that
implements Hibbard deletion. So now we
have a fully dynamic symbol table where we
can insert and delete. The number of nodes
that we have in the tree as always
proportion to the number of key value
pairs in the symbol table. And the problem
is, and this was quite a surprise when it
was first discovered actually many years
after Hibbard proposed the algorithm is
this lack of symmetry that tends to lead
to difficulties. And here we are just
inserting the leading alternating insert
and delete a random key. So that maybe
well models a situation, practical
situation. And as you watch it go for
awhile. You can see that this thing about
going to the right and taking the
successor all the time. The tree's
becoming much less balanced than it was.
And, this seems to be a, a problem. We
can't be having, supposedly having a
dynamic situation, that is going to, allow
support of lots of different inserts and
de letes. And in the end, win up with a
less balanced tree. What's worse, if you,
so how you are going to fix it? At the end
researches show that after, sufficiently
long sequence of random inserts and
deletes, the height of the tree becomes
square root of N not lg N. Square root of
N is usually bigger than lg N. It might
make difference between acceptable and
unacceptable performance in real
applications. Then what's worse is you try
to fix it by say randomly choosing between
the left and the right, that doesn't work,
it still becomes square root of N. And
that's a very long standing open problem
to find a natural, simple, efficient
delete for binary search trees. That's
another one like merging in place, that
you think there ought to be another easy
way to do it, but in 50 years no one's
really discovered one. Now we're going to
look at something pretty close in the next
lecture, but here's the situation that
we're left with. We have a binary search
tree algorithm, which is fine in that
gives us lg N performance for search and
insert, in a situation where we can think
that these things are happening randomly.
But we're kind of stuck if we allowed
delete. In fact everything regenerates to
square root of N, and we also have a
problem with, with the worst case if the
keys happen to have some order in them our
trees are not going to be balanced at all.
And that's going to make the difference
between acceptable and not acceptable
performance. What we're going to look at
next time, called a red black minor search
tree, will guarantee logarithmic
performance for all operations. So that's
extremely significant and much better then
binary search trees but the delete
operation for binary search trees shows us
the kind of complexity that we can
encounter with working with these kinds of
data structures.