Next we'll look at a proof that the
Ford-Fulkerson algorithm is valid, known
as the max-flow min-cut theorem.
It also proves that the two problems are
equivalent.
We need a couple more definitions to, to
show, first we want to show the
relationship between a flow and a cut.
So in this case we've got a cut where T is
on one side and all the other vertices are
on the same side as S.
And what we talk about is the flow across
the cut.
And that, what that is, is the sum of the
flow on it's edges that go from S to T,
minus the amount that goes the other way.
That's the flow across the cut.
So this, what's called the flow value
lemma is that, if you have a flow then for
any cut.
The net flow across the cut is the value
of the flow.
That's called the flow value lemma.
Doesn't matter what the cut is, this, this
is a max flow, a flow with value 25 and
every cut is going to have 25 flowing
across it.
So, this cut, this is a more complicated
cut where S and these three vertices are
colored.
So the flow of a, across that cut has to
take the all the edges that go from a gray
vertex to a white one.
So, there's ten plus ten, plus from a gray
vertex to a white one, five plus ten + 00.
Then, we have to subtract off the edges
that go from a white to a gray one.
So we add up all the ones that go from
gray to white.
Ten + ten + five + ten + zero + zero and
subtract off the two that go from a white
to a gray and, still, the net value across
the flow is the same, the value of the
flow.
That's the flow value lemma that gives a
particular relationship between flows and
cuts.
And that's not too difficult to prove by
induction on the size of one of the sets.
For example, if we do an induction on the
size of the set containing T, it's
certainly true when that set consists of
just T, because the value of the flow is
exactly equal to the edges coming into T.
And then to prove by induction, you can
move any vertex from A to B in local
elibriums, local equilibrium's going to
make sure that the flow value limma is
true.
And so that's, that's how it's proved.
And a corollary of that is that, that
outflow from S is equal to the inflow to
T, which is equal to the val, all equal to
the value of the flow.
And that's also easy to see in all of our
examples.
So to get started let's, let's look at
what's called weak duality.
If, F is any flow at all, in network.
If AB is any cut.
The value of the flow is going to be less
than or equal to the capacity of the cut.
So in this case value of flow is 27 and
the capacity of the cut is 30.
Value of the flow is always less than or
equal to the capacity of the cut.
And well the net flow across a cut has got
to be less than less than or equal to it's
capacity 'coz it's at least that and then
if there's any edges going the other way,
they get subtracted to compute the lugnut
flow.
So a weak duality, is that, that's an easy
thing to prove.
So what we want to prove are these two
theorems.
The max-flow min-cut theorem is really two
theorems combined called the augmenting
path theorem that says the flow's at
max-flow if and only if there's no
augmenting paths, and that the value of
the max-flow equals the capacity of the
min-cut.
In any network.
And the way we prove that is to prove that
the following three conditions are
equivalent.
Again this is a proof that's a little
intricate logically.
It's worthwhile for me to go through it,
but to really understand it you're going
to need to read it carefully and convince
yourself that these three conditions work.
So here's the three conditions that we're
going to prove our equipment.
First one is, there is a cut, there's some
cut whose capacity equals the value of the
flow.
The second one is that f is a max flow.
So if there's a cut whose capacity equals
the flow then f is a max flow.
And if f is a max flow there's such a cut.
And then the third one is that there's no
augmenting path.
So we're going to prove those three
conditions are equivalent.
And we'll do it with a little logic
trickery.
So first we could prove that one implies
two.
If there exist a cut capacities equals the
value flow, then f is the max flow.
Alright, so suppose that we have such a
cut, capacity is equal the value of the
flow then any other flow by weak duality,
flow is going to be less than or equal to
the capacity of that cut, .
In fact that cuts equal to the value of
the flow, so therefore, that's the
maximum, max flow.
The value of any flow, if less or equal in
value of f, so it's the max flow.
So that proves that one implies two.
Okay.
Now we're going to prove two implies
three.
One implies two, and also two implies
That also means one implies three.
So in order to prove that we're going to
prove the counter-positive.
So we'll prove that not three implies not
two.
That is, if there is an augmenting path
then F is not a max flow.
Well, that's pretty straightforward, then,
'cuz that's what we do in the algorithm.
We could improve the flow by sending flow
along the path.
So it can't be a max flow.
So that's, pretty easy.
If that was a max flow, there's no
augmenting path cuz if there is an
augmenting path, that's not a max flow.
So that's the, second, part of the proof.
And now the third part of the proof, will
prove that three implies one.
So, that'll give you, the circular logic
condition that proves that they're all
equivalent.
So we want to prove that if there is no
augmenting path, then there is a cut in
this capacity that equals the value of the
flow.
So if there's no augmenting path.
Then what we're going to have is a cut
where A is the set of vertices.
That are, connected to S by an undirected
path with no full forward or empty
backward edges.
And so there has to be such a cut if
there's no odd many path.
S has got to be in A and T has got to be
in B otherwise there will be a path from A
to B with no four, four front and empty
backward with edges and the capacity of
that cut equals the net flow across the
cut but all the four edges are fallen, all
the backward edges are empty so that's
exactly equal to the value of the flow.
So if there's no augmenting path then we
can demonstrate a cut whose capacity
equals the value of the flow and that is
completes the proof of the max flow and
the cut theorem.
Sorry.
Alright.
So the one last step is if we have
computed a max-flow, then what we can do
is compute the min-cut by computing the
set of vertices.
And we can do that just by a graph search.
We start at S and if there's a path that
has no, has a, a forward edge that's not
full then we follow that path and if we
have a backward edge that's not empty, we
follow the path.
And we just do a, a graph search to get to
all the vertices that we can reach with
forward edges that aren't full, and
backward edges that aren't empty.
And then we treat the full forward edges
and the back empty edges as not being
there.
Otherwise, we do just a regular graph
search.
And that's, going to give us, the, the,
then the set of edges that define by that
cut are going to be the min-cut.
So, not difficult to compute a min-cut
from a max-flow.
So that's a proof of the augmenting path
there min, max-flow min-cut there.