Today we're going to talk about tries,
which is a data structure for searching
with string keys that is remarkable
effective in enabling us to deal with huge
amounts of data that we have to process
nowadays.
Just as a motivation, when we left off
talking about searching algorithms, or the
symbol table implementations here's where
we were.
The best algorithms that we examined were
balanced red, black, binary search trees,
in hash tables.
And With respect to the basic search,
insert and delete operations.
Red black BSTs we're able to guarantee
that we can get those done in logorithmic
time, actually, pretty efficiently.
And for hashing, we'd get'em done in
constant time under certain assumptions.
That we could have a uniform, hash
function.
And also, for hashing, what we need to
compute a hash, code for binary search
trees, we use, a compare to function.
And another difference is, binary search
trees, we can support more operations.
Than we can support with hashing ordered
operations.
For example, getting the rank of a key in
the tree, and other things.
And those are terrific algorithms.
And we looked at plenty of go, good
applications of those algorithms.
But still there's the question could we do
better?
And the answer is that yes, we can do
better.
As with string sorting, we can avoid
examining the entire key.
Which is going to give us algorithms that
can compete and even beat these classic
algorithms.
So to get started we are going to
articulate in API for symbol tables that
specialize for the case when the keys are
strings.
So simply, we just add the modifier string
to our standard symbol table EPI.
And we can take a generic value just put
the keys or strings.
And then we take all the methods that we
articulated before.
And for key type, instead of generic, we
use string.
And this is going to allow us to develop
efficient algorithms that take advantage
of properties of strings.
Our goal is to get, some algorithms that
are even faster than hashing.
And maybe, more flexible than BSTs.
And we're going to be able to achieve both
those goals.
So, this again is the summary of the
running times for when, in the case that
the keys are strings for red black BSTs
and for hashing.
And let's take a look at those so if L is
the length of the string.
And n is the number of strings and then
also the rate x is r is going to be a
factor later on but its not going to be
for these two.
Then for hashing for every operation we
have to compute a hash function, which
basically means looking at every character
in the string.
Actually in Java string hash functions are
cached, so sometimes there's efficiencies
cuz you only have to comp, and they're
mutable, so you only have to compute the
hash function once.
And then this is roughly the amount of
space that takes into account the table
and the string size for red black BSTs,
the analysis is a bit more complicated.
For a search hit, you have to look at the
entire string.
Given a entire key to check that every
character's the same and then the
comparison's depending on the nature of
the keys for a typical case though its
something like log squared N. we had log N
comparison's but usually you have to look
at something like a log N characters in
the key in order to get down the tree.
For a search miss you might be able to
find out before you get to the end of the
tree and sing a for an insert so the
running times are something like this.
Then here's some experimental evidence
that, that we, we can use to test out
these analytic hypothesis.
And we'll just look at two examples one is
the entire text of Melville's Moby Dick
which we've used before and that's about a
million characters.
And maybe 200,000 strings.
And add to this 200,000 strings, about
32,000 are distinct.
And then this,
There's another file of actors from the
Internet movie database that's much bigger
maybe tourism magnitude bigger.
And it's got maybe about a million
different words.
So we'll want our algorithms to do better
than, or at least as well as red black
BSTs in hashing on these data sets.
I think, you know, our test is to dedupe
these data sets.
So that's our challenge.
Efficient performance for string keys and
try to come up with algorithms that can
compete with the best classic algorithms.
Now in order to do that we're going to
look at R way tries.
That's a particular data structure, that
was, invented actually really quite a
while ago.
This data structure, dates back, to the
60s.
And, the first thing to know about it is
that, the name is based a little bit, on a
pun.
It actually is the middle letters of the
word retrieval, but we don't pronounce it
tree because then we couldn't distinguish
it from binary search trees, so we
pronounce it try.
And this is a confusing fact of life that
we've been living with for many decades
now with this data structure.
And let's look at what a try is and we'll
look at some, examples before we get to
the code.
So, for now, we're going to think of a try
as some nodes.
A tree structure with nodes where we store
characters in the nodes,
Not keys.
And the other thing is that each node has
R children, where R is the rate, it's the
number of possible characters.
And there's g-, the possibility of a child
for each possible character.
Now in the standard implementation, this
is going to involve on all links.
We have to have a placeholder for each
possible character.
So there's a lot of null links and tries.
And we'll get back to that in a minute.
But to get the concept, we'll use this
graphical representation, where we have
characters and nodes and we don't show any
null length.
And the other thing is, remember a symbol
table is associating a key with a value,
so this try is built for this set of key
value pairs.
And what we do is we.
Store values in nodes that correspond to
the last characters in keys.
And we'll look, that's what these numbers
here are.
And we'll look at a little more in detail,
on how this try is built in just a second.
So that's the basic idea.
We're going to have string keys.
We're going to associate values, and we're
going to use this tree-like, tree data
structure but we're not going to draw the
imply null links for now.
So, for example, in this trie so the root
re-, represents all strings.
And, coming out of the root is one length
for each possible letter.
In particular in this try, the middle link
is the link to the, to a sub try that
contains all the keys that start with S.
Then we go further down.
Each time we go by a node, we pick off a
letter so that this length, for example,
goes to the try for all keys that start
with s followed by h followed by e.
And so forth.
So now all, out of all the keys that start
with SHE, actually one of them, the one
that just has the letters in then ends,
has a value associated with it.
So when the node corresponding to the last
letter, the E, we put the value zero.
And so that's, how the try is going to
look.
So just given that definition, then let's
look at, how to do search, in a try.
All we do is use the characters and the
key to guide our search down the data
structure.
So, let's say we're looking for the key
shells.
So we start at the root, and we go down
the S link, since we started with an S.
Now our second letter is H, so we look to
see if there's a non-null link that,
corresponding to H, and in this case there
is.
Now our next letter is E, so we look for
an E.
Now.
No need to examine the value here because
well we haven't looked at all the letters
in our key yet.
So now we look for L now we look for
another L and then finally we find the S
and when we find the S we look to see if
there's a value there.
In this case there is a value and so
that's what we return the value associated
with the last key character.
So that's a typical search hit in a tri.
Another way is...
So, that node was down at the bottom but
if you had.
We're doing a search for SHE, you follow
the same path.
But now when you get to the E, that's the
last character of that key and so we just
know how to return that, value associated
with that node.
That is, the search doesn't have to go all
the way to the bottom.
It might terminate at an intermediate
node.
And we just return the value associated
with the node corresponding to the last
character in the key.
What about a search miss?
Well, there's two cases.
It's for a search miss.
So one of them is we've followed down the
tree picking off the letters in the key
one letter at a time as, as before.
And then when we get to the end of the key
we take a look to see if there is a value.
In this case there's no value associated
with the last key character that mean
there's no key in the data structure
that's been associated with a value.
So we just return no.
Or, the other thing that can happen is, we
can, reach a null link.
So, our key now is S, starts with S, and
then H, and then E, and then L, and now
our next letter is T, so we look to see if
there's a non null link coming from this
node associated with T.
And in this case, there's no such link, so
we return null.
That's evidence that, that string, there's
no key associated with that string in our
data structure.
So that's a search miss.
Iii.
Now, what about insertion?
Well insertion is also pretty simple.
So we follow two, two rules.
One is again, we go down links
corresponding each character in the key.
If we come out on a link, we create a new
node that's associated with the character
that we're on.
And just keep doing that until we get to
the last character of the key, in which
case, we put the value.
So if in this try, we're supposed to
associate the value seven with
[inaudible].
We follow, our path from the root to s,
'cause our first letter is s, and then
h.'Cause our next letter is h.
And then a O, we had an, [inaudible] kinda
ran into a null link.
So we have to put, a node there, with the
character, associated with the character
O.
So in later searches for this key, we'll
be able to find it by passing through that
node.
And now we move to the next letter, and
there's no node again.
In the next letter, there's still no node.
Iii.
When we get to the end, then that's the
last character in the key, and we put our
value seven.
And now we've modified the data structure,
adding the nodes that are necessary for a
later search to go through, character by
character and find the value associated
with that key.
So that's an insertion into a try.
Just to cement all these ideas let's do a
demo of how that tree was constructed from
scratch.
So we have a null try.
So we're going to start by putting the,
associating the value zero with the string
SHE.
So we start at the root node, which, and
I'll try, it just has that one node.
Create a new node for S, create a new node
for H, create a new node for E.
Associate zero.
So the key is the sequence of characters
from the root to the value, and the value
is in the node corresponding to the last
character.
This try represents the symbol table that
contains just on string SHE, and
associated with zero.
Every other string, if you search for any
other string in this try you'll either end
in a node that doesn't have a value or
you'll end at a null link.
All right, so now, let's say we put in the
key S, E, L, L, S and you can kinda tell
where it's going, we made room for it in
the try.
So we go for S, and now the second letter,
E, corresponds to a null link, so we
create a new node.
And similarly we go through and create new
nodes for each of the remaining characters
in the key and then associate the value
one at the end.
So now we have a try that has two keys in
it, SHE and SELLS.
Now our next is to insert SEA.
So now we have S, we already have a node
corresponding to E.
And so now we just have to create one new
node, the one corresponding to A.
And put our value two there.
And now, we're going to put SHELLS in.
So we already have the S, already have the
H, already have the E, so now we have to
add nodes for the last three letters in
that string.
And associate the value three with it.
Now we're going to put finally a key that
doesn't start with S.
So that means we create a new node
corresponding to the first letter of that
string, I, N to the other letter two.
And then associate the value four.
And here's another one that doesn't start
with s.
So we create new nodes corresponding to
each one of its characters, and associate
the value five with the last one.
Now here's SEA.
So this is, remember, our symbol table API
is associative, which means that if we get
a new value for a key that's already in
the table, we overwrite.
The old value with the new value.
That's the way, the convention that we've
chosen for symbol tables.
So that is easily done with tries as well.
Now here's one more key, S, H.
And now we have to add a new node because
there's no node that's a child of H that
corresponds letter O.
So we have to create new nodes for O, R,
and E, and associate the value seven with
it.
So that's a tri that has precisely eight
keys.
If you look for any one of those eight
keys you'll get the value.
If you look for any other string you'll
either come to a node that has a null
value or go out on a null link and so the
search would be unsuccessful.
That's is a demo of tri construction.
Now that you have a basic idea of how,
what tris are and how they work, let's
take a look at what's needed to implement
them in Java.
The key idea in the tri representation for
implementation in Java or any computer
language is that. Instead of representing
a node as a character in the node, what we
do is represent the links as an indexed
array with one entry for each possible
character.
And the idea is the characters are
actually.
Implicitly defined by link indeces.
So just for example, we have this small
try that we built over here.
In this case, the root has only one node
below it.
That's for all the keys that start with S.
The way that's represented in real
representation, and this is for
efficiency.
And it's the way that tries get their
Is we have one link corresponding to each
possible letter.
And the only one that is un-null is S.
So the character S is defined implicitly
by the fact that, that link that
[inaudible] that, that corresponds to S is
not null.
Over here there's from e to a there's two
links coming out of E.
And the only way that we represent A is by
having the first link be not null.
If the link corresponding to a letter is
not null, then it corresponds to having
that letter in the node that it points to.
So in this case we have E connected to A
and L.
So we have the entries corresponding to A
and L filled with non null values.
So you can see immediately the
correspondence between this tri the way
we've been drawing it and the job
representation of it.
Where each node contains 200, or r links
if there's r different letters.
And letters are implicitly represented by
non [inaudible] links.
Now, you just go in the node.
So for example, I, in this try, S, E, A,
but which is easy to follow down through
the try.
We're looking for an S.
And S is the twentieth letter in the
alphabet.
Or so.
We index into the twentieth position and
that takes us right to S.
And E's the fifth letter, we take the
fifth link.
Then A's the first letter, we take the
first link.
So we can use the character as index into
the array of links.
To quickly travel down the tree.
Then when we get to the last character, we
can check the value at that node that's
stored in the node.
One slight complication in the
implementation that we encountered before
with hashing algorithms and other things.
We're going to need arrays of nodes.
That's what our lengths are.
So we can't have any generics with nodes,
even though I would like to.
So we have to declare the value to be a
type object, and then we'll have to cast
it back to whatever type it should be,
when we return it.
And we'll see that in code.
Other than that little complication.
This is quite straightforward
representation of tries.
And it leads to a very easy
implementation.
So the keys and the characters are not
explicitly stored.
They're, they're implicitly, because of
the links.
And that's a, a very important point to
think about when it comes to, implementing
using tries.
Given that representation, this code for
implementing try, simple table in Java
almost writes itself.
So it's a [inaudible] implementation in
this slide has the implementation of put
using the same recursive scheme that was
used many other times in building trees
the what are the instance variables?
Well we declare artery 256 as usual in our
string implementations where working with
extended asking and then we have one
instance variable that matters and that is
the root of the [inaudible].
So tries begin with, start, all tries
start with a null node.
So first thing we do is create a new node
and put a reference to that node in root.
So our empty trie consists of a node
that's got a.
Remember, when you create a new node we
Build an array of R links to nodes.
And at the beginning those'll all be empty
links.
Or all null links.
So the root points to a node that has 256
null lengths.
Now to put.
Or to associate a key with the value in a
trie.
We use this instance method that calls
recursive method.
Again, the same way that we've done for
other tree construction schemes before.
So we take the recursive method, takes a
node as argument and returns a node.
So it takes a reference to a trie and
returns to, a reference to the trie that
it constructs.
After a associating the key with a value.
Just to get started suppose that our first
key has just one character.
So in that case, we would call.
Another recursive put for the root, with
our one character.
And so our one character key.
And call the recursive routine.
Now our node is not null.
It's the root node.
So and our key is length one.
And we, called it starting at zero.
So the first thing that we do is pick out
the [inaudible] character of our, Yeah key
so zero of character which is our one
character and I guess its an index
whatever letter might happen to B.
Say its B then C would be two that's sort
of thing and then all we do is recursively
are follow that link in ser.
Our, associate our key value in the try
pointed to by that link.
And then take the link that we get and put
it back into that link out of the root
node.
So the next call there's nothing in the
word dot next it's a, it's null so the
next call we get null so we create a new
node.
And then that new node this point we've
called with D plus one moving to the next
character.
So now we have D equals one which is equal
to our key dot length.
So we associate the value in that node
with our node and we return it.
So that return one level up will set the
length of the new node in the appropriate
entry corresponding to the root.
Again once you've learned our normal
recursive way of structuring building tree
structures this code is very natural.
So for a longer key I'm again thinking
recursively we find the if we're suppose
to insert the key associate the key with a
value, and we're working on the
[inaudible] character.
We pick out the, The character at the deep
position.
We use that to index and to be in link
array of the current node and then that's
the link that we set when we do a put of
the new node.
So when we start with a longer string and
a perfectly empty tree we create new nodes
all the way down and then put their links
to their parents all the way up.
In this recursive structure.
And it's a very simple and natural
recursive code.
So that's the put.
Now that takes a little study but not so
much once you're use to our standard
recursive way of producing tree
structures.
And get is even simpler.
So contains and gets.
So our scenario's standard convention is
to return null if we have a key that's not
there or that contains and the get
function is a again recursive.
Procedure that will return in reference to
the node, and if that's null, we return
null.
Otherwise, we can get the value out of the
node return by the recursive procedure.
And then remember we had the omega value
in nodes of type objects.
So we have to cast that back to the type
value.
And the recursive get is very simple.
To find the node that contains the value
associated with a given key.
And we're working on the deep character.
And we're currently on, node x.
We just, return null.
Effects happens to be null.
That means it's not there.
If we're, at the last character in the
key, we return our current node.
Otherwise, we get that [inaudible]
character.
And we use that to index into the next
array of the current, node.
And recursively called the get routine,
for, that node moving, one down the tree.
And incrementing our key pointer by one.
Extremely simple, recursive code to do the
tri implementation.
So what about the performance?
Well in a cert chip we simply go down the
tried examining all L characters just
using each one to index into an x-array at
some note.
And then go down to the end to, to see if
there's a value there.
Search miss we might have to go all the
way down to the last character.
But we could also just have a miss match
on the first character and find a null
link right away.
And actually.
Typically, in a try.
In typical applications, we only examine a
few characters.
So right away, you can see, by thinking
about a search miss, that try algorithms
can be sublinear.
We can find out that a key's not in the
tree, by only examining a few characters.
If we don't have any.
Strings in our try that begin with the
same few characters as our search key,
then, it's not there.
That's a typical case.
Now the downside of tri performance in
lots of applications is the amount of
space used.
There is the problem that every node's got
R lengths in it.
And particularly, down at the bottom, the
leaf nodes that correspond to the last
characters and keys and, the prefix in the
key in the try that's going to be null
lengths.
Now it is possible in a huge try with lots
of strings that are short and sharing
common prefixes to actually much less
space then this but be ardenal links at
each leaf is a real problem in some
applications so we're going to take a look
on how to deal with that.
So the bottom line is for symbol tables
with relatively small numbers of string
keys where the amount of space used by the
[UNKNOWN] is not a problem.
Then we get very fast, search hit.
And even faster search miss but we burn up
some space.
That's the bottom line about try
performance.
And, just a typical application.
Maybe you get a job interview question
about, what data structure you use for
spell checking And then, so, and this is
just an example, to show, how effective
tries can be for such an application.
Where all the words are three letters.
And the solution is, build a 26 way try.
So spell checking, usually, there'll be
pre-processing to strip out everything but
the lowercase letters that make up the
word.
So you can build a 26 way try that, will
immediately tell you whether you have a
misspelled word or not.
Another interesting thing about prize is
that, deletion is, very easy, what do we
do to delete a key value pair, well you
find, the node corresponding to key and,
set the value there corresponding to null,
.
So that's, easily done, so we want to
delete shelves we cross out the, value
there, and now, there's two cases.
One case is this one where that node, now
we set its' value to null and its got all
null links.
Now there's no reason for its existence.
So it wouldn't have been created except
for the fact that we inserted shells.
So if the node has got null links, just
remove it.
And then, just delete it.
And then when you go back up the tree,
which you do because you got down there.
Every node that you touch you check if
it's got a no value and all no links, just
delete it.
And you keep going until you find one that
has either a value or a downhill link and
then that's when you can stop the leading
node.
So it's pretty easy to delete a key value
pair in an R-way tri.
And that's unusual for other search
structures that we saw in the deletion was
a significant challenge to implement
often.
So our challenge is to find a way to use,
less memory.
Be, particularly because, nowadays, many
strings are built with Unicode.
And the number of null links in a tri
would be truly huge.
Again we talked about this, with rated
sorting.
A lot a programs broke when this.
Switch went from ASCII to Unicode.
In any program that use this reposession,
representation for Tries, certainly broke.
So that's an introduction to Tries with
R-way Tries.