Next we're going to look at Ternary
search tries, which is another data
structure that new data structure, that
responds to the problem of too much
memory space used by our way tries.
this is a very easy to describe and
implement data structure.
And it came out of the same paper that
Jon Bentley and I wrote in the 1990s when
we developed the three way Ternary
quicksort.
the idea is now we're going to actually
store characters in nodes in values.
but, we're not going to store whole keys
in there, just characters.
but we're not going to use this idea of a
big array, where a nominal link is an
implicit value of a character, actually
going to store the characters.
but what we're going to do is, make each
node have three children not two, like in
a binary search tree.
And not r, like in a Nr way trie, but
exactly three and the three children are
for the trie corresponding to smaller
keys.
The trie corresponding to trees that
start with the same, character in the tri
corresponding to larger trees.
And just given this, this des,
description and experience with many of
the data structures that now, we've
talked about already in this course.
many of you could go off and implement
this data structure, and we'll see how
simple the implementations are.
but still let's work through precisely
what the data structure looks like.
'cuz sometimes the recursive code looks
almost too simple and kind of mass
understanding.
So this is the representation of trie's,
that we started with.
and all we do with Ternary search trees
is it's, it's almost like having a binary
search tree representation of the
non-null links for every node.
so, in this case we're going to have an
ad, an s at the root, and that depends on
where your keys are inserted.
and the key idea is, the middle link
coming off the root node, is a link to
the TSTs that have all the keys that
start with S, with S stripped off.
now, but for the left and right links
those are for keys that start with some
letter that appears before S on the left,
and after S on the right.
and then say, on the left, the node for B
is, if you go down this link, it's all
the keys that start with B.
Otherwise the B is just to divide the
ones that are less, from the ones that
are bigger, and so forth.
and again, if you [COUGH] search for a
key by say, look search for SHE, so
that's going down middle links and
matching keys.
Then some nodes will have values
associated with them, that's the value
associated with the last letter, last
character in the search key.
So, that's what the data structure looks
like.
and I'd begin to describe the search
algorithm, it's quite simple given the
definition of the data structure.
Again, we follow links corresponding to
each character of a key.
If we have a character that's less than
the character in the node, we go left, if
we have one that's greater, we can go
right.
and if it's equal we move to the next
character, and take the middle link.
so this is an example of a search for a
SEA.
Start with S, that's a match, we take the
middle link.
Now the next character is E that's a
mismatch and E is less than 8, so we go
to the left.
now we find a note that has E, and we
didn't update our pointer into the key
character, because we didn't find a
match.
So, we're still looking at the E, and
now, now we can match that E, so we go
down the middle link.
Now we're looking at the A in the search
key, and that's less than L, so we go to
the left.
now we're still looking at the A in the
search key, and that's a match and it's
the last character in key, so, we return,
the value associated with the last
character in the key.
So, it's the same basic algorithm, that
we used for trie's except, we just have a
different way to decide whether we match
the character.
We explicitly store characters in nodes.
We follow middle link on a match, and
update the pointer in our key character.
Otherwise, we, we follow the left or
right link, because we know that the key
is going to be found in the left or right
sub-tree.
And each node has exactly three links.
So here's a example of search in a TST,
again this is the example I just talked
about in a dynamic form, form.
So, if S is the first character in the
key, matches the S in the first node of
tree, so we take the middle link, and
move on to the second character in the
key which is e.
Compare that against h, it's not a match
in fact it's less, so we go left.
So, now we're still looking at e and c,
and it's a match with the character in
the node that we're currently processing.
So, we take the middle, and now we move
to the next character in the key which is
a.
And now we take a compared to l, and a is
less, so we go left, we're still looking
at the a, didn't updated it, 'cuz it's
not a match, and now it is a match.
and it's the last character in the key,
so we look at the value, and that's the
value we return.
what about unsuccessful search?
well, let's see how that works.
So, for shelter, it starts with an S, so
we take the middle link, second, and move
to the second character.
Second character's an h, and that's a
match.
So, we take the middle link, and move to
the next character.
Third character's an e and third
character, and that, that's also a match.
So again, we take the middle link, and
move to the next character.
the fourth character's an l, that's also
a match.
So, again, we take the middle link, and
move to the next character.
Now the next character is a t, which is
not a match, so we want to move to the
right but moving to the right takes us to
a null link.
So that means that shelter is not in the
TST and, and so we return null.
Again, in every, in every step what we do
is completely well-defined.
and any search for a key that in the TST,
it's going to return it's associated
value.
Any search for any other key, is either
going to, go out on a null link, or end
on a node that involves a mismatch.
so, with that basic idea, let's take a
more detailed look in the demo, of how
the tree gets constructed.
and following through this demo, will
give you a pretty good feeling for how
these trees are constructed.
So, we're going to associate the value 0
with a string, SHE.
so, again every time we move to a new
letter, we have to create a new node,
until we get to the end of the key.
And at which case, we put the, associated
the value with the node that contains the
last character in the key.
so, that's the starting point.
key is a sequence of characters down the
middle links that [COUGH] goes to from
the root to some node.
And the value is in the node that
corresponds to the last character.
so, how do we put a new one in this tree
so the in this Ternary search trie.
Our first character is S, so we go down
the middle.
Our next character is not a match so
[COUGH] we go to the left, and it's a
null link but we have a node that we want
to put there.
That's the one corresponding to the
second letter, in sell's so we do that,
and then we make nodes with middle links,
going until we get to the last character
in sell's, and we associate that with the
value 1.
So, what about SEA, let's see how that
one works.
so, first character is S, so I take the
middle link, second character is e which
is less than h and not a match so we move
to the left and continue looking for the
e.
now this node we find the e, so we take a
middle link, and move to the next node
[COUGH] next character which is a, a is
less than l.
it's not a match so we go to the left,
that's a null linl, and that's where we
put our a, and we associate it with the
value 2.
OK, here's sh, shells so we have a match
at s, go to the middle link, and go to
the next letter, match h middle link next
letter.
and then we go down and add the three
nodes corresponding to the last three
letters and put a three at the node
corresponding to the last letter.
OK?
now B Y we look at S not a match it's
less, so we're going to go to the left,
that's a null link.
That's where we put our first character,
and then we go down the middle link to
add the node for the last character,and
then ah,associate the value for there.
and then B is a similar thing on the
right.
And then go for the t and h and e, and
that gets our share with the value 5.
SEA again, it's associative, so we do the
search, so S is a match.
So we go down the middle link, and move
to the next letter.
E is less than h so we go to left, and
keep looking for e.
Now we find e is a match, so we go down
the middle link, and move to the next
letter.
that's a, which is less than l, so we go
to the left to look for the a, and there
we find it.
and we're [COUGH] building an associate
symbol table, so we update and overwrite
the old value with the new value, 6.
S, H, O, R, E.
we match the S, match the h, now we're on
O, that does not match e, so we go to the
right, and keep looking for O.
Now, we don't find it, so we create a new
node for O, R, E, and then put the value
7 in the values associated with the last
character in that key.
so, that's the construction of a Ternary
search tree containing eight keys.
Let's take a look at a slightly bigger
Ternary search trie.
so here's our example with three letter
words.
now for that example, we didn't show all
the null links, but there's lots of null
links, 26 null links in each leaf for
this 26 way trie.
And there's other null links higher in
the tree, and actually counting up
there's over a thousand null links in
this tiny 26 way trie.
But in a TST, it's got about the same
number of nodes it's actually got more
nodes, because it's got one for each
character.
And the other ones correspond to links,
but not that many more nodes.
But the key thing is, it has many fewer
null links, because there's only three
links per node.
And this effect is obviously going to be
much more dramatic when R is much bigger.
like a 256 way trie or even a unicode
65,000 way trie.
that's the key benefit of TSTs, that and
they're much more space-efficient, then
our way trie's for large R.
so, let's take a look at the
implementation in Java, and then we'll
look at the code, and then we'll talk
some more about performance.
oh, the representation in Java is very
straightforward, as I said many of you
could code this up, just from the
description.
what does a node have to have?
It's going to have a value, it's going to
have a character.
it's going to have references to left,
middle, and right TSTs.
and that's what it's built from.
so whereas the standard trie
representation has a ray of links with
characters implicit.
TST has explicit characters with only
three links per node.
so that's TST representation and then
given the representation the code is
follows almost immediately.
with our standard setup if we're supposed
to, now we use, we call a recursive
routine, giving the root as first
argument.
And give the tree returned going to give
a reference that back to the root.
so our recursive routine takes a node and
returns a node and for most of the time,
it, it doesn't do much.
But when it can do node, is created this
this code is effective, because any link
we go down, we replace with a link that
we got back, our standard setup.
so, the recursive port routine if we're
that character d, we pull out the d
character.
if once we've done that, if our node is
null, we create a new node and give it
that character.
and now we test our character in our
search key, against the character in the
given node.
Either the one we just created, or the
one we happen to be on.
if if it's equal, it will fall through to
test if we are on the last key.
If we're not, if, if we're on the last
character in the key we just reset the
value.
if its equal and we're not on the last
character in the key, we go down the
middle link.
and we replace that link with what we get
by going down the middle link by moving
to the next character in the key.
otherwise, we go either down the left or
right link under the same circumstances,
without moving to the next character in
the key.
so that's extremely straightforward code
for put in Ternary search trie's.
and again, get is even simpler.
it's a similar set up that we've used
several times before.
Use a recursive routine that returns a
node, and we pull our value out of that
node.
we don't have to cast in this case, cause
we're not running arrays, and our nodes
just has the value type in it.
and if we get a null node back, yea, we
return null that its not there, the
recursive routine will pull out the
character if its less than our if our
search character is less we go to the
left.
And if its greater we go to the right,
and if its equal we and we're not at the
end of the key, we go down to the middle
and we move to the end of the key.
If its equal and we are at the end of the
key, we return the node.
And even that node, is going to contain a
value or it's not, but that's what we'e
return.
so, extremely straightforward
implementation of both get and put for
Ternary search drives.
so this, adds this line to our table,
where, the amount of space taken for
Ternary search trie's is just three
lengths you know, plus the value
character in each node.
so similar to what red-black BST and
hashes would use, so no space
disadvantage.
the determining the cost of search hits
and search miss, these values are given
for random keys, and they're the subject
of deep analysis.
but it's not too many.
Le, Let's, let's put it that way.
And our experimental results bear that
out.
So, for, for a search miss in a Ternary
search trie, you don't have to look at
the whole key.
Usually, you look at maybe fewer
characters than than the whole key, and
actually these results are, are for
typical, or random.
but actually TSD's really shine, in the
case where data is not random.
they very well adapt to the data.
like text written in English language, is
not really language really random.
And you can see that Ternary search trees
actually out perform both hashing and red
black BSTs for our benchmark, which is
deduping these big text files.
[COUGH] now you, you can go ahead and try
to get worst case guarantees.
By using rotations to balance the the the
internal binary search tree's
corresponding to each character in, in
TSTs.
although that's probably normally not
worth the trouble.
but the bottom line is that TST is at
least it's as fast as hashing for string
keys and it's it's space efficient for
sure.
And it's pretty easy to speed it up.
the idea is to speed it up, that works
extremely well in practice is to, use our
way of branching, at the be, at the top
of the TST.
so rather than fool around with the
first, couple of characters, simply do a
big branching at the root.
You can do r way branching at the root of
26, but in practice, it's pr, proven it
works fine to do, let's say, r squared
way branching at the root.
and immediately take care of the first
two characters, which is the common case,
and then get down to small TSTs.
and there's variations of this, that you
might imagine, but this is a really
simple one that almost always works.
you have to deal especially with one and
two letter words.
and we'll leave that for exercise.
but with that change now we get a, an
algorithm that's is definitely faster
than hashing in red-black BSTs for our
benchmarks.
and that'll turn out to be the case, for
many applications.
So, just to summarize what are the trade
offs between TSTs and hashing?
for hashing you have to examine the
entire key, in order to compute the hash
function.
we talked about examples, where people
try to skip doing that, and wind up with
performance problems.
Not much difference between a hit and a
miss in a hashing, and there's a lot of,
of reliance and maybe difficulty of
implementation ah,depending on the hash
function.
and also, hashing is really only good for
search and insert.
the other kinds of operations that we'd
like to perform in symbol table when
there's order in the keys is not
supported by hashing.
with TSTs, it only works for strings or
if you have keys that are numbers, then
you can rework them into strings, or
string like things.
And that's that's a restriction but does
cover a huge number of applications.
it, it only examines the key characters
that it needs to, and in particular, a
search miss might involve only a few
characters.
So, in typical applications you'll get
sub-linear performance in TSTs.
You can get searches done without looking
at the whole key.
the other thing is there's other, the
ordered symbol table operations you can,
you know easily support with TSTs.
just by extending, what we did for binary
search tree.
and even more important there's other
interesting operations that we can add
for string keys.
that are very useful, and we'll see
applications, and implementations of
these, in just a minute.
so the bottom line is that this data, is
a relatively new data structure.
but, its better than the classic ones for
important applications.
Its faster than hashing particular for
search misses.
and its got more flexibility even than
red black BSTs, and that's what we will
talk about soon, but that's an
introduction to TSTs.