So, the algorithm that we're going to look
at for solving the substring search
problem is called the Knuth-Morris-Pratt
algorithm.
It's got an interesting history that we'll
get to at the end.
But I just want to start by saying that.
This is one of the coolest algorithms that
we'll cover in this course.
And it's not an algorithm that anyone
would come up with without a lot of lotta
hard work.
But understanding this algorithm really
gives somebody an appreciation for what's
possible with careful algorithmic thinking
even for such a simple problem as this.
It's a quite ingenious method.
So, here's the intuition behind the
algorithm.
So, say, we're looking for the pattern.
B followed by a bunch of a's in the text.
So we're going along and so ahm well,
we're trying to mismatch right away so
we'll move over to first position.
And we'll go BAAAA, and then we find a
mismatch at the end in this case.
So now, what the, brute force method is
going to do is back up to move over one
position if b doesn't match the a, back up
again if b doesn't match the a, and keep
going matching the first b against all
these a's before getting to the next
character in the text.
So, we've matched five characters and we
mismatched on the sixth.
But the key point is that when we got that
mismatch all we have is A's and B's.
We already matched BAAAA, four A's and we
got a mismatch so it's AB..
So, at that point we know what the
previous characters in the text are, and
we know that if we move over one position,
we're going to be trying to match B
against A.
So we should be able to take advantage of
that knowledge, that's the intuition on
the method of the Knuth-Morris-Pratt.
We don't need to back up the text pointer
in this case.
When we get the mismatch, we can just keep
going.
We don't even have to match the first b we
know it's there So,
We can just keep going in the text pointer
and start in the second pattern pointer.
The Knuth-Morris-Pratt algorithm is a very
clever method that manages to always avoid
backup no matter what the pattern is.
So, let's take a look at what's involved.
It's based on the idea of building a
deterministic finite state machine for
string searching.
Now, the deterministic finite state
machine, if you're not familiar or don't
remember, it's a very simple thing.
You've got a finite number of states.
It's always in one of the states.
There's a start state and a, and a halt
state.
And from every state, there's exactly one
transition for each possible character in
the alphabet.
So we're, if we're in a state and we're
reading a particular character we move to
the state that is indicated by that
character.
So, if we're in state two and we're
reading an A, we move to state three,
that's what this line in the table says.
If we're in state two and we read A, that
happens to be the pattern character is a,
and if we see and A, we move to state
three.
If we see AB or AC,c we go back to state
zero.
That's what this machine says. It says,
the tabular representation and the
graphical representation.
If we get to stage six then we just say,
except we found the pattern and you could
see how that is, the pattern and then if
we match the pattern character, we move
right through this machine till we get to
the halt state.
So, let's first take a look at exactly how
the machine works to make sure that
everybody follows that.
And then we'll look at how to rebuild this
machine.
So that's our machine and that's our text
up at the top.
So, we start at state zero we're reading
in a.
What are we supposed to do if we're in
state zero and we're reading an A?
This enter the table and says, we're
supposed to go to state one.
So, we go to state one.
Every, at every step, we consume a text
character.
A.
And in the graphical representation, it
says, stay in state one.
Or in this representation, it says, if
you're in state one and you see an a, stay
in state one.
So that's what we'll do.
We'll read the a and stay in state one.
Now, we're in state one and so you can say
that in, in state one is reading a's and
in a way, looking for something that's not
A,
No matter how many a's you have, you'll
read them right here in state one.
So now, we're in state one and we're
reading a B and it says, go to state two
in that case.
So, that's where we'll go, read the B.
Now, we're in state two and reading an A,
So we go to state three and read the A.
Now, we're in state three and see a C.
In state three, when we see a C we're
supposed to go back to state zero.
That's a mismatch our pattern sees not
until the end.
So now, we have to start the search all
over again.
Although in the final state machine does
not know that, it's just plotting along
according to the state transitions they're
supposed to do.
So, we read the C, C, now we're back in
state zero.
So now, we're in state zero looking at an
a.
And we move to one, and read the A.
And then we see another A so we stay in
one and read the A.
And now we see a B, and we go to state
two, and read the B. And then we go to
state three and read the A, state three
and read the A.
State four and read the A.
State five and read the C.
And now, we're in state six.
And that means we found the pattern.
So, that's the simulation of what the
deterministic finite state be. that is
corresponding to this pattern would do.
And as we'll see the code for implementing
this simulation is quite simple.
That's a demo of DFA simulation.
So let's just take a quick look at what
the interpretation of what this DFA is.
So, what is it, what does it mean after we
just read the ith character of the text?
Well the number of the state is the number
of characters in the pattern that we've
matched up to the current point.
So, that is it.
At state three, we've matched three
characters in the pattern.
And what's happened is, that we've matched
a prefix of a pattern, the first three
characters of the pattern.
It's, and actually, it's the longest
prefix of the pattern that's also a suffix
of the i, first i plus one characters from
the text,
Text from zero to i.
That's the interpretation of what it is.
So and if the DFA is in state three after
the first six characters of the text it's
got ABA is the longest prefix of a
pattern.
That's also a suffix of first six
characters of the text.
So, another prefix of the pattern that
looks like it might work is ABABA but
that's not a suffix of the text string
ending at character six.
And third, interpretation is useful to
understanding what's going on.
So given that we've constructed this DFA.
It's just the state transition table for
the DFA is simply a two-dimensional array.
That's indexed by the pattern character.
So, if, if you in a, a certain, if you're
reading a certain pattern character sorry,
if you're reading a certain text character
then for each we reset the pattern pointer
to be the entry given in the table that
corresponds to the current one.
So let's go back to the table to be sure
about that.
So when we're in a particular state like
two and we see an a we read, so this would
be j we refer to that column.
And whatever text character we happen to
see, that's how we update j.
So that's what this code does.
And then, if we ever to get to the
transition state, the final state, we just
return i minus m. Now, this is just like
that alternate implementation of the brute
force method that we gave.
But the key idea is that,
Notice that i never gets decremented.
All we're doing is incrementing i and
changing j.
Either always just referring to the table.
When we have a match, the table
automatically increments j.
We have a mismatch, it figures out the
right state to go to.
So, that's a very simple and economical
and fast implementation of substring
search.
So the running time is clearly, all it
does it look up an entry in the table for
every text character.
So, that's linear time.
The key is, is.
How do we build that table that drives the
algorithm?
And that's the tricky algorithm.
So a warning.
This is definitely the trickiest algorithm
we've looked at so far.
And the idea, the importance, again, of no
backup is that since the text pointer
never decrements, you could use the input
stream and just replace text [UNKNOWN]
just read the next character in the next
input stream.
And this algorithm is going to work fine,
no matter how big the input stream is.
It will just go right, right through.
Its not no memory of what the text is.
But its got some memory of what the
pattern is that's built into the DFA.
So, this is the key that, you have a
pattern,
You can spend some time building this DFA
table and doing pre-processing.
But then, when you get the text, just,
just index into this table for every text
character and you're doing this substring
search.
So, you can build a machine that does
this.
No backup.
Okay.
So let's take a look at what it means to
construct this DFA.
So it depends on the pattern instead of
with one character one state for each
character in the pattern plus an extra at
substate.
And let's look at what it means to build
the same.
So first thing now we do to one character
one stage for each character in the
pattern.
So the first thing we do is deal with the
match transitions.
So, that's when the you've, you're in
state j,
That means you've already matched j
characters in a pattern.
Then if, if the next character matches.
So that the character that you have is
the, the character that's supposed to
match.
You're going to so it's, add that
character j, that's just a j plus first
character,
Then you know that you've matched j plus
one characters.
So, all that means is we can put in the
match transitions.
So, we have ABABAC, and these guys go
ABABAC if you're in state zero and you see
an A you go to state one, if you're state
one and you see a B, you go to state two
and so forth.
That's how we get the match transitions to
get us all the way through the pattern to
the accept state.
So that's the, the easy part.
And then the hard part is the mismatch
transitions.
What are you supposed to do if you come
against a text character that does not
match the current text character?
So, for example, if you're in state zero,
the pattern starts with an A.
If you didn't see if you don't see an A as
the first character in the text,
If you see a B or a C, then obviously you
want to stay in state zero.
So, you can think of state zero as,
scanning through the text looking for an
A.
It's going to stay in, in state zero as
long as it sees a B or C as soon as it
sees an A, it'll go to state one.
That completes state zero, you know what
to do if you have a, an A, you know what
to do if you have a B or a C.
What about state one?
So, we know that if you're in state one,
you saw an A in the text, and you see a B
in the text, what are you supposed to do?
Well there's two different cases.
If you,
If you see a B going to state two if you
see a C and that's not going to match the
first character A in the pattern.
So, you go back to state zero.
But if you see an A, it's just as if you
saw an A, a in state zero,
So, you might as well stay in state one.
So, that's how we fill in the DFA for
state one,
If you see a B going state two, you
matched.
If you see an A, well that matches the
first character.
So, stay in state one.
If you see a C, clearly you have to go
back to state zero.
Okay, what about the next one?
So if we're in state two and we see an A
we know that we go on to state three.
And what about the mismatch pages?
Well, in that case, it's a B or C and
again if you're sitting out a B or a c, C
you'd better go back to state zero to keep
looking for an a.
This is state three, and well, now it gets
to be a little more complicated.
C, you state three, see a B, you
succeeded, if you see a C, you go back to
state zero.
It's not so bad if you see an A, it's just
like before.
That's going to be like the first one.
So seems like we're going along pretty
fine.
And again if we're in state four, we seen
A, you go to five.
If you see a B or a C, then you better go
back and look for an A again.
This one, is the one that's a little more
complicated.
If you're in state five and you see a B
you, you go back to state four.
And that's it's a little more work to
figure out why that's the case.
And then that last case is kind of the
essence of the algorithm.
So we'll look at a systematic way to be
able to figure out what you do on a
mismatch in each case.
In this case, you only needed that, that
for that one state.
Otherwise, it was elementary reasoning.
So that's a full DFA for KnuthMorrisPratt.
A demo of at least thinking about how it's
going to be constructed.
Okay, let's look a little more carefully
and systematically at the construction
process for the KnuthMorrisPratt DFA.
So the, the start is clear.
We're going to go through the pattern.
And for systematically fill in the match
transitions.
If we're in state zero and we see an A, we
want to go state one.
If we're in state one and we see a B,
we're going to, we want to go to state
two.
State two, so we look up the pattern
character and then, whatever that one is,
we want to go to the next state.
So, we can fill in at least that much
automatically.
Now the real key is the mismatch
transition.
So, here is the idea of the mismatched
So if you're in stage J and you get a
mismatch, the next character in the text
does not match the jth character in the
pattern.
So as pointed out at the beginning as
motivation for KnuthMorrisPratt,
You know a lot about the text at that
point.
And you know that the last j, j minus one
characters of the text are if you lop off
the first character of the pattern, it's
from one to j minus one. So, in this case
and then, it's followed by the text
character that, that you're looking at.
So one thing that you could do, so what
you want to do, so you know that.
And what you could do is simulate the DFA
that you have built on that part of the
pattern and then take the transition for
the character that you just find.
So, let's, let's look at this.
So let's run this machine, if we'd seen it
on the text of, of BABA,.
What we want to do,
We want to put the machine in the state as
if we have backed up, but we don't want to
backup. So, if we see a B, we stay in
zero, if we see an we, we go to one.
Then we see a B we go two.
And if we see an A, we go to three.
So now we're in state three in if we had a
mismatch then the, for the fifth
character, what we do on a, on a mismatch
here we have to look what happens if we
get an A or we get a B.
If we'd run it on BABA and we get an A,
then we should go back to one.
So, what that says is, if we had a
mismatch and we saw an A in five we would
need to be in state one.
Because if we had, had run the thing on
the characters that we know, BABAA, we
would wind up in state one.
And similarly if we were if we got the
mismatch on a B,
A if we did BABA,, we would be in state
three.
And, we're in state three and we saw B
we'd go to four.
So again to summarize, if four instate
five and we see a C, we know that's a
match, we go to six.
If we see an A, we know that the previous
five characters in the text were BABAA.
So, we can just simulate the machine.
Babaa, we're in state one.
And ifwe get a mismatch that's a B, then
that's DFAB five,
Then we know that the previous five
characters in the text were BABAB. And
that would put us in state four.
So that's the simulation of BABA puts us
in state three.
If we get an A, we go to one.
So that means that from five, we go back
to one.
And if we get a B, we go to four.
So, that's how, one way to calculate the
mismatched transitions.
And as we've noted in the simulation, this
is the only non-trivial one for this
example.
Now, there's a little problem with that,
Is that it seems to require j steps to do
the simulation.
In order to figure out these mismatched
transitions, I had to all the way through
the pattern shifted over one to figure out
this state three.
So that seems to be a bit of a problem,
but actually it's no problem at all,
because we can run this simulation one
character at a time as we're building the
machine.
All we need to do is keep track of the
that we would be at if we had run the DFA
on the pattern starting at position one.
Once, once we get going it's pretty easy
but just let's start well, let's just
illustrate it by saying, okay,
We maintain this state x,
Which is where we would be if we if we had
run the machine and the pattern had
shifted over one.
Now when we come to do our mismatches to
figure out where the mismatch transitions
from five are all we do is look at if we
get, if we were to get an A, would be as
if we were to state X and got an A.
So that's one and if we were to get a B
it's as if we were at state X and got a B.
And that's state four.
So, what we need to do is to compute the
mismatch transitions is keep track of
state x.
And that is where would the thing be if we
had run it starting with the, at the
pattern one position shifted over.
And we want to update that.
So, when we're moving to the next state,
if we had a match on C, state x gets
updated to where it would have gone if it
got a C.
Because for the next character, when we
move j over for the match on C we'll want
to have x updated.
So, that's the key is keeping track of the
state where the machine would be if we had
backed up or if we had run it on the
pattern shifted over one.
So let's take a look at a demo that does
the full construction for the KMP DFA.
So here, here goes.
Again, one state for every character plus
an accept.
Match transitions are easy.
We build those.
And we're going to start at position zero.
And the mismatched transitions are easy.
So now, when we move over x is when we're
in position one of the pattern, x is where
we would be if we started out without
that, that character,
Which would be the empty string.
So we start out with just filling in
zeros.
For state zero and we can do that without
any further every reason and now we've got
x initialized. so now, what we need to do
is fill in the mismatch transitions for
state one.
So, what are they?
They're what would happen if we found
those characters?
And, and we're in state x,
If we found an A, we would go to state
one.
If we found a C, we'd go to state zero.
And maybe you noticed, that's just taking
the entries corresponding to the entries
we need from x's column and putting them
in j's column.
That's all it is.
And then, we need to update x, which is
where it would be if we matched a B.
So, well stay and x will stay in state
zero.
So now let's look at state two.
So we need to fill in what would happen if
we got a B and what would happen if got a
C.
Well, it's what would happen if we were in
state x and we got a B or a C,
So what we'll do is move those two zeroes
over to column two.
And then don't forget we have to update x
and x goes where the machine goes if we
saw an A, that transitions from two to the
three.
So, we just move x to state one.
So now, we have x in state one, and we're
doing position three and now you can see
how really simple the algorithm is once it
gets going.
So now the mismatched transitions are A
and C, and that's what we have to fill for
column but those mismatched transitions
were already computed that's where x would
go if we, that's where it would go if we
happen to be in state one.
So, we move the one and zero from column
one over to column three.
And again, we update x and when we see a B
x goes to state two.
And, and again, you can check what, what
is x suppose to be.
It's, it's suppose to be where you would
be if you started the machine on the
pattern with the first letter cut off.
So, it's, it's suppose to be where would
you wind up if you got BAB, BAB and that's
a check.
Alright, so now it's straightforward,
straightforward we have to fill in B and
C.
We go to x's column and copy over B and C
from x's column.
Then we update x.
That's if you see an A, you go to state
three.
Now we're ready for state five.
We've got x all computed and we need to do
A and B.
And we get those from X.
If it's an A it's a one.
And if it's a B it's a four.
It's just moved them over.
And then when we do the C and get the
accept there's no mismatch.
That's the we do update x to get ready.
But when we get to state six we're done.
And again, it's just as a doublecheck, x
is where you'd be if you saw BABAC.bac
That's the construction of the
Knuth-Morris-Pratt DFA efficient
algorithm.
Really ingenious and as it turns out,
simple to implement.
Implementation for the DFA construction
for Knuth-Morris-Pratt requires remarkably
little code so it just goes through with
what we did in the demo.
So we've got x and for every entry of the
DFA and x's column that corresponds to
everyone except for the match we just copy
x's column to j's column.
In fact, we just copy'em all, and then
overwrite one corresponding to the match
case, to j plus one.
So there. And the entry in the column that
corresponds to the pattern character,
that's where do we go if we match, that's
j plus one, all the rest of them are
copied from x.
So, one forwarded the copy from x then set
the match case and the only other thing to
do is update x.
And how do you update x?
You take the [unknown] machine to where it
would go if it were at state x and I got
the current x pattern, pattern character.
So that's the, DFA construction amazingly
a line of code.
So the only, so flaw in this codec, is
that it does take time proportional to R
times M where are R is the radix and, and
M is the length of the pattern and, and as
we'll see this, ways to, get around this.
But for relatively small alphabets this is
no problem because the search is so
efficient this way and the construction as
well.
But if you're doing this for Unicode for a
long pattern maybe that's too much memory
to devote to the DFA representation.
So the bottom line is and this follows
immediately from examining the code is
that the substrings can be substring
search as linear time.
Your only access at most, each character
in the pattern, each character in the
texts wants quite remarkable.
Each pattern character you have accessed
once when your making the DN, DFA.
And each text character is accessed once
when you're simulating the DFA, and that's
in the worst case.
Now the space again, is proportional to RM
because we have all those mismatches.
It is possible to develop a version of
Knuth-Morris-Pratt that constructs the
automaton in time and space proportional
to M.
It's actually a non-deterministic
automaton cuz it's either a match or all
mismatches and mismatch might involve
multiple hops.
So if you are interested you can read
about that version of KMP.
But it's sufficiently more complicated
that you should be, be prepared to study
it carefully to really understand it.
This algorithm is really interesting
because of its history.
It was actually independently discovered
by two theoreticians and a hacker.
So there's Knuth who was one of the
fathers of computer science.
Who read a paper that was a very esot by
Steve Cook, a very esoteric theoretical
result that he realized implied that it
should be possible to solve the substring
search problem in linear time.
The theorem really didn't give any way to
solve it but it indicated that it should
be possible to solve it in linear time.
So, Knuth worked on it and figured out a
way.
And then Pratt who was a student of
Knuth's at Stanford at the time figured
out a way to take care of this mismatch,
independent of the alphabet side.
And in the meantime, across the Bay at
Berkeley Jim Morris was busy writing a
text editor.
In those days people were using
typewriters.
And other people were realizing that
computers would be really good at editing
text.
And so you know,
Many people would work on text editing and
formatting systems.
Ahm it was kind of a badge of honor in
those times.
Morris actually worked for the computer
center at Berkeley.
And wanted to have a really bolt-proof
text editor that everyone could use.
And one of the things he wanted to do was
avoid backup.
Cuz backup was just really inconvenient,
Involved a lot of code.
And just something that he didn't want to
have.
And he basically came up with the same
algorithm and the community was kind of
small at that time.
And theory meets practice.
And that's where this paper came from
1977.
Morris, then went on to get his PHD, and
to work at Xerox Parc.
And unfortunately later on another systems
programmer came and took a look at
Morris's code and couldn't understand it,
and put the brute force algorithm back in.
But that part of the story is maybe a less
successful example of theory meeting
practice.
That's Knuth-Morris-Pratt algorithm, one
of the most ingenious algorithms that
we'll see.